<TEI>
<text>

    <body>
        <div>


<pb n="3"/>
<head>PART V: 
THE FALL AND RESTORATION TO FAVOUR
OF BUZURJMIHR, AND THE WISDOM OF
NUSHIRWAN</head>

<div>
<head>ARGUMENT</head>

<p>Buzurjmihr, while in attendance upon the Shah during a hunting-expedition, has a premonition of coming trouble and immediately afterwards falls under the Shah’s displeasure, and is disgraced. Conscious of his own rectitude he refuses to own that he is in fault and is treated with increasing rigour till the Shah has need of his services to expound a problem proposed by Caesar, but with his sight greatly impaired by his sufferings.</p>

<p>The rest of the Part is taken up with an account of the wisdom of Nushirwan as shown in his replies to questioners and in his letter of advice to his son Hurmuzd.</p>
</div><div>
<head>NOTE</head>

<p>§2. We have other instances of such problems and “hard questions.” See Vol. vii, p. 5.</p>

<p>§§ 3. and 5. On Persian Wisdom-literature see Vol. vii., p. 278 seq.</p>

<p>§4. It is manifest from the account in the Shahnama, and it is probably true historically, that Nushirwan did his best to provide himself with a worthy successor.<note n="1">Cf. NT. p. 252 and note.</note> In addition to this letter of counsel we have in Part VI. the account of the examination that his son Hurmuzd had to pass,<note n="2">p. 57.</note> and some final exhortations.<note n="3">p. 61.</note> Unfortunately</p>

<quote>
    <l>The best laid schemes o’ mice an’ men</l>
    <l>Gang aft a-gley.</l>
</quote>
</div>

<div><pb n="4"/>
    <head>§1
        How Nishirwan was wroth with Buzurjmihr and ordered him to be put in Ward</head>
    <p>
    <lb/>Consider now the case of Buzurjmihr,
    <lb/>Who from the dust rose to the circling sphere,
    <lb/>Which will exalt one to the clouds on high,
    <lb/>Then bring him down in sorry dust to lie <note n="1">Two couplets omitted.</note>
    </p><p>
    <lb/>It happened in those days that Nushirwan
    <lb/>Went forth from Mada’in to hunt. He chased
    <lb/>Along the wilderness the mountain-sheep
    <lb/>And the gazelles. The mountain-sheep dispersed.
    <lb/>The Shah was left behind with Buzurjmihr,
    <lb/>Who followed both from duty and from love.
    <lb/>Then from the waste the monarch reached a meadow,
    <lb/>And saw trees, grass, and shade. The weary Shah
    <lb/>Alighted from his steed to rest his eyes
    <lb/>Upon the grass. He saw no followers ;
    <lb/>The one of goodly face remained, no more.
    <lb/>The Shah reposed awhile upon the mead,
    <lb/>His head right lovingly upon the lap
    <lb/>Of Buzurjmihr. It was that wise king’s wont
    <lb/>To wear a jewelled armlet. As it chanced
    <lb/>This clinging armlet snapped upon his arm,
    <lb/>And fell beside his couch. A sable bird
    <lb/>Swooped from the clouds to where he lay, looked round,
    </p><p>
    <lb/>Beheld that armlet, brake the thread whereon
    <lb/>The gems were strung, then ate them each in turn,
    <lb/>The lustrous pearls and topazes alike,
    <lb/>Flew from the monarch’s couch, and disappeared.
    <lb/>At that adventure Buzurjmihr aghast
    <lb/>Mused at the process of the turning sky.
    </p><p>
    <pb n="5"/>
    </p><p>
    <lb/>He understood: “My fall, my day of wrath,
    <lb/>My season of dismay, are hard at hand!”
    </p><p>
    <lb/>The Shah awoke, marked how he bit his lips,
    <lb/>Scanned his own arm, beheld the jewels gone,
    <lb/>And seeing no one of his escort there<note n="2">Couplet inserted from P.</note>
    <lb/>Conceived that while he slumbered Buzurjmihr<note n="3">Reading with P.</note>
    <lb/>Had gulped the armlet down, and said to him:—
    <lb/>“Thou dog! who said to thee: ‘’Tis possible
    <lb/>To hide one’s natural bent?’”<note n="4">Couplet omitted.</note>
    </p><p>
    <lb/>But Nushirwan
    </p><p>
    <lb/>Fatigued with many words his tongue in vain;
    <lb/>He got no answer but a deep, cold sigh,
    <lb/>While Buzurjmihr stood withered by the Shah,
    <lb/>And by the process of revolving heaven.
    <lb/>That wise man marked at once the ominous sign
    <lb/>Of downfall and remained struck dumb by fear.
    <lb/>The escort of the Shah had gone about
    <lb/>The mead while Nushirwan was in its midst.
    <lb/>He mounted on his charger’s back in wrath,
    <lb/>And noticed no one on his journey home,
    <lb/>But bit his lip at Buzurjmihr the while,
    <lb/>And muttering much alighted from his steed,
    <lb/>Bade smite the sage’s face as ’twere an anvil,
    <lb/>And to imprison him in his own palace.
    <lb/>So Buzurjmihr abode there and beheld
    <lb/>A frowning sky. He had a kinsman, brave
    <lb/>And young, attending on Shah Nushirwan
    <lb/>Within the palace day and night on terms
    <lb/>Of intimacy. Buzurjmihr one day
    <lb/>Asked that dependant of the sun-faced Shah:—
    <lb/>“How dost thou wait upon him? Let me know
    <lb/>So that thou mayest be more serviceable.”
    </p><p>
    <lb/>“Chief of archmages!” said the servitor,
    <lb/>“It chanced this very day that Nushirwan
    </p><p>
    <milestone unit="caled" n="1752"/>
    <pb n="6"/>
    </p><p>
    <lb/>Looked so on me, his bondslave, that I said:—
    <lb/>‘There is an end for me of food and sleep!’
    <lb/>I poured the water for him after meat,
    <lb/>Transgressing with the basin in the act,
    <lb/>And when the world-lord was offended at me
    <lb/>I let the basin fall.’ _
    <lb/>Then said the sage:—
    <lb/>‘Arise! Fetch hither water and pour out
    <lb/>As thou wouldst pour it o’er the Shah's own hands.”
    <lb/>The young man brought warm water which he poured
    <lb/>Upon the sage’s hands with gentleness,
    <lb/>Who said: “Pour thus when he requireth it,
    <lb/>Avoiding any awkwardness, and when
    <lb/>The water shall perfume the basin’s brim
    <lb/>Forbear to pour.”
    <lb/>The servitor took heed,
    <lb/>And on the next occasion, when he brought
    <lb/>The salver, poured the water as the sage
    <lb/>Enjoined with neither tardiness nor haste.
    <lb/>“O thou whose love increaseth!” said the Shah,
    <lb/>“Who told thee this?”
    <lb/>He answered: “Buzurjmihr,
    <lb/>For he it was that taught to me the mode
    <lb/>Marked by the Shah, the master of the world.”
    <lb/>The Shah said: ‘‘Go and say thus to the sage:—
    <lb/>‘With all that high estate of thine and lustre
    <lb/>Why didst thou seek the worse and not the better
    <lb/>Through thine ill nature and misgovernance?’”
    <lb/>The attendant heard and coming quickly sought
    <lb/>The palace eagerly with stricken soul,
    <lb/>Gave Buzurjmihr the message of the Shah,
    <lb/>And privily received this answer back:—
    <milestone unit="caled" n="1753"/>
    <lb/>"My station both in public and in private
    <lb/>Far bettereth the monarch of the world’s.”
    </p><p>
    <pb n="7"/>
    </p><p>
    <lb/>The servitor returned with this response,
    <lb/>But counted as he went the grains of dust.
    <lb/>The answer made the Shah exceeding wroth.
    <lb/>He had the sage bound in a dismal dungeon,
    <lb/>And asked the servitor the second time:—
    <lb/>“How beareth that insensate one his lot?”
    </p><p>
    <lb/>The messenger came with a tearful face,
    </p><p>
    <lb/>And told the words to Buzurjmihr who thus
    <lb/>Made answer to that faithful friend of his:—
    <lb/>“My days are passed more lightly than the Shah’s.”
    </p><p>
    <lb/>The messenger turned back, came like the wind,
    <lb/>And told the Shah that answer, which enraged him;
    <lb/>He was as ’twere a pard and bade to make
    <lb/>A narrow iron cage, then studded it
    <lb/>With spikes and nails inside, and set thereon
    <lb/>Withal an iron lid. Thus Buzurjmihr
    <lb/>Could neither rest by day nor sleep by night.
    <lb/>Thus for the fourth time to the servitor
    <lb/>The Shah said: “Take this message and bring back
    <lb/>His answer. Say to him: ‘How far’st thou now,
    <lb/>Environed as thou art by piercing nails?’”
    </p><p>
    <lb/>The attendant came and gave the message sent
    <lb/>By that imperious prince. Thus Buzurjmihr
    <lb/>Made answer to the youth: ‘‘My days are better
    <lb/>Than those of Nushirwan.”
    </p><p>
    <lb/>Now when the man
    <lb/>Returned with this reply the Shah’s face grew
    <lb/>All livid at the words. Out of the palace
    <lb/>He chose a truthful man and capable
    <lb/>Of comprehending what the sage should say,
    <lb/>Dispatched too with the messenger a swordsman,
    <lb/>Who acted as the executioner,
    <lb/>And said: “Go to this bad, ill-fortuned man,
    <lb/>And say: ‘If thy reply give pleasure, well;
    <lb/>If not the deathsman with his trenchant sword
    <lb/>Shall show thee Doomsday in that thou hast said
    </p><p>
    <pb n="8"/>
    <lb/>That jail and nails and cage, and pit and bonds
    <lb/>Are better than the throne of Nushirwan.’”
    <lb/>The envoy came apace to him and told
    <lb/>The words of Nushirwan. Said Buzurjmihr
    <lb/>To that good envoy: “Fortune ne’er hath shown us
    <lb/>Its face. None of us is exempt from change,
    <lb/>And verily all good and ill will end.
    <lb/>Enthroned and rich or grievously oppressed,
    <lb/>We have no choice, we all must pack and part.
    <lb/>To pass from durance is an easy thing;
    <lb/>The quaking is for them that wear the crown.”
    <lb/>That wise man and the executioner
    <lb/>Returned and, coming to the exalted Shah,
    <lb/>Narrated everything that they had heard.
    <lb/>The fear of evil fortune came upon him.
    <lb/>They bore that righteous guide from that strait cage
    <lb/>Back to his palace with the Shah’s consent,
    <milestone unit="caled" n="1754"/>
    <lb/>And heaven turned awhile with matters thus,
    <lb/>While wrinkles filled the face of Buzurjmihr,
    <lb/>His heart grew more oppressed and worn, and both
    <lb/>His eyes were darkened by anxiety,
    <lb/>While since his travailing surpassed his gain
    <lb/>He wasted with his care and pined with pain.</p>
    
</div>

<div><head>§ 2
    How the Ambassador of Caesar came to Nushirwan with a locked Casket and how Buzurjmihr was set at large to declare its Contents</head>
<p>
<lb/><pb n="9"/>Now in those days it chanced that Caesar sent
<lb/>An envoy with a letter to the Shah,
<lb/>With gifts, with presents, and a padlocked casket,
</p>
<p>
<lb/>And said: “O king of warriors and chiefs!
<lb/>Thou hast no lack of holy archimages,
</p>
<p>
<lb/>So let them tell, not tampering with the lock,
<lb/>What is concealed therein. If they say right
<lb/>We will send tribute and our wonted gifts;
<lb/>But if thy clever archimages’ hearts

<lb/>Fail in this knowledge indispensable
<lb/>The Shah must not ask tribute at our hands,
<lb/>Nor send an army to invade our realm.
</p>
<p>
<lb/>Such is the message that hath come from Caesar:
<lb/>Make answer as it seemeth good to thee.”
</p>
<p>
<lb/>The monarch of the world said to the envoy:—
<lb/>“This thing is not a mystery to God,

<lb/>And by His Grace divine I will achieve it,
<lb/>Convoking holy men to give me aid.
<lb/>Abide here for a se’nnight, cheered with wine,
<lb/>Make merry in thy heart and be at ease.”
</p>
<p>
<lb/>The matter proved perplexing to the Shah:
<lb/>He called to him the great men and the wise,
<lb/>Who all examined it in every way
<lb/>To find a means whereby to loose that coil,
<lb/>Examined, as did all the archimages,

<lb/>That casket and that lock whose key was lacking,
<lb/>But could not tell and owned their ignorance.
<lb/>Now when that concourse proved of no avail

<lb/>The heart of Nushirwan, the Shah, was grieved.
<lb/>He said: “The intellect of Buzurjmihr

<lb/>Will search this secret of the turning sky.”
</p><p>
<lb/>The king of kings, in sore embarrassment,
<lb/>Gave orders to his treasurer to provide
<lb/>A change of raiment from the treasury,

<lb/>And had a choice steed saddled royal wise.
</p><p>
<lb/>He sent them to the sage. “‘Thou must forget,”
<lb/>He said, “the hardships that thou hast endured
<lb/>Because high heaven above us so ordained

<lb/>That thou shouldst have affliction at our hands.
<lb/><pb n="10"/>
<lb/><milestone unit="caled" n="1755"/>
<lb/>Thy tongue excited my displeasure: thou
<lb/>Hast been the author of thine own oppression.
<lb/>I am confronted with a thankless task,
<lb/>The elders’ hearts have been perplexed thereby,
<lb/>For Caesar hath dispatched to us from Rum
<lb/>A famed priest of that land and therewithal
<lb/>A casket with a tightly fastened lid
<lb/>Padlocked and sealed with musk. The envoy saith:—
<lb/>‘Thus said my lord: “Reveal this hidden thing,
<lb/>And let the sages and the princes say
<lb/>What lieth in this casket.” So methought:—
<lb/>‘No one will see through this veiled mystery
<lb/>Unless it be the soul of Buzurjmihr.’”
<lb/>When Buzurjmihr had listened to those words
<lb/>His pain and former trouble were renewed;
<lb/>He left the prison, bathed his head and body,
<lb/>And first approached in prayer the Lord of all.
<lb/>Albeit innocent himself he feared
<lb/>The Shah, the wrathful world-lord’s, tyranny.
<lb/>He watched that day and night alike and pondered -
<lb/>According to the message of his master.
<lb/>What time the sun was brilliant in the heavens
<lb/>He mused upon the aspects of the stars,<note>Couplet omitted and reading with P.</note>
<lb/>He laved his heart’s eyes in the stream of wisdom,
<lb/>Chose out a trusty man among the sages,
<lb/>And said to him: “My market hath been spoiled,
<lb/>My vision ruined by my sufferings.
<lb/>Observe upon the road the passers by,
<lb/>Address them, have no fear, and ask their names.”
<lb/>Forth from his house went Bazurjmihr and met
<lb/>A woman hasting, beautiful of face.
<lb/>That wise man vigilant informed the sage
<lb/>Of all things that were hidden from his eyes,
<lb/>And he as feeling for his way rejoined:—
<pb n="11"/>
<lb/>“Ask if this Moon be wedded.”
<lb/>Said the lady:—
<lb/>“I have a spouse and child withal at home.”
</p>
<p>
    <lb/>The sage on his white roadster, when he heard
    <lb/>Her answer, started. Then another woman
    <lb/>Appeared and, seeing her, his agent asked:—
    </p><p>
    <lb/>“O woman, hast thou got a child and spouse,
    <lb/>Or, being single, only wind in hand?”
    </p><p>
    <lb/>“I have a husband if no child,” she said,
    </p><p>
    <lb/>“Thou hast mine answer, suffer me to pass.”
    </p><p>
    <lb/>Just then another woman came—the third.
    </p><p>
    <lb/>Her too the friend approached. “My Fair!” said he,
    <lb/>“What mate hast thou who hast such goodly carriage
    <lb/>And daintiness?”
    <lb/>“I never had a husband,”
    <lb/>She said, “I would not one should see my face.”
    </p><p>
    <lb/>Now mark the inference of Buzurjmihr
    <lb/>On hearing these replies. He hurried on
    <milestone unit="caled" n="1750"/>
    <lb/>With anxious mien. They brought him to the Shah,
    <lb/>Who ordered that he should approach the throne,
    <lb/>But was exceeding troubled in his heart
    <lb/>Because he missed the sage’s piercing glance,
    </p><p>
    <lb/>And heaved full many a deep and chilling sigh,
    <lb/>Excused himself for having wronged the guiltless,
    <lb/>Then talked of Caesar and of Rum, and spake
    <lb/>Of casket and of padlock. Buzurjmihr
    </p><p>
    <lb/>Made answer to the monarch of the world:—
    <lb/>“Be lustre thine so long as heaven shall turn.
    <lb/>Now must we hold a session of the wise,
    </p><p>
    <lb/>Of Caesar’s envoy, and the archimages,
    </p><p>
    <lb/>And have the casket laid before the Shah,
    <lb/>Before the Great, the seekers of the way;
    <lb/>Then in God’s strength, who gave me intellect,
    <lb/>And made the right the business of my soul,
    </p><p>
    <lb/>I will declare the casket’s whole contents,
    <lb/><pb n="12"/>
    <lb/>And lay no hand on it or on its lock.
    </p><p>
    <lb/>Although mine eyes be dim my heart is bright;
    </p><p>
    <lb/>The breastplate of my soul withal is knowledge.”
    <lb/>The king joyed at the words. His heart grew fresh
    <lb/>As roses in the Spring. Anxiety
    </p><p>
    <lb/>Bent him no longer, and he called for envoy
    <lb/>And casket, summoned all the archimages
    <lb/>And mighty men, and seated many a sage
    <lb/>With Buzurjmihr, then told the ambassador:—
    </p><p>
    <lb/>“Repeat thy message and demand an answer.”
    <lb/>The Ruman, hearing, loosed his tongue and thus
    </p><p>
    <lb/>Told Caesar’s words: “From the victorious world-lord
    <lb/>We look for wisdom, knowledge, and renown,
    <lb/>And thou, O master of the world! hast Grace,
    <lb/>And stature, greatness, lore, and might of hand.
    </p><p>
    <lb/>The wise archimages—seekers of the way—
    <lb/>The chiefs and heroes that attend upon thee,
    <lb/>Are either all assembled at thy court,
    <lb/>Or are thy lieges still where’er they be.
    </p><p>
    <lb/>If these shrewd-hearted sages shall behold
    <lb/>This casket with its lock and seal and stamp,
    <lb/>And state distinctly what is there concealed,
    <lb/>So that their statement shall accord to wisdom,
    <lb/>Then by this token I will send to thee
    <lb/>The tribute that my realm can well afford;
    <lb/>But if in any wise they fail herein
    <lb/>Ask not for tribute from our land again.”
    <lb/>Whenas the sage had heard the speaker’s words
    </p><p>
    <lb/>He loosed his tongue and offered praise and said:—
    <lb/>“Oh! be the world’s Shah Shah for evermore,
    <lb/>May he be eloquent and fare with fortune!
    </p><p>
    <lb/>Praise to the Master of the sun and moon,
    <lb/>Who showeth to the soul the path to knowledge,
    <lb/>And knoweth all things manifest and hidden;
    <lb/><pb n="13"/>
    <lb/>I covet knowledge, He is past all need.<note>Reading with P.</note>
    <milestone unit="calced" n="1757"/>
    </p><p>
    <lb/>Within the casket are three lustrous pearls,
    </p><p>
    <lb/>And greater coverture than I have said.<note>Reading with P.</note>
    </p><p>
    <lb/>One pearl is pierced, the second is half pierced,
    <lb/>The third hath had no intercourse with iron.”
    <lb/>The Ruman sage, on hearing, brought the key
    </p><p>
    <lb/>To Nushirwan who looked. Concealed within
    <lb/>There was a pyx, and in the pyx a veil
    <lb/>Of painted silk, and in the silk three jewels,
    <lb/>Just as the wise man of Iran had said,
    </p><p>
    <lb/>Because of those three gems the first was pierced,
    <lb/>The second half pierced and the third intact.
    <lb/>Then all the archimages praised the sage
    <lb/>And showered gems on him. The king of kings
    <lb/>Became of joyful countenance and filled
    </p><p>
    <lb/>The mouth of Buzurjmihr with lustrous pearls.
    <lb/>His conduct in the past oppressed his heart,
    <lb/>He writhed, his face grew furrowed: why had he
    <lb/>Dealt so oppressively with Buzurjmihr
    <lb/>From whom he had experienced love and faith?
    </p><p>
    <lb/>The sage, when he beheld the Shah’s shrunk face,
    <lb/>And grief-pierced soul, revealed what had been hidden,
    <lb/>Declared all that had passed to Nushirwan,
    <lb/>Told of the armlet, of the sable bird,
    <lb/>The liege’s care, the slumber of the Shah,
    <lb/>And added: “This was doomed to come to pass,
    <lb/>And sorrow and remorse will profit not.
    <lb/>When heaven is intending good or ill
    <lb/>What are Shah, archimage, or Buzurjmihr?
    <lb/>God hath implanted in the stars the seed,
    <lb/>And we must write the sentence on our heads;
    <lb/>So let the heart of Nushirwan, the Shah,
    <lb/>Rejoice exempt from pain and grief for ever.
    <lb/>Exalted though the Shah be yet his state
    <lb/><pb n="14"/>
    <lb/>Is made more gracious by his minister.
    <lb/>The chase, war, pleasure, largess, justice, feast,
    <lb/>These are the business of the king of kings.
    <lb/>He knoweth what Shahs did in days of yore,
    <lb/>So by that token let him do the same.
    <lb/>To gather treasure, to provide the host,
    <lb/>To chide, speak, hear the suppliant, and take thought
    <lb/>For rule and treasure, these things are a care,
    <lb/>That, heart and soul, the minister must bear.”</p>
    
</div>

<div><head>§ 3
    Discourse on the Responses of Nushirwan</head>
<p>
<lb/>Thus was it at the time of Nushirwan:
</p><p>
<lb/>He was at once the Shah and paladin,

<lb/>At once a warrior and archimage,

<lb/>The Fire-priest and the captain of the host.
</p><p>
<lb/>He had his emissaries everywhere,

<lb/>And trusted not the world to ministers.
<milestone unit="caled" n="1758"/>
</p><p>
<lb/>None could conceal from him in great or small

<lb/>The good and evil of the world’s estate.
<lb/>One day a loyal archmage of his agents

<lb/>Took on himself to put this to the Shah:—
</p><p>
<lb/>“One time without reproof thou passest by

<lb/>A fault. Another time the same offender

<lb/>Is hung howe’er much he excuse himself!”
<lb/>The Shah replied: ‘‘When one doth own his fault

<lb/>I am as leech, he is as wretched patient

<lb/>That would avoid the dose and sheddeth tears;
</p><p>
<lb/>If that dose fail I leech his soul no more.”
<lb/>Another archmage said to him: “Be blest,

<lb/>And sheltered from all ill on every side!
<lb/><pb n="15"/>
</p><p>
<lb/>The captain of the host went from Gurgan

<lb/>With privacy, and entering a wood.
<lb/>There for a while he slumbered. The Gurkils

<lb/>Bore off his baggage! He was left unfurnished,

<lb/>And, further, turneth back on that account!”
<lb/>The Shah made answer thus: “We do not need

<lb/>That militarist. How can he guard troops

<lb/>Who cannot guard himself?”<note>Mohl translates: <quote xml:lang="fra">Le Sipehbed est sorti un jour de Gourgan en secret, est entré dans un bois et y a dormi pendant quelque temps ; ses bagages étaient sur un autre steppe, il n’avait rien avec lui et fut obligé de s’en revenir pour rejoindre ses bagages.” Nouschirwan répondit par cette sentence: ‘Je n’avais pas besoin d’une escorte ; celui qui veille sur l’armée ne s’inquiète pas pour lui-même.</quote></note>
<lb/>Another said:—
<lb/>“Live happy evermore with archimages

<lb/>To sit, to banquet, and repose with thee!
<lb/>There is a famous chieftain present here,

<lb/>Whose treasure passeth thine!”
<lb/>The Shah replied:—
<lb/>‘Yea, rightly, for he is our empire’s crown.
<lb/>I tender both his treasures and his life,

<lb/>And toil to magnify him.”
<lb/>Said another:—
<lb/>“Great king! live ever and unscathed by ill!
</p><p>
<lb/>Among the captives carried off from Rum
<lb/>Are many babes unweaned.”
<lb/>He gave this sentence:—
<lb/>“The little ones must not be reckoned captives.
<lb/>We will dispatch them glad and in good case
<lb/>To their own mothers.”
<lb/>People wrote to him:—
<lb/>“A hundred wealthy Rumans offer ransom.”
<lb/>“If they are doing it through fear,” he said,
<lb/>“‘Sell each chief for a cup of wine and ask
<lb/>No more because we do not lack their goods.
<lb/>I will require their jewels, purses, slaves,
<lb/><pb n="16"/>
<lb/>And gold and silver with the scimitar.”
</p><p>
<lb/>They told him: “Of the rich men of the city
<lb/>There are two merchants and they keep folk waking
<lb/>The best part of the night with shouts of revel,
<lb/>And twanging of the rebeck and the harp.”
</p><p>
<lb/>He made them this reply: “No hardship this,
<lb/>And do ye others that are wealthy too
<lb/>Live like these twain in mirth and jollity;
<lb/>Be inoffensive and live unaggrieved.”
<milestone unit="caled" n="1759"/>
<lb/>One day they wrote to him: “Mayst thou be happy!
</p><p>
<lb/>Far from thee ever be the evil eye!
<lb/>The monarch of Yaman observed at court:—
<lb/>‘When Nushirwan doth ope his mouth to speak
<lb/>He talketh so much of the dead that those
<lb/>Alive have their glad lives made sad thereby’
</p><p>
<lb/>He answered thus: “All wise and high-born men
<lb/>Speak of the dead: the friendship is not sound
<lb/>Of any that would purge the heart of them.”
<lb/>Another said: “O Shah! thy youngest son
<lb/>Doth act not with the justice of his sire.
</p><p>
<lb/>He buyeth an estate at such a rate
<lb/>As to aggrieve the seller!”
<lb/>Said the Shah:—
<lb/>“This is not well, so let the seller keep
<lb/>Both price and land.”
<lb/>‘O Shah,” another said,
<lb/>“Imperious, far from blame and from reproach!
<lb/>Thy heart was gentle once: why hath it grown
<lb/>So overbearing and so choleric?”
</p><p>
<lb/>He thus made answer: ‘I had no teeth then,
<lb/>And fed on milk because I could no other,

<lb/>But since my teeth came, and my back grew straight,
<lb/>My quest is flesh because I have grown strong.”
<lb/>Another said: ‘‘I own that thou art mighty,
<lb/><pb n="17"/>
<lb/>Our better both in counsel and in knowledge,
<lb/>But how hast thou surpassed the kings of kings,
<lb/>And made the whole world watch thy policy?”
<lb/>“My wisdom is a thing,” he thus replied,
<lb/>“That is beyond their ken. Sense, knowledge, counsel—
<lb/>These are my ministers, my treasury
<lb/>Is earth, my treasurer thought.”
<lb/>Another said:—
<lb/>“O king! thy hawk in chase hath bound an eagle!”
<lb/>Thus said he: “Beat its back; why should it fall
<lb/>Upon its better? Gibbet it on high
<lb/>To suffer in its turn, for e’en in fight
<lb/>The subject may not seek to conquer kings.”
<lb/>Another chief—one of the emissaries—
<lb/>Said thus: ‘O monarch of the world! Barzin
<lb/>At morn departed with the host and met
<lb/>A reader of the stars who prophesied:—
<lb/>‘None will behold again this haughty chief,
<lb/>This mighty army, and its equipage,
<lb/>When once their backs are turned upon the king!’”
<lb/>The Shah replied: ‘Revolving heaven hath shown
<lb/>Barzin’s designs a loving countenance,
<lb/>And stars and sun and moon will not destroy
<lb/>That chieftain with his treasure and his host.”
<lb/>Another archmage said: “The king, one day,
<lb/>Bade choose a man, illustrious by birth,
<lb/>To make the circuit of the sovereignty
<lb/>Both for the sake of justice and to send
<milestone unit="caled" n="1760"/>
<lb/>Reports concerning matters great and small,
<lb/>And good or evil, to the court. Gashasp
<lb/>Is both illustrious and old: ’twere well
<lb/>That justice be administered by him.”
<lb/><pb n="18"/>
<lb/>The Shah replied: “Gashasp, though far from want,
<lb/>Is still possessed by greed. Choose some one else,
<lb/>Who toileth not upon his own behalf,
<lb/>And is possessed of treasures of his own,
<lb/>One of experience, upright and austere,
<lb/>Whose first concern is for the poor.”
<lb/>One said:—
<lb/>“The chief cook hath a grievance ’gainst the Shah
<lb/>And chiefs, and saith: ‘I dress his favourite meats,
<lb/>And serve them at cross roads. He savoureth not,
<lb/>Nor toucheth, them!’ That loyal—servant quaketh.”
</p>
<p>
<lb/>“Too much food may disgust,” the Shah replied.
<lb/>Another said: “All thoughtful people blame
<lb/>The king of kings because he goeth forth
<lb/>Without an ample escort, and the hearts
<lb/>Of all his friends are full on that account
<lb/>For fear some enemy with ill designs
<lb/>May suppliant-wise contrive to get at him.”
</p>
<p><lb/>He made this answer: “Equity and wisdom
<lb/>Protect the great king’s person. Right sufficeth
<lb/>To guard the just Judge though he be alone.”
</p>
<p><lb/>Another said: ‘O wisdom’s mate! the prince
<lb/>Of Khurasan said on the riding-ground:—
</p><p>
<lb/>‘I know not why the king recalled Garshasp.’”
</p>
<p><lb/>The Shah made answer: ‘He hath left undone
<lb/>My bidding and ignored my purposes:

<lb/>I ordered him to ope for good or ill
<lb/>My treasury’s portal to deserving folk.

<lb/>The man that is a niggard in his gifts
<lb/>Concealeth all the monarch’s Grace divine.”

<lb/>Another said: “The great king is a magnate
<lb/>With all men, and munificent and holy.

<lb/>What hath Mihrak, that ancient servant, done
<lb/>To have his pay reduced, his visage wan?<pb n="19"/>
</p><p>
<lb/>The Shah replied: “Mihrak hath grown too bold,
<lb/>Relying on his former services.
<lb/>He came to court and took his seat bemused,
<lb/>And he was never save with wine in hand.”
</p>
<p><lb/>An archmage of the intelligencers said:—
<lb/>“The Shah, when marching to encounter Caesar,
<lb/>Called only the Iranians to the war,
<lb/>And so Iran became hard pressed by Rum.”
</p>
<p><lb/>He answered: “This hostility is innate,
<lb/>'Tis war with Ahriman.”
<lb/>Another time
<lb/>One ventured to observe: “The Shah selecteth
<lb/>Troops differing from those of former Shahs.
<lb/>What look’st thou for in charger-riding Lions,
<lb/>Expert of hand, upon the day of battle?<milestone unit="caled" n="1761"/>
</p>
<p>
<lb/>He thus replied: “The cavalier of war
<lb/>Ne’er must be satiate of combating.
<lb/>Feast and the field of battle must be one
<lb/>To him both by bright day and darksome night.
<lb/>He never faileth in the hour of need,
<lb/>And few or many make no odds to him.”
</p>
<p>
<lb/>Another said: ‘O Nushirwan, the Shah!
<lb/>Live ever joyful and with youthful fortune.
<lb/>A man was at the gateway from Nisa—
<lb/>A servant and a trusty officer—
<lb/>Who at the reckoning at the taxing-office
<lb/>Was found short by three hundred thousand drachms.
<lb/>He pleaded: ‘All are spent.’ Chiefs, archimages,
<lb/>And tax-collectors are concerned.”
<lb/>The king,
<lb/>On hearing how the archimages claimed
<lb/>The money from the officer, commanded:—
<lb/>“Press not for what is spent: give him too something
<lb/>Out of the treasury.<pb n="20"/>
</p>
<p>
<lb/>Another said:—
<lb/>“A gallant cavalier was hurt and long
<lb/>Disabled. Cured he charged the ranks of Rum,
<lb/>Fell, and hath left behind him little ones.”
<lb/>The Shah commanded: “Be four thousand drachms
<lb/>Assigned to them out of the treasury,
<lb/>Because when any one is slain in war,
<lb/>And leaveth babes as his memorial,
<lb/>Whene’er the scribe shall read out from the roll
<lb/>His name, his children must have drachms, so pay
<lb/>A thousand thus to them four times a year.”
</p>
<p>
<lb/>Another said: “Be happy all thy days.
<lb/>At Marv the captain of the host hath gathered
<lb/>Much wealth in money but he spendeth not,
<lb/>And people are abandoning the march.”
<lb/>He thus made answer: “Give that wealth—the cause
<lb/>Whereby the land is made depopulate—
<lb/>Back to the folk from whom it hath been taken.
<lb/>Make proclamation of the fact in Marv,
<lb/>And bid erect a gibbet at his door,
<lb/>In sight of all his province and his troops,
<lb/>And hang alive the tyrant on the gallows,
<lb/>Head-downward, that hereafter nobody
<lb/>Among our paladins may turn aside
<lb/>In heart and spirit from our ordinance.
<lb/>Why must he bleed the poor to get him wealth,
<lb/>And joy his body to his soul’s destruction?”
<lb/>Another said: *God-fearing Shah! thy subjects
<lb/>Throng in thy court, extol thine equity,
<lb/>And praise the Maker for thee.”
<lb/>He replied:—
<lb/>“Thank God that we inspire alarm in none.
<lb/>Be it ours to tender yet more carefully
<lb/>Both innocent and guilty.<pb n="21"/>
</p>
<p>
<lb/>Said another:—
<lb/>“O Shah endowed with Grace and understanding!
<lb/>The world is full of joy, delight, and sweets,<milestone unit="caled" n="1762"/>
</p>
<p>
<lb/>And lord and liege are dizzied in their heads
<lb/>At night-fall with the din.”
</p>
<p>
<lb/>“In us,” he answered,
<lb/>“May small and great rejoice throughout the world.”
</p>
<p>
<lb/>Another said: “O Shah of power supreme!
<lb/>Detractors speak with blame of thee and say:—
<lb/>‘He squandereth vast treasures but he never
<lb/>Hath felt the labour of amassing them.’”
</p>
<p>
<lb/>He thus returned reply: “If I withhold
<lb/>The wealth laid up within my treasury
<lb/>From those deserving of it all my gain
<lb/>Will turn to loss at last.”
</p>
<p>
<lb/>Another said:—
<lb/>“O thou exalted king! God grant that scath
<lb/>May never come upon that soul of thine!
<lb/>The Jews and Christians are thine enemies,
<lb/>Are double-faced, and worship Ahriman.”
</p>

<p>
    <lb/>He answered thus: <q>A brave Shah is not great
    <lb/>Save he be tolerant.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/><note n="1">Reading with P.</note>Mardwi hath spent,
    <lb/>Another said, <q>three hundred thousand drachms,
    <lb/>Famed king! out of thy treasury and more
    <lb/>On mendicants, and chiefly on himself.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>He said thus: <q>Such withal is our command :
    <lb/>'Tis well for thee to give to the deserving.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>Another said: <q>O Shah that toilest not !
    <lb/>Much largess hath made void thy treasury.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>He thus returned reply: <q>The open hand
    <lb/>Doth start a man afresh, both leaf and bough.
    <lb/>The world-lord, when a worshipper of God,
    <pb n="22"/>
  
    <lb/>Hath at his disposition all the world,
    <lb/>But we have seen it niggard to the mean,
    <lb/>And greed and harshness tempt not me.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <note n="4">O king!</note> <lb/>93
    <lb/>An archmage said, <q>shrewd Kurakhan hath wrung
    <lb/>From famous Balkh three hundred thousand drachms,
    <lb/>And handed them to us who laid them up
    <lb/>Among thy treasures.</q>
    <lb/><q>We,</q> he made reply,
    <lb/><q>Require not drachms through others’ sufferings,
    <lb/>So give them back to those from whom they came,
    <lb/>With somewhat also from the treasury,
    <lb/>Because the world-lord that adoreth God
    <lb/>Hath no desire to vex his subjects’ hearts.
    <lb/>Raze Kurakhan’s fine palace and enrich
    <lb/>His roofs with clay. His palace shall be waste,
    <lb/>His profit toil and, after toil, distress
    <lb/>And malison. Take from our roll his name,
    <lb/>And hold of no account his likes at court.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>Another said: <q>O Shah of glorious race !
    <lb/>Thy converse turneth greatly on Jamshid
    <lb/>And on Kats.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>Thus Nushirwan replied :—
    <lb/><q>Oh! may our knowledge keep them ever young !
    <lb/>I speak of them that mine own head and crown
    <lb/>May be remembered after I am dead.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/><q>Why hideth,</q> asked another man, <q>the Shah
    <lb/>His secrets from the illustrious Bahman ?</q>
    </p>
    
    <milestone unit="caled" n="1763"/>
    
    <p>
    <lb/>The Shah replied: <q>He turneth him from wisdom,
    <lb/>And eateth of the fruit of his own lusts.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>One said: <q>O Shah that tendereth thy subjects ?
    <lb/>Why hast thou recently become remiss ?</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>He thus made answer: <q>I associate
    <lb/>With sage and archimage, for when the voice
    <lb/>Of Ahriman is at our ears our hearts
    <pb n="23"/>
    
    
    <lb/>Grow void of counsel and our brains of sense.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>An archmage asked the monarch of the earth
    <lb/>To speak concerning kingship and the Faith,
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>And said: <q>A man of wisdom will allow
    <lb/>A faithless better than a kingless world.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>He thus made answer: <q>I have said the same,
    <lb/>And holy men have heard my words. The world-lord
    <lb/>Ne’er saw a faithless world though every one
    <lb/>Hath his own Faith. One man adoreth idols,
    <lb/>Another’s Faith is pure. One said: <q>A curse
    <lb/>Is better than a blessing,</q> but mere words
    <lb/>Will never wreck the world, so speak thy mind.
    <lb/>But when the great king too is void of Faith
    <lb/>No one will bring down blessings on the world.
    <lb/>Faith and the sovereignty are like the body
    <lb/>And soul; the twain support the world.</q><note>Cf. Vol. vi. p. 250.</note>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/><q>QO Shah
    <lb/>Of joyous nature! thou hast oft observed,</q>
    <lb/>One said, <q>before the chiefs : <q>What time the throne
    <lb/>Is destitute of king then Faith and wisdom
    <lb/>Are worthless.</q> Once thou saidest: <q>I am fortune,
    <lb/>And fortune’s pretext both for good and ill,
    <lb/>And when one uttereth praises in the world
    <lb/>The crop in secret cometh back to me.</q></q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>He answered: <q>Yea, ’tis well. The great king’s head
    <lb/>Is fortune’s crown. The world is as the body ;
    <lb/>Kings are its head and crowned accordingly.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>Another said: <q>O Shah, the people’s friend !
    <lb/>Be thine the sovereignty and length of days!
    <lb/>Five days have passed, O lustre of the soul !
    <lb/>Since last the high priest came before thy presence.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>He answered: <q>I am not concerned thereat,
    <lb/>For he is occupied on mine affairs.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>One said: <q>O Shah of sunlike Grace to whom
        <pb n="24"/>

    <lb/>Time will bring forth no peer! we see a suitor
    <lb/>Attending court each morn, and that affairs
    <lb/>Are wrong with him, but wot not of his grievance.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>He answered: <q>In Hijaz<note>Reading with P. In A.D. 575 the Persians overthrew the
    <lb/>Axumite power in Arabia and conquered Yaman. The Hijaz would come to some extent within their sphere of influence.</note> thieves plundered him
    <lb/>Of countless goods. That he may not be troubled
    <lb/>I have replaced them from the treasury,
    <lb/>And keep him at the court on this account
    <lb/>To see if he can recognise the thieves.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>Another said: <q>O Shah of glorious birth,
    <lb/>The lord of bounty and the lord of justice !
  
    
    <milestone unit="caled" n="1764"/>
    
 
    <lb/>Down from the time of Gayomart till now
    <lb/>No Shah like thee hath filled the royal throne.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>He said: <q>I give thanksgiving unto God
    <lb/>That matters are as He would have them be.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>The sentences of Nushirwan are past,
    <lb/>The world is old but ever young my care ;
    <lb/>My genius hath not blossomed to this last
    <lb/>Though keen it grew, such fire in eld was there !
    <lb/>For many a year I told this history
    <lb/>Though hidden ’twas from Saturn, moon, and sun,
    <lb/>But since Mahmud’s name crowned my poetry
    <lb/>Its commendation through the world hath run.
    <lb/>The idolators of Hind he bringeth down
    <lb/>With sword whose sheen, like silk of Wash,<note>son épée damasquinée comme une broderie. Mohl. Wash is the name of a city in Turkistan, famous for its silk.</note> is bright.
    <lb/>Oh! may the age fare well through his renown,
    <lb/>And in his diadem the heaven delight.
    </p>
    

</div>

<div><pb n="25"/>

    <head>§ 4
        Nushirwan’s Letter of Counsel to his Son Hurmuz</head>
    <p>
    <lb/>Now read the letter of Shah Nushirwan,
    <lb/>And muse upon it in thine ardent soul.
    <lb/>He said: <q>This letter grateful to the heart,
    <lb/>Instructed, learned, well counselled, and abstruse,
    <lb/>Is from the Shah exalted and sun-faced.
    <lb/>Great is he, heaven inclineth to his wish,
    <lb/>The world-lord he, just and beneficent,
    <lb/>Without reproach, the lavisher of treasure,
    <lb/>Increaser of Kubad’s renown and throne,
    <lb/>Transmitter of the crown of state and justice,
    <lb/>Possessed of Grace and stature, fame and conduct,
    <lb/>And all that he could wish for from the crown
    <lb/>Of greatness, to Hurmuz, our own pure son,
    <lb/>Who heartily accepteth all our counsels,
    <lb/>And is through God glad and victorious,
    <lb/>For evermore a world-lord crowned and throned.
    <lb/>This lucky month upon the day Khurdad,
    <lb/>With fair stars and world-brightening presages,
    <lb/>We set upon thy head the crown of gold,
    <lb/>As we ourselves received it from our sire,
    <lb/>And give thee too the blessings which Kubad,
    <lb/>The glorious, bestowed upon our crown.
    <lb/>Be vigilant and master of the world,
    <lb/>Be wise and noble and without offence,
    <lb/>Increase in knowledge and incline to God,
    <lb/>Because He is the Guider of thy soul.
    <lb/>We have inquired of one of good discourse,
    <lb/>One ancient both in wisdom and in years:—
    <lb/><q>What man of us approacheth nearest God?
    <lb/>Who goeth by the straitest path to Him?</q>
    <lb/>He gave reply: <q>Choose knowledge as thou wouldst
    <lb/>That people should bless thee because the sage

    
    <pb n="26"/>
    
    <milestone unit="caled" n="1765"/>
   
    <lb/>Deriveth not addition from the dust:
    <lb/>Make thy pure spirit then approved by knowledge.</q>
    <lb/>Through knowledge doth the Shah adorn the throne:
    <lb/>Mayst thou be sage and of victorious fortune.
    <lb/>God grant thou never be a promise-breaker,
    <lb/>For promise-breakers have the dust for shroud.
    <lb/>See that thou punish not the innocent,
    <lb/>Or listen to the words of slanderers.
    <lb/>Let every ordinance of thine be just,
    <lb/>For justice will delight thy spirit. Seek not,
    <lb/>As thou wouldst be the lustre of thy throne,
    <lb/>To compass falsehood with thy tongue. Secure
    <lb/>A subject in the enjoyment of his wealth,
    <lb/>For others’ havings are no friends of thine:
    <lb/>Joy in the wealth that thou hast earned thyself.
    <lb/>‘Tis thine to be the asylum for all folk,
    <lb/>For overlord and underling alike.
    <lb/>Reward the man that acteth uprightly;
    <lb/>Oppose withal the evil-doer. Although
    <lb/>Thou mayst be held in honour in the world,
    <lb/>Forget not travail, misery, and loss;
    <lb/>Be what one may this is a Wayside Inn
    <lb/>Wherein it booteth not to feel at home.
    <lb/>Seek worth and be associate with the wise
    <lb/>If dost wish that fortune shall commend thee.
    <lb/>By knowledge bind the hands of tyranny,
    <lb/>As thou wouldst scape the evil of mishap,
    <lb/>And dearly tender him who in thy presence
    <lb/>Hath trodden under foot thy foeman’s life.
    <lb/>The great men and the merchants of the city
    <lb/>Must have their share of justice. When thou settest
    <lb/>The crown of king of kings upon thy head
    <lb/>Discern the worse way from the truly great.
    <lb/>Keep ever in thy presence some wise man,
    <lb/>And hold him as thy body and thy soul.
    
    
    <pb n="27"/>
    
    
    <lb/>In matters great and small pay no regard
    <lb/>To any save the accomplished and well born.
    <lb/>Give not the worthless battle-gear for when
    <lb/>Thou seekest it ’tis not to hand. Thy friend
    <lb/>Will yield thee to the foe; a double task
    <lb/>Both difficult and wretched will be thine:
    <lb/>He will bring down thy weapons to the field,
    <lb/>And one day will employ them on thyself.
    <lb/>Be generous to persons in distress,
    <lb/>Avoid ill-doing, fear calamity,
    <lb/>Discern the hidden motives of thy heart,
    <lb/>Make no mere outward show of good and right,
    <lb/>Be not unmeasured in beneficence,
    <lb/>And hear the counsels of the experienced.
    <lb/>Lean toward religious men but watch religion,
    <lb/>Because it causeth bitterness and wrath.
    <lb/>Proportion thine expenses to thy means,
    <lb/>And be not careful to augment thy store.
    <lb/>Observe the precedents of former Shahs,
    <lb/>And be a righteous judge in everything;
    
    
    <milestone unit="caled" n="1766"/>
    
    
    <lb/>The Shah that doth unjustly is accursed;
    <lb/>Approve but justice then and court not curses.
    <lb/>Where are the crowned heads of the kings of kings?
    <lb/>Where are the great men and the ministers?
    <lb/>Their fame is now their sole memorial;
    <lb/>This Wayside Inn abideth not with any.
    <lb/>Command not to shed blood, or urge the host
    <lb/>To battle, lightly. Heed this weighty letter.
    <lb/>Set not thy heart upon this Hostelry.
    <lb/>Herein have I but sought thy good and decked
    <lb/>Thy heart with knowledge by the rede of Him
    <lb/>Who ruleth sun and moon; by Him keep off
    <lb/>The influence of the Div. Have thou before thee
    <lb/>This letter, day and night. Let wisdom rule
    <lb/>Thy heart. If thou dost make a memory here
    <lb/>Thy name will never want for majesty.
    
    
    <pb n="28"/>
    
    
    <lb/>Now be the Maker of the world thy refuge,
    <lb/>May time and earth affect thee. May high heaven
    <lb/>Turn but at thy desire and in the world
    <lb/>Be none aggrieved by thee.</q>
    </p><p>
    <lb/>He placed the letter,
    <lb/>When written, in the treasury and abode
    <lb/>With fear and trembling in this Wayside Inn.
    <lb/>A king of kings well counselled, wise, and just,
    <lb/>Will strive to make his modesty unite
    <lb/>With strength of hand and gallantry in fight,
    <lb/>Be of pure Faith and put in God his trust.
    <lb/>See what man of these virtues is possest
    <lb/>And, seeing, him his meed of praise prefer,
    <lb/>Seek one that is as bright as Jupiter,
    <lb/>Aspiring, armed with sword, with mail on breast;
    <lb/>Who taketh from idolaters the sway,
    <lb/>Who with brocade of Faith his heart hath bound.
    <lb/>Yea verily the man himself is found:
    <lb/>Mahmud is monarch of the world to-day.
    <lb/>The quest of battle and of banqueting
    <lb/>Are one to this world’s lord. Abwt’l Kasim!
    <lb/>God grant the age joy in the sight of him,
    <lb/>That open-handed and victorious king.
    </p>

    
</div>
<div><head>§5 How an Archmage questioned Nushirwan and how he made Answer</head>
<p>
<lb/>There was an elder versed in our old speech,
<lb/>And antiquate with action and discourse,
<lb/>Who from a volume in the ancient tongue
</p>

<pb n="29"/>

<p>
<lb/>Saith that an archmage asked of Nushirwan:—
<lb/><q>In what way should the worshipper invoke
<lb/>In secret prayer the Master of the world
<lb/>That He may give an answer and bestow
<lb/>Withal fair fortune on his suppliant?
<lb/>A man, with arms outstretched toward the sky,
<lb/>May make request before the Lord of time,</q>
</p>

<milestone unit="caled" n="1767"/>

<p>
<lb/>Yet gain not his desire for all his prayers,
<lb/>And hath but tearful eyes and furrowed face.
<lb/>The conquering Shah replied: <q>Be moderate
<lb/>In thy requests to God; when they pass bounds
<lb/>A heart o’ercharged will come of that desire.</q>
<lb/>The archmage asked: <q>What man deserveth good,
<lb/>And who is worthiest of the name of ‘Great?’</q>
<lb/>The Shah replied: <q>He that amasseth treasure
<lb/>Without exertion, and bestoweth not,
<lb/>Is unfit for the throne; from time to time
<lb/>His fortune will grow dark, but well is he
<lb/>That giveth. Give, if wealth be thine, and hoard not.</q>
<lb/>“What is the base of wisdom?” asked the archmage,
<lb/><q>And who rejoiceth in its boughs and leaves?</q>
<lb/>“The sage rejoiceth,” Nushirwan replied;
<lb/><q>So doth the modest man of noble birth.</q>
<lb/>The archmage asked: <q>Who profiteth by knowledge,
<lb/>And who is witless and calamitous?</q>
<lb/>The Shah replied: <q>The cherisher of wisdom
<lb/>Will cherish life which profiteth thereby
<lb/>When it aboundeth, but its lack entaileth
<lb/>Grief, care, and loss.</q>
<lb/>The archmage inquired:—
<lb/><q>Is knowledge better than the Grace of kings,
<lb/>For Grace and majesty adorn the throne?</q>
<lb/>“A sage possessed of Grace,” replied the Shah,
</p>

<pb n="30"/>

<p>
<lb/>Will take the whole world underneath his wing.
<lb/>Thou needest wisdom, Grace, renown, and birth;
<lb/>With these four heaven will keep thee still in mind.
<lb/>“In kingship who illustrateth the throne?”
<lb/>The archmage said. “Who is unfortunate?”
<lb/>And Nushirwan made answer: <q>One that seeketh
<lb/>First for the aidance of the King, the World-lord,</q><note>Reading with P.</note>
<lb/><q>For bounty, knowledge, and right usages
<lb/>Will make him tender toward the suppliant.
<lb/>Next let him give authority to those,
<lb/>Who merit such distinction by their worth.
<lb/>Then let him see that nothing in the world
<lb/>For good or evil is concealed from him.
<lb/>He should distinguish, fourthly, foe from friend:
<lb/>Tis well that kings should be without offence.
<lb/>When he hath Grace and wisdom, Faith and fortune,
<lb/>Then he is worthy of the crown and graceth
<lb/>The throne, while if thou findest such things lacking
<lb/>Good sooth! thou wilt behold him lustreless;
<lb/>He after death will leave an evil name,
<lb/>And win not jocund Paradise at last.</q><note>Five couplets omitted.</note>
</p>

<milestone unit="caled" n="1768"/>

<p>
<lb/>The archmage asked: <q>How many modes of speech
<lb/>Are there and what are they, because o’er some
<lb/>One needs must weep while others are crown, treasure,
<lb/>And reputation, those grief, these content?</q>
<lb/>Said Nushirwan: <q>The sage hath classified
<lb/>The modes of speech and thought the matter out.
<lb/>First, profitable speech; the sweet-voiced sage
<lb/>Saith that it is the harmless. Secondly,
<lb/>That which thou callest the deliberate
<lb/>Know to be that of shrewd and fluent men,
<lb/>For they speak</q><note>Reading with P.</note><q>largely to the point and leave


<pb n="31"/>


<lb/>Their memory in the world. Next is the speech
<lb/>Of one ambitioning the word in season;
<lb/>He will abide in honour all his years;
<lb/>And, fourthly, that of one called by the sage
<lb/>Delectable—the competent reciter,
<lb/>Who uttereth all, both new and old, in verse;
<lb/>While, fifthly, is the warm deliverance
<lb/>Of one of sweet tongue and harmonious voice,
<lb/>Who when he hath impleached his web of words
<lb/>Attaineth verily his heart’s desire.</q>
<lb/>The archmage said: <q>In spite of all thy lore,
<lb/>And thou hast kindled all thy soul with knowledge,
<lb/>Yet thou still questionest the little worth!
<lb/>Dost say then: ‘How shall knowledge have an end?’</q>
<lb/>The Shah replied: <q>From all that I have learned
<lb/>I have attained my soul’s desire and wisdom.
<lb/>Avoid wrong-doing then and look to knowledge—
<lb/>A thing more precious than the crown and throne.</q>
<lb/>The archmage said: <q>I have seen none so praised
<lb/>And eminent for lore that one could say:—
<lb/>‘Such is his eminence that no wise man
<lb/>Can teach him any further.’</q>
<lb/>Thus the Shah
<lb/>Replied: <q>Can treasure satiate a man
<lb/>Until he lieth underneath the dust?
<lb/>The way of knowledge is more glorious
<lb/>Than wealth, more precious in the sage’s eyes.
<lb/>Our words remain as our memorial:
<lb/>Compare not wealth with knowledge.</q>
</p>

<pb n="32"/>

<p>
<lb/>Said the archmage:—
<lb/><q>What with their learning and remembering
<lb/>The sages cannot be but ancient men.</q>
<lb/>The Shah replied: <q>Although the man be old
<lb/>His knowledge faileth not to keep him young.
<lb/>Thou wilt prefer him to the foolish youth,
<lb/>Whose dust is only valued for its tomb.</q>
<lb/>The archmage asked: <q>It was thy wont to speak
<lb/>About the fortune of the kings of kings
<lb/>Before the Great,</q><note>Reading with P and T.</note><q>and more than ever now
<lb/>Thou namest them but with a deep cold sigh?</q>
<lb/>The Shah said: <q>It was never in my heart
<lb/>That I should praise a process such as this—
<lb/>To govern this world with the scimitar
<lb/>Of justice, then pass on and vilely die.</q>
</p>

<milestone unit="caled" n="1769"/>

<p>
<lb/>“Thy usage,” said the archmage, “in the past
<lb/>Was this—to speak to all in nobler words.
<lb/>Now, thou despisest them and sayest naught
<lb/>About the past or present.”
<lb/>Nushirwan
<lb/>Made answer saying: <q>I have talked enough,
<lb/>And now I purpose to depend on deeds.</q>
<lb/>The archmage said: <q>Thy prayers in former times
<lb/>Before the Fire were not so long as now.
<lb/>Thy praises too are longer than they were,
<lb/>Thy plaints and supplications more profuse.</q>
<lb/>He gave this answer saying: <q>Holy God
<lb/>Exalteth from the dust His worshipper,
<lb/>Doth favourably dispose the sky toward him,
<lb/>And maketh all the world to be his slave.
<lb/>If this slave faileth to appreciate,
<lb/>Let him not scape from hardship and distress.</q>
<lb/>The archmage asked: <q>Since thou becamest king
<lb/>What greater cause for thankfulness hast thou
<lb/>Toward thy Maker? Hath that eminence
<lb/>Increased thy joy and filled thy foemen’s hearts
<lb/>With blood?</q>
<lb/>He answered thus: <q>Thanks be to God,
<lb/>Our fortune hath been good. None in my presence
<lb/>Hath ever sought for the supremacy,


<pb n="33"/>


<lb/>But at my chastening washed his hands of ill.
<lb/>My foemen have grown feeble in the fight
<lb/>When they beheld mine onset and my mace.</q>
<lb/>The priest went on: <q>When warring in the West
<lb/>Thou wast both quick of clutch and valorous,
<lb/>But when thou wast campaigning in the East
<lb/>Thou wast long-suffering and deliberate.</q>
<lb/>And Nushirwan made answer thus: <q>The youth
<lb/>Accounteth not of pain and toil of mind,
<lb/>But when a man hath come to sixty years
<lb/>He must assume a gentler attitude.
<lb/>Thanks to the World-lord who is all-providing,
<lb/>The Author of the good and ill of fortune,
<lb/>That I had prowess in my youthful days,
<lb/>And recked not if my luck were good or bad.
<lb/>Now knowledge, treasure, generosity,
<lb/>And rede, accompany my days of age,
<lb/>The world is ’neath my rule and usages,
<lb/>And circling heaven my breastplate in the fight.</q>
<lb/>Said the archmage: <q>The Shahs of long ago
<lb/>Desired to hold discourse on all affairs;
<lb/>Thy words are briefer and thy secrets more,
<lb/>Yet thou surpassest those famed men of old.</q>
<lb/>He made this answer, saying: <q>Every king,
<lb/>That doth believe in Him who giveth all,
<lb/>Is not concerned about himself for He,
<lb/>Who made the world, still watcheth over it.</q>
</p>

<pb n="34"/>

<p>
<lb/>The archmage said: <q>Shahs used to tend themselves,
<lb/>Employing drug and leech and remedy,
<lb/>Lest they should have to soil themselves with tears.</q>
<lb/>“A man, whose time is not yet come,” he said,
<lb/><q>Not yet o’ertaken by the turning sky,
<lb/>Will stand secure, and drugs will profit naught,
<lb/>Because the chance of time protecteth him,
<lb/>But when the hour for passing is at hand
<lb/>Then no precaution will avert his fate.</q>
<lb/>The archmage said: <q>Thou praisest much and prayest
<lb/>The Maker, yet at heart thou art not glad
<lb/>The while, but ever hast a soul all care.</q>
<lb/>“There is no care at all,” said Nushirwan,
<lb/><q>The Shah’s heart is at one with turning heaven;
<lb/>I fear that those who offer praise to me,
<lb/>And shower benedictions on my Faith,
<lb/>Affect a greater fervour than they feel:
<lb/>Mine object is to read my subjects’ hearts.</q>
</p>

<pb n="35"/>

<p>
<lb/><q>Why joy we in our children,</q> asked the archmage,
<lb/><q>And why do we desire a family?</q>
<lb/><q>The man that leaveth children in the world
<lb/>Will not become forgotten,” he replied.
<lb/>“If he have children he will relish life,
<lb/>And for that reason will abstain from vice,
<lb/>While if he pass away the pang is slight,
<lb/>Because a child’s eyes watch his paling face.</q>
<lb/>“Who liveth at his ease,” the archmage asked,
<lb/><q>And who repenteth of his own good deeds?</q>
<lb/>He thus replied: <q>The worshipper of God
<lb/>Will take the reins of fortune in his hands
<lb/>And, seeking no addition, is at ease,
<lb/>Who if he sought it would be full of fear.


<pb n="36"/>


<lb/>Then as for what thou said’st about good deeds,
<lb/>And secret inclinations to do good,
<lb/>Know, no one is more mortified than he
<lb/>That meditateth good for thankless folk.</q>
<lb/>“The evil-doer dieth,” said the archmage,
<lb/><q>The world removeth from the roll his name.
<lb/>The righteous man will likewise pass away,
<lb/>And destiny account his every breath.
<lb/>What need is there for praising excellence
<lb/>Since death is here to reap both good and bad?</q>
<lb/>And Nushirwan made answer thus: <q>Good deeds
<lb/>Will find a ready market everywhere.
<lb/>He that doth good deeds dieth not though dead,
<lb/>But resteth, giving up his soul to God;</q><note>Couplet omitted.</note>
</p>

<milestone unit="caled" n="1771"/>

<p>
<lb/>The archmage further said: <q>No ill is worse
<lb/>Than death. If so, then what is our resource?</q>
<lb/>The Shah replied: <q>On leaving this dark earth,
<lb/>The life which then thou wilt have gained is pure.
<lb/>Whoe’er lived here in fear and care must needs
<lb/>Bewail that life but, whether Shah or subject,
<lb/>Thou wilt be quit of this world’s fear and pain.</q>
<lb/>The archmage asked him: <q>Which is worst of these
<lb/>In filling us with anguish and chagrin?</q>
<lb/>The Shah made answer: <q>Reckon mountain-heavy
<lb/>The troubles that descend on us in troops,
<lb/>And what is fear except the fear of troubles,
<lb/>Than which there is naught stronger in the world?</q>
<lb/>“How can we ’scape from these?” the archmage asked,
<lb/><q>For this world’s doings give us cause to weep?</q>
<lb/>He thus made answer: <q>Knowledge is the way:
<lb/>The sage is ever cheerful.</q>
</p>

<pb n="37"/>

<p>
<lb/>“Which of us,”
<lb/>Inquired the archmage, <q>hath most store of treasure?</q>
<lb/>The Shah made answer: <q>He that hath least toil.</q>
<lb/>The archmage asked: <q>Which is the foulest fault,
<lb/>One alien most from worth and Paradise?</q>
<lb/>The Shah made answer: <q>In the case of women
<lb/>A strident voice and lack of modesty;
<lb/>But, in the case of men, to be a fool,
<lb/>And thus to spend a lifetime as in prison.</q>
<lb/>The archmage asked: <q>Who hath most confidence?</q>
<lb/>“He that hath least remorse,” replied the Shah,
<lb/><q>And goeth soiled in body, and with heart
<lb/>Black with iniquity, before his God.</q>
<lb/>The archmage said: <q>Who is the upright man,
<lb/>Whose heart is proven by his soul and wisdom?</q>
<lb/>The Shah thus answered: <q>He that toileth on
<lb/>Through gain and loss and compasseth no ill.</q>
<lb/>The archmage asked: <q>Who is the best of men,
<lb/>The crown upon the head of all mankind?</q>
<lb/>“The meek to whom a crown availeth naught,”
<lb/>The Shah replied; <q>not one intent on profit,
<lb/>Not even though he be of lofty aims;
<lb/>Next, he whose greatness is its own reward—
<lb/>The generous man whose heart is purged from darkness—
<lb/>And, thirdly, he that hath a zeal divine,
<lb/>Proceeding from integrity and wisdom.</q>
<lb/>“What,” said the archmage, <q>is the heart’s chief dread?</q>
<lb/>“The troubles that we bring upon ourselves,”
<lb/>The Shah replied.
<lb/>“What giving is the best,”
<lb/>The archmage said, <q>so that the man who giveth


<pb n="38"/>


<lb/>May be exalted and great?</q>
<lb/>“In gain and loss,”
<lb/>The Shah rejoined, <q>keep naught from the deserving.</q>
<lb/>The archmage asked concerning this world’s doings:—
<lb/><q>Declare its process open and concealed.
<lb/>Whate’er the manner of that action be,
<lb/>For loss or profit, shall we acquiesce?</q>
</p>

<milestone unit="caled" n="1772"/>

<p>
<lb/>“The All-knowing,” thus the Shah replied, <q>is greater
<lb/>And higher than this ancient sky although
<lb/>It knowing be and mindful; He is Lord
<lb/>Of this world’s lords. Become not then perverse,
<lb/>Avoid disaster, and attribute not
<lb/>Good fortune and misfortune to the sky.
<lb/>Know that both ill and good proceed from Him
<lb/>That hath no peer—the One eternal Cause,
<lb/>Whose word is ‘Be’ and what He willeth is,
<lb/>Who was and is and will be evermore.</q>
</p>

<p>
    <lb/>“The body is the hostel of the soul:
    <lb/>Which of them feeleth pain?” the archmage asked.
    <lb/>The Shah replied: <q>Our mortal bodies suffer
    <lb/>So long as they have brains, but when the soul
    <lb/>Hath filtered through they lose their consciousness,
    <lb/>And when it hath departed are dissolved.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>The archmage questioned him on self-control:—
    <lb/><q>In what way can we hide our greed and need?</q>
    <lb/>The Shah replied: <q>’Tis fitting that the sage
    <lb/>Suppress them, yet thou ever wilt be vexed
    <lb/>By greed because ne’er satiate of treasure.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>The archmage asked: <q>Among the kings of yore,
    <lb/>The men of sense, rede, faith, and precedent,
    <lb/>Whom knowest thou as subject of our praise,
    <lb/>When he is dead, O monarch of the earth?</q>
    <lb/>“That great king,” this was Nushirwan’s reply,
    </p>
    
    <pb n="38"/>
    
    <p>
    <lb/><q>Who is a worshipper of God and pure,
    <lb/>And thankful to the righteous Lord of all,
    <lb/>Who filleth none with fear of tyranny,
    <lb/>Who giveth to the good a hopeful heart,
    <lb/>And to the bad a heart of fear and pain,
    <lb/>Who furnisheth his troops from his own treasures,
    <lb/>And turneth on malignants their own ill,
    <lb/>Who questioneth the sages of the world,
    <lb/>And keepeth from his foes his bad and good.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
    <lb/>The archmage asked: <q>Wherein consisteth worship,
    <lb/>And who approacheth to God’s holiness?</q>
    <lb/>“The subtle will direct,” the Shah replied,
    <lb/><q>His soul as by fine hair-breadths and first know
    <lb/>The being and the unity of God,
    <lb/>Which small instruction will make evident,
    <lb/>And he will offer thanks for mercies given,
    <lb/>While putting trust in God and fearing Him,
    <lb/>Who is thy terror when thou seekest ill,
    <lb/>Thy trust when thou dost well. If thou art sound
    <lb/>Of Faith and seek’st the Way all will esteem thee,
    <lb/>While if thou art malign and ill-disposed
    <lb/>Thy soul hath forwarded its packs to Hell.
    <lb/>Feel not at home with this world for 'twil hold
    <lb/>Its secrets from thee. Tend to works of Faith;
    <lb/>Thy good choice will not injure thee. Let wisdom
    <lb/>Instruct thy heart and let not fortune fool thee.
    <lb/>Again, thou shalt consort not with the guilty</q>
    </p>
    
    <milestone unit="caled" n="1773"/>
    
    <p>
    <lb/><q>In wrong and strife. Loathe secretly at heart
    <lb/>This world because of that which is to come.
    <lb/>Let thy seat ever be among the sages,
    <lb/>A devotee of everlasting joys,
    <lb/>For what we have on earth will pass away,
    <lb/>And reason counteth them no joys at all.
    <lb/>Mayst thou incline to sense and rede. Let wisdom
    <lb/>Guide thee to God. Speak not unmeasured words,
    <lb/>For thou’rt new-fangled and the world is old.
    </q>
    </p>
    
    <pb n="39"/>
    
    <p>
    <lb/><q>Be drunk not with the pleasures of the day.
    <lb/>Choose not the company of wicked men.
    <lb/>Refrain thy heart from what can never be,
    <lb/>And give such largess as 'tis fit to give.
    <lb/>Withhold not from a friend aught that thou hast,
    <lb/>Though he should ask thine eyes, thy brains, and skin,
    <lb/>And if two friends would take account together
    <lb/>No daysman should be needed for that task.
    <lb/>If thou associate with a foe so act
    <lb/>That he may not obtain a hold upon thee.
    <lb/>When one doth seek the path of right his need
    <lb/>Is parts, humility, and gentleness.
    <lb/>Let not thy tongue exaggerate thy merits,
    <lb/>For falsehood is no merit with the just,
    <lb/>Who hold one’s high estate a thing of naught,
    <lb/>Another’s poverty no mark for scorn.
    <lb/>If some malicious person talk with thee
    <lb/>Let not his malice anger thee, and then,
    <lb/>When, being well assured that thou art weak,
    <lb/>He useth language that is past all bounds,
    <lb/>Reply to him in measured terms and speak
    <lb/>Words goodly and well-liking. If it be
    <lb/>That thou canst bring him to himself by kindness
    <lb/>He will repent his former speech. Devote not
    <lb/>Thy leisure to indulgence. Idleness
    <lb/>Is naught if thou art wise. Be diligent
    <lb/>In all thine undertakings and give ear
    <lb/>To knowledge. Enter on no enterprise
    <lb/>Whereof the end will cause remorse or anger.
    <lb/>Have pity on the sad in his distress;
    <lb/>Bring not his heart to anguish and disaster.
    <lb/>The sage that traineth his own heart to patience
    <lb/>Is not held worthless in the World-lord’s eyes,
    <lb/>But knoweth what he meriteth with Him,
    <lb/>And compasseth all actions with discretion,
    </q>
    </p>
    
    <pb n="40"/>
    
    <p>
    <lb/><q>For increase from a friend is laudable,
    <lb/>And greatness and integrity will bring
    <lb/>Addition. Furthermore that man of God
    <lb/>Will not begrudge the scattering of treasure,
    <lb/>But turneth him from waywardness and loss,
    <lb/>And maketh right and service his profession—
    <lb/>A stem with boughs whereby God’s worshipper,
    <lb/>The virtuous saint, hath proved victorious.
    <lb/>There is but one injunction and one way—
    <lb/>Incline to God and let Him shelter thee.</q>
    </p>
    
    <milestone unit="caled" n="1774"/>
    
    <p>
    <lb/>If thou, O monarch! art of just intent
    <lb/>Good will remain to be thy monument
    <lb/>As it doth with Shah Nushirwan whose flesh
    <lb/>Hath turned to dust although his fame is fresh.
    <lb/>Himself unseen his fame is plain to all;
    <lb/>His words survive as his memorial,
    <lb/>And through the righteous deeds that he hath done
    <lb/>His fame past doubt will live while time shall run,
    <lb/>And on his soul shall be, while earth and sky
    <lb/>Abide in place, the sages’ eulogy.
    </p>
    
    </div>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>