<TEI>
<text>

<body>
<div><head>XLIV. KUBAD (COMMONLY CALLED SHIRWI): HE REIGNED SEVEN MONTHS</head>

<div><head>ARGUMENT</head>
<p><pb n="3"/>
Kubad on his accession sends two chiefs to accuse of misgovernment the fallen and imprisoned Shah, Khusrau Parwiz, who justifies himself at great length. His fall is made the subject of a lament by Barbad, the minstrel, who afterwards mutilates himself. The chiefs, noticing symptoms of remorse in Kubad, insist upon the death of Khusrau Parwiz who is killed with all his other sons. Kubad falls in love with, and wishes to marry, Shirin, who poisons herself rather than consent, and Kubad himself is poisoned soon afterwards.
</p>
</div>

<div><head>NOTE</head>
<p>
The days of the reign of Kubad (Kobad II., Feb.-Sept., A.D. 628) were few and evil. Tradition already had prepared the ground for this in the unfavourable account given of his early years.<note n="1">See Vol. viii., p. 390</note> The murder of his father was followed by that of all his brothers, and by the tragic death of Shirin, while in addition to all these horrors a frightful pestilence broke out in his reign and the great mortality that ensued still further weakened the resources of an already almost exhausted country and helped to pave the way for the successful Arab invasion of a few years later on. Kubad is represented in the poem as a loutish, uneducated youth,<note n="2">See Vol. viii., p. 390</note> but even if his abilities had been great it is difficult to see how he could have extricated himself from the coil in which

<pb n="4"/>

he found himself involved without mishap to himself or others. He owed his release from prison and perhaps his life to the very conspirators that subsequently demanded of him for their own security the death of his father. To have refused would have been fatal to himself, while in all probability his father and his brothers, with the exception of one who would have been made Shah, would have perished all the same. It is inconceivable that the conspirators would have run the risk to themselves of restoring Khusrau Parwiz, with his black record of ingratitude as instanced by his treatment of Bandwi and Gustaham,<note n="3">See Vol. viii., p. 354 seq.</note> to his former position as ruler. With the exception of his infatuation for Shirin, which hardly can be regarded as historical, Kubad throughout his short reign was the victim of circumstances.
</p><p>
§§ 1 and 2. Kharrad, son of Barzin, was one of the most trusted ministers of Khusrau Parwiz and planned the assassination of Bahram Chubina.<note n="4">See Vol. viii., p. 331 seq.</note> According to Tabari he fell at the battle of Dhi Qar.<note n="5">See Vol. viii., p. 190.</note>
</p><p>
As the epoch of the Sasanian Dynasty draws to an end through scenes of deepening tragedy the legitimist leanings of the tradition seem to become more and more pronounced and we have an instance here. It is hardly to be supposed, historically speaking, that formal charges of misgovernment were drawn up against, and as formally answered by, Khusrau Parwiz, but rather that someone, desirous of vindicating that Shah’s memory and conversant with the circumstances of the time, soon after his death drew up the charges and the replies thereto. Versions of them are given in both the Arabic and Persian Tabari and elsewhere. Four of the charges are found in both the Tabaris as well as in the Shahnama.<note n="6">NT, 363 seq. ZT, ii., 334 seg.</note> They are :—
<list>
<item>1. The murder by Khusrau Parwiz of his father Hurmuzd.</item>

<item>2. The illegitimate accumulation of treasure as a result of the financial oppression of the people.</item>

<item>3. The harsh treatment of the royal princes.</item>

<item>4. The refusal to restore the True Cross.</item>
</list>
To these the Arabic Tabarf adds:— ,

<list>
<item>1. The general ill-treatment of all prisoners.</item>

<item>2. Enforced recruiting for the royal Haram even of women already married.</item>



<pb n="5"/>

<item>3. The keeping of the troops for a long period absent
from home. </item>
</list>
The Persian Tabarf adds :—

<list>
<item>1. The imprisonment of the troops defeated by the Arabs at Dhu Kar and by Heraclius.</item>
<item>2. The exactions of arrears of tribute for the previous twenty or thirty years.</item>


<item>3. The attempt to slay the youthful Yazdagird (afterwards the last Sésénian Shah).</item>

<item>4. The deposition of Nu’mén, prince of Hira.<note>See Vol. viii., p. 190</note></item>


<item>5. The mutilation and subsequent execution of Mardan-shâh.<note>See p. 6.</note></item>
</list>

</p>
<p>
In the Arabic Tabari, eight charges are made against Khusrau Parwiz, two of which—those relating to the royal Haram and the refusal to restore the “True Cross”—are left unanswered.
</p>
<p>
In the Persian Tabari, eleven charges are formulated, to each of which, in the same order, an answer is made. Some of the charges, however, must be regarded as later additions, while that relating to Nu’man is not likely to have suggested itself to a Persian and must come from an Arab source. In the Shahnama, there are eight charges, all of which are more or less answered, but not in the same order as they are preferred, but in the following:—1, 6, 7, 8, 2, 5, 3, 4. Thus, Khusrau Parwiz replies to the most serious accusations—those of offences against persons—first. The Shahnama agrees most closely with the Arabic Tabari, supplies the missing answer with regard to the <quote>True Cross,</quote> but does not deal with the gravamen of the royal Haram question, as that particular charge is not one of those mentioned in the poem.
</p>
<p>
Galinush subsequently served in the war against the Arabs, fought at the Battle of the Bridge, and was perhaps slain at Kadisiya.<note n="7">NT, p. 365 note. RM, Pt. ii., vol. iii., pp. 95, 116.</note>
</p>
<p>
§5. Indignant legitimate tradition is naturally very wroth with Mihr Hurmuzd, the murderer of Khusrau Parwiz, whom it describes as the lowest of the low and vilest of the vile. According to Tabari, however, Mihr Hurmuzd was the son of Mardanshah, the governor of Nimruz and one of the most obedient and faithful of Khusrau Parwiz’ officials. In the Persian Tabari’s version of the Romance of Bahram 
<pb n="6"/>
Chubina, that hero’s brother, Yalan-sina in the Shahnama, is called Mardanshah. Yalan-sina is always represented as being one of Bahram Chubina‘s most loyal adherents just as the other brother, Gurdwi, was a firm supporter of Khusrau Parwiz, while their sister Gurdya held an intermediate position, faithful to Bahram Chubina, but opposing his kingly ambition in every way in her power. Later on, when married to Gustaham, the maternal uncle of Khusrau Parwiz, she agreed, on condition that she should become the Shah’s wife and that a full amnesty should be given to all her adherents, to murder her husband and did so. There would be nothing strange therefore in Mardanshah, if identical with Yalan-sina, becoming reconciled to, and receiving high office from, Khusrau Parwiz. He would serve one master as faithfully as he served the other. In the circumstances, the strange thing would have been for the treacherous Shah not to have taken the first convenient occasion against him. According to the story, the Shah, two years before his deposition, consulted the astrologers who informed him that his death would come from Nimruz. He therefore began to suspect and summoned Mardanshah, but finding no pretext for putting him to death, as he was perfectly loyal and withal an aged man, determined merely to cut off his right hand and make him a large present of money as compensation. The sentence was carried out. Mardanshah regarded such a mutilation as worse than death and, when shortly afterwards the Shah was good enough to send and express his regret for what had occurred, asked the Shah to grant him a boon. The Shah swore to do so, on which Mardanshah requested that his head should be struck off in order to wipe out the disgrace put upon him. The Shah, bound by his oath, felt himself obliged to consent and the execution took place accordingly. The Shah wished to make Mardanshah’s son governor of Nimruz, but he refused and withdrew from the army.<note n="8">NT, p. 379. ZT, ii., 330.</note> He joined the conspiracy against Khusrau Parwiz<note n="9">See Vol. viii., p. 196.</note> and by avenging his father on the Shah justified the prediction of the astrologers.
</p>
<p>
The account given by Theophanes of the last days of the Shah is different. As a general rule, it is not prudent to put faith in stories of what occurred in Oriental palaces or prisons, but owing to the special circumstances of the case, his information may be good in this instance, as it appears to be <pb n="7"/> based on letters written by Heraclius. After the capture of Khusrau Parwiz by the conspirators, he was bound and confined in the <quote>House of Darkness</quote>, which he had himself built as a stronghold for his treasures. Here he was sparingly fed on bread and water for, said Shirwi: <quote>Let him eat the gold that he has vainly amassed, and for whose sake he has starved many, and made the world itself a desert.</quote> Shirwi also sent satraps to revile and spit upon him, had his son Mardasas, whom he had wished to crown, slain before his eyes, and all his other sons as well, sent his enemies to beat and spit upon him, and, after five days of such treatment, had him put to death with arrows. Shirwi then wrote to Heraclius to announce the death of the detested Khusrau Parwiz, arranged terms of peace, released all the captives, and restored the <quote>True Cross.</quote><note n="10">CTC, i., 502.</note> With regard to these latter statements of Theophanes, it should be observed that peace was not concluded, and the “True Cross” restored, till after the death of Shirwi.<note n="11">NT, p. 392 and note.</note>
</p>
<p>
According to Tabari, Kubad had Mihr Hurmuzd put to death.<note n="12">NT, p. 382.</note>
</p>
<p>
§6. The association of Khusrau Parwiz and Shirin began, it would seem,<note n="13">See vol. viii., p. 383.</note> before his accession to the throne, and he reigned for thirty-eight years. If Shirwi really wished to marry Shirin, it must have been for political motives and because she had been so much in his father’s confidence and might furnish useful information. For a son to marry his father’s wives was, according to Persian ideas, quite the correct procedure in the circumstances.
</p>
<p>
Kubad is said to have been bitterly reproached by his two sisters, Purandokht and Azarmidokht, for his share in the deaths of his father and brothers, and to have suffered much from sickness and remorse. He died at Dastagird, but from what cause is uncertain.<note n="14">NT, p. 384 and notes.</note> The plague was very virulent at the time. Poison was often made to account for what was really due to disease.
</p>

</div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><head>How Shirwi ascended the Throne, announced his Will, and sent Chiefs to his Father with Counsel and Excuses</head>
<p>
<pb n="8"/>
<lb/>Now when Shirwi sat on the goodly throne,
<lb/>And donned the royal crown so much desired,
<lb/>The leaders of the Iranians each drew near
<lb/>To proffer him the homage due to kings,
<lb/>Exclaiming: <q>Worshipful and honoured Shah!
<lb/>Know, God gave thee the crown, and now thou sittest
<lb/>Securely on the throne of ivory,
<lb/>And may thy sons and scions have the world.</q>
<lb/>Kubäd replied: <q>Be ever conquering
<lb/>And happy. Never will we practise ill.
<lb/>How good is justice with benevolence!
<lb/>The world will we keep peaceful and cut off
<lb/>The works of Ahriman by every right,
<lb/>Ancestral precedent that greateneth
<lb/>The Glory of our Faith. I will dispatch
<lb/>A message to my sire and tell him all.
<lb/>He is in evil odour in the world
<lb/>Through his ill deeds: let him excuse his faults
<lb/>To God and turn to custom and the way.
<milestone unit="calced" n="2027"/>
<lb/>If he shall heed me he will not resent
<lb/>My conduct. Then will I devote myself
<lb/>To state-affairs and strive to compass justice
<lb/>Both publicly and privily, do good
<lb/>Where good is due, and break no poor man’s heart.
<lb/>I need two honest men of goodly speech,
<lb/>Whose memories are charged with ancient lore.</q>
</p>
<p>
<pb n="9"/>
<lb/>He asked the assembly: <q>Whom shall I employ?
<lb/>Who is most shrewd and honest in Iran?</q>
<lb/>The warriors all suggested by their looks
<lb/>Two men of lore if they should give consent.
<lb/>Kubäd perceived whom the Iranians
<lb/>Agreed to choose: one of them was Ashtad,
<lb/>The other was Kharrad, son of Barzin,
<lb/>The old—two sages eloquent and heedful.
<lb/>Kubad addressed them thus: <q>O ye wise men,
<lb/>Ye chiefs experienced and veteran!
<lb/>Deem not the conduct of the world too toilsome,
<lb/>Because the Great by travail compass treasure.
<lb/>It is for you now to approach the Shah;
<lb/>Perchance through you he may conform himself.
<lb/>Appeal to him by instance new or old
<lb/>As there is need.</q>
</p><p>

<lb/>With tears unwillingly
<lb/>Those sages made them ready. When Kharrad,
<lb/>Son of Barzin, and when Ashtad, who had
<lb/>Gashasp for sire, had mounted on their steeds,
<lb/>As bidden, Kubad said: <q>Now with right good will
<lb/>Tis yours to take the road to Talikan,<note n="1">Couplet omitted.</note>
<lb/>To carry to my glorious sire a message,
<lb/>And bear it all in mind from first to last.
<lb/>Say: <q>Twas no fault of ours nor did the Iranians
<lb/>Cause this, but having left the way of Faith
<lb/>Thou hast thyself incurred God’s chastisement,
<lb/>For, first, no son legitimate will shed
<lb/>His sire’s blood though impure or give assent
<lb/>Thereto and fill the hearts of upright folk
<lb/>With pain. Again, thy treasures fill the world,
<lb/>And thine exactions reach all provinces,
<lb/>While, thirdly, many horsemen brave and famed
<lb/>Within Iran who gladdened there have left
<lb/>Son, country, and their own pure kith and kin,

<pb n="10"/>
<lb/>Have parted, this to Chin and that to Rum,
<lb/>And now are scattered o’er each march and land.
<lb/>Again, when Caesar, who had done and borne
<lb/>So much for thee, had given thee a host
<lb/>And daughter too with treasure and much else,
<lb/>Desired of thee the Cross of Christ for Rum,
<lb/>So that his land might be revived thereby,
<milestone unit="calced" n="2028"/>
<lb/>How did the Cross of Jesus profit so
<lb/>Thy treasures when complaisance on thy part
<lb/>Would have made Caesar glad? But thou didst not
<lb/>Restore it, hadst not wit enough for that,
<lb/>Or one to guide thee to humanity.
<lb/>Again, thy greed was such that wisdom’s eye
<lb/>Was all obscured in thee, and thou didst seize
<lb/>The chattels of the poor whose curses brought
<lb/>Ill on thy head. Thou slewest thy mother’s brothers,<note n="2">Bandwi and Gustaham.</note>
<lb/>Two loyal men who gave thy throne a lustre.
<lb/>Moreover, thou hadst sixteen sons whose days
<lb/>And nights were passed in prison while no chief
<lb/>Could sleep secure from thee but hid in fear.<note n="3">This sentence comes at the end of the speech in the text.</note>
<lb/>Know, that which hath befall’n thee is from God;
<lb/>Reflect on thy foul deeds. As for myself,
<lb/>I am but as the instrument in all
<lb/>This wrong, am but the heading of the tale.
<lb/>By God, ’twas not my fault, no aim of mine
<lb/>To wreck the Shah’s throne! Now for all seek grace,
<lb/>And say so to these chieftains of Iran;
<lb/>Turn from ill deeds to God—the Guide to good—
<lb/>Who may abate the woes that thou hast brought
<lb/>Upon thyself.</q></q>
</p><p>
<lb/>On hearing this the twain
<lb/>Departed with their hearts all seared and sore
<lb/>Till, sorrowful and weeping, they arrived
<lb/>At Talikan and in that city sought

<pb n="11"/>
<lb/>The palace of Marusipand for there
<lb/>The exalted king resided. Galinush
<lb/>Sat at the palace-gate: thou wouldst have said:—
<lb/><q>Earth is convulsed before him!</q> He was armed
<lb/>In helm and breastplate, all the Arab steeds
<lb/>Wore bards, and all his soldiers were drawn up,
<lb/>Equipped, and sword in hand. He grasped a mace
<lb/>Of steel, his heart all fire and storm. Now when
<lb/>Kharrad, son of Barzin, and when Ashtad,
<lb/>Son of Gashasp, those sages twain, dismounted,
<lb/>He rose forthwith, rejoiced to look on them,
<lb/>And gave them place befitting, hailing them
<lb/>As famous chiefs. The eloquent Kharrad
<lb/>First laved his tongue in valour and then said
<lb/>To Galinush: <q>Kubad the glorious
<lb/>Hath donned in peace the Kaian crown. Iran,
<lb/>Turan and Rum have tidings that Shirwi<note n="4">That being the name by which he had been generally known, his real name (Kubad) having been kept secret. See Vol. viii., pp. 371, 416.</note>
<lb/>Is seated on the throne of king of kings.
<lb/>Why this cuirass and helm and massive mace?
<lb/>Who is thine enemy?</q>
</p>
<p>
<lb/>Said Galinush:—

<milestone unit="calced" n="2029"/>
<lb/><q>O veteran! may all thy doings prosper.
<lb/>Thou art concerned about my tender frame
<lb/>Because I am in iron garniture.
<lb/>I bless thee for thy kindness; thou deservest
<lb/>That I shall sprinkle jewels over thee.
<lb/>Thy words are naught but good, and may the sun
<lb/>Be thine associate in the world. Declare
<lb/>Why thou hast come, then look for my reply.</q>
<lb/>He thus gave answer: <q>Glorious Kubad
<lb/>Commissioned me to bear Khusrau Parviz
<lb/>A message and if now thou wilt ask audience<note n="5">Reading with P.</note>
<lb/>I will deliver what the world-lord said—

<pb n="12"/>
<lb/>That monarch of the flock.</q>
<lb/>Said Galinush:—
<lb/><q>Who can remember words so well as thou,
<lb/>O worshipful? Yet nathless Shah Kubad
<lb/>Gave me full many a counsel touching this,
<lb/>And charged me, saying: <q>Let none have by day
<lb/>Or night an audience of Khusrau Parviz
<lb/>Unless thou hearest what the messenger
<lb/>Hath got to say in Persian new or old.</q></q>
<lb/>Ashtad said: <q>I hold not my message secret,
<lb/>O fortunate! It is: <q>The sword is fruiting,
<lb/>And nuzzling princes’ heads.</q> In this regard
<lb/>Now ask for audience of Khusrau Parviz
<lb/>That we may tell the message of the Shah.</q>
<lb/>This hearing Galinush arose, made fast
<lb/>His mail, went to the Shah with folded arms,
<lb/>As servants should, and said thus: <q>Live for ever,
<lb/>O Shah! May evil never vex thy heart.
<lb/>There cometh by Ashtad and by Kharrad,
<lb/>Son of Barzin, a message from the Shah
<lb/>From court.</q>
<lb/>Khusrau Parviz laughed out and said:—
<lb/><q>Speak wiser words for if he be the king
<lb/>Then what am I, and why am I within
<lb/>This narrow prison, and why need’st thou ask
<lb/>That I shall grant an audience unto any,
<lb/>Be their words false or true?</q>
<lb/>So Galinush
<lb/>Returned to those two warriors, reported
<lb/>The answer of the paladin, and said:—
<lb/><q>Now go with folded arms, declare your message,
<lb/>And hearken his reply.</q>
<lb/>Those sages twain
<lb/>Of honest speech inswathed their visages
<lb/>In sashes brought from Chin and, when they saw
<lb/>The Shah, did reverence and waited long

<pb n="13"/>
<lb/>What while he sat upon a lofty throne
<lb/>Adorned with effigies of sheep and wolves,
<lb/>Impleached with gold and gems, with under him
<lb/>A couch of yellow broidery. He leaned
<lb/>On cushions hued like lapis-lazuli,
<lb/>Held a fine quince and drowsed there all amort.
<milestone unit="calced" n="2030"/>
<lb/>When he beheld those chiefs supreme in wisdom
<lb/>He roused himself and secretly invoked
<lb/>God’s help. He laid that: fine quince on the cushions
<lb/>That he might welcome those two wayfarers.<note><cit><quote xml:lang="fra">ces deux esclaves.</quote> <bibl>Mohl.</bibl></cit></note>
<lb/>The quince slipped from the cushions, rolled unbruised
<lb/>Upon the'cduch and thence from throne to floor.
<lb/>Ashtäd tan, took it up, wiped off the dust,
<lb/>And laid the quince upon his head. The world-lord
<lb/>Turned front Ashtad that he might neither see
<lb/>Nor scent the quince. They set it on the throne,
<lb/>And stood themselves. The matter of the quince<note>Reading with P.</note>
<lb/>Perturbed Khusrau Parwiz who boded ill,
<lb/>Looked up to heaven, and said: <q> O truthful Judge!
<lb/>Who can establish one whom Thou o’erthrowest,
<lb/>Who join what Thou hast broken? When bright fortune 
<lb/>Departeth from a race it bringeth sorrow
<lb/>Because the day of joy is passed away.</q>
</p><p>
<lb/>Then to Ashtäd : <q> Now for thine ambassage
<lb/>From mine unnatural child of ill repute,
<lb/>And from that handful of conspirators,
<lb/>My hateful and black-hearted enemies.
<lb/>Malignant fools are they and in their folly
<lb/>Most wretched. Fortune will desert our race ;
<lb/>None will rejoice again; the crown and throne
<lb/>Will pass to those unfit ; this royal Tree
<lb/>Will be destroyed ; the Base will be exalted ;
<lb/>The spirits of the Great grow sorrowful.




<pb n="14"/>

<lb/>The majesty will bide not with our sons,
<lb/>Or with our kindred or posterity ;
<lb/>Their friends all be their chiefest enemies,
<lb/>Revilers and destroyers of the race.
<lb/>This quince hath made the secret evident ;
<lb/>The throne of king of kings will bear no fruit.
<lb/>Now tell to me the words that thou hast heard :
<lb/>I count his less than water in the stream.</q> 
<lb/>Then those two men released their tongues to speak,
<lb/>And told all that Kubad, his son, had said,
<lb/>Not keeping e’en a whisper back from him. 
<lb/>The king of kings, when he had hcard the message,
<lb/>Writhed with distress and heaved a deep, cold sigh.
<lb/>Then said he to those chiefs: <q> Hear my résporise,
<lb/>And bear it to the young prince, every word.
<lb/>Say : <q>Quit thine own misdeeds ere blaming others.
<lb/>What thou hast uttered are they words of thine ?
<lb/>A murrain on the prompter !<note>Reading with P. and T.</note> Speak not so

<milestone unit="calced" n="2031"/>
<lb/>As to rejoice thy foe with thy fool’s talk,
<lb/>And let him learn that thou hast not the wisdom
<lb/>To furnish speech with knowledge from thy brains.
<lb/>If thy trust is in words that profit not
<lb/>Thou mak’st default in soul and wisdom too.
<lb/>He that shall call thee wicked, then acknowledge
<lb/>Thee to be world-lord, should not sit before thee,
<lb/>And order matters whether great or small.
<lb/>Think not in future of such messages
<lb/>Or thou wilt cause thy foemen to rejoice.
<lb/>My state hath been appointed me by God ;
<lb/>My hopes are set upon the other world,
<lb/>And thou by these thy charges which are lics
<lb/>Wilt gain no glory in the nobles’ eyes.</q></q>


</p></div>

<pb n="15"/>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><head>How Khusrau Parwiz answered Shiruwi</head>
<p>
<lb/><q>Now will I make full answer that thou mayst
<lb/>Repeat my words in public. They will serve
<lb/>As my memorial when I am gone—
<lb/>A truthful statement of my case—and thou
<lb/>Wilt know, when I reveal my grief and travail,
<lb/>That all my treasures were derived from toil.
<lb/>Thou speakest in the first place of Hurmuz,
<lb/>His anger with me, and those bygone days:
<lb/>My father’s wrath against us was aroused
<lb/>By slanderer’s words and thus confusion came.
<lb/>When I had learned what occupied his thoughts
<lb/>I left Iran—by night, avoiding roads.
<lb/>He sought my death by poison; I perceived
<lb/>No antidote but flight and so I fled,
<lb/>And was not taken in the net of bale.
<lb/>I heard that ill had come upon the Shah,
<lb/>And quitted Barda’ when the news arrived.
<lb/>That knave Bahram Chubina with his troops
<lb/>Opposed us on the battlefield. I fled
<lb/>From him too on the day of fight that I
<lb/>Might fall not in his clutches. Afterwards
<lb/>I came a second time and bravely fought,
<lb/>My troublous fortune passed away and all
<lb/>The realm that I had lost returned to me.
<lb/>My contest with him was no brief affair;
<lb/>The whole world were spectators of the strife.
<lb/>By the command of God who multiplieth
<lb/>His benefits on us, and is the Guide
<lb/>In good and ill, Iran and Turkistan<note>Turan in the text.</note>

<pb n="16"/>
<lb/>Submitted and Bahram Chubina’s plans
<lb/>Were foiled. Released from war with him I hastened,
<lb/>First, to take vengeance for my father’s death.
<milestone unit="calced" n="2032"/>
<lb/>Bandwi and Gustaham, my mother’s brothers,
<lb/>Men that had not a peer in any land,
<lb/>Had risked their lives for me and were all mine
<lb/>In love as well as kinship, but there were
<lb/>My father’s death and mine own grief thereat;
<lb/>I was not sluggish to avenge his blood.
<lb/>I lopped Bandwi both hand and foot for he
<lb/>Had made the Shah’s place dark, while Gustaham,
<lb/>Who disappeared and sought some distant nook,
<lb/>Was slain all unawares by my command:
<lb/>Those murderers’ lives and aims all came to naught.
<lb/>Next, as to what thou said’st of thine own case,
<lb/>Of thine own strait confinement and affairs;
<lb/>It was to keep my sons from evil deeds
<lb/>That would recoil upon themselves. Ye were
<lb/>Not straitly bound in prison, not misprized,
<lb/>And had no harm to fear, I did not then
<lb/>Treat you with scorn but held my treasury
<lb/>At your disposal, acting as the Shahs
<lb/>Had done before, not idly or without
<lb/>A precedent. Chase, minstrelsy, and polo—
<lb/>All that befitteth chiefs—were yours at will,
<lb/>With hawks and cheetahs, jewels and dinars.
<lb/>Your so-called prison was a palace where
<lb/>Ye lived in joy. I dreaded thee moreover
<lb/>Through what the readers of the stars had said.
<lb/>That was the cause of thine imprisonment
<lb/>That thou mightst do us naught of injury—
<lb/>The very injury that thou art doing.
<lb/>I never parted with thy horoscope
<lb/>Till I had sealed and given it to Shirin.

<pb n="17"/>
<lb/>When I had reigned for six and thirty years,
<lb/>And thou past doubt amidst such pleasant days
<lb/>Gav’st all the matter to the wind, although
<lb/>Much time had passed o’er us, there came to thee
<lb/>A letter out of Hindustan but not
<lb/>Without my cognizance. The chief of Rajas
<lb/>Sent us a letter, jewels, divers stuffs,
<lb/>An Indian scimitar, white elephant,
<lb/>And all that I could hope for in the world,
<lb/>And with the scimitar was gold brocade
<lb/>With all varieties of gems uncut.
<lb/>To thee the letter was on painted silk;
<lb/>So when I saw the Indian script I called
<lb/>An Indian scribe, a fluent, heedful speaker,
<lb/>Who when he read the Indian Raja’s words
<lb/>Wept for the letter ran: <q>Live joyfully
<lb/>For thou art worthy both of joy and realm,
<milestone unit="calced" n="2033"/>
<lb/>And on the day of Dai in month Azar
<lb/>Thou wilt be king and ruler of the world.
<lb/>Thy sire will reign for eight and thirty years,
<lb/>For so the stars ordain. Good times will shine
<lb/>Upon thee; thou wilt don the crown of greatness.</q>
<lb/>These words have been fulfilled to me to-day,
<lb/>But we should wash not from our hearts affection.
<lb/>I was aware that fortune had decreed
<lb/>That when thy throne had gained its brilliancy
<lb/>Mine only portion would be toil and pain,
<lb/>And that my bright day would be turned to gloom;
<lb/>But as I gave, had Faith, made friends, and loved
<lb/>I did not lour by reason of that letter.
<lb/>I gave it, having read it, to Shirin,
<lb/>And pondered much upon it. In her keeping
<lb/>Are both the letter and the horoscope,
<lb/>And no one great or small is ware thereof.
<lb/>If thou wouldst see it make request of her;
<lb/>Thou haply mayst regard it more or less.
<lb/>I wot that seeing it thou wilt repent,
<lb/>And seek to heal the past. For what thou said’st

<pb n="18"/>
<lb/>Of bonds and of imprisonments, and how
<lb/>We have done others hurt, ’tis this world’s way,
<lb/>And that of former chiefs and kings of kings,
<lb/>And if thou know’st it not speak with an archmage;
<lb/>He will enlighten thee thereon and tell thee:—
<lb/><q>Tis ill to keep God’s enemy alive.</q>



<lb/>Those that were in our prison were mere divs
<lb/>Complained of by the righteous. Neither bloodshed
<lb/>Nor utter harshness ever was our trade.
<lb/>I shut up criminals and did not hold
<lb/>Of small account wrongs ‘done by them to others;
<lb/>But now I hear that thou hast freed these men—
<lb/>Men worse than dragons—and for this thou art
<lb/>A sinner guilty both in word and deed
<lb/>In God’s sight. Now that thou art lord be prudent,
<lb/>And if thou know’st not how consult the wise.
<lb/>Forgive not those that vex thee though thou hopest
<lb/>For wealth through them, and what can better bonds
<lb/>For one in whom thou seest naught but harm?
<lb/>In talking of my wealth thou hast not shown
<lb/>Good sense and wisdom. We have never asked
<lb/>For more than toll and tax. When these were paid
<lb/>If any were still rich, though men might say
<lb/>That they were foes and miscreants of the seed
<lb/>Of Ahriman, we thought of God and passed
<lb/>Such matters lightly by. From Him I had
<lb/>The crown and throne, and they have cost me dear.
<milestone unit="calced" n="2034"/>
<lb/>The Maker of the world, the righteous Judge,
<lb/>Hath willed this change of fortune. In the world
<lb/>His will is paramount, so when He would
<lb/>Our minishment we seek not for addition.
<lb/>We sought to please our Judge, but by our toils
<lb/>Have not evaded His apportionment,
<lb/>And when He asketh me I will tell all.
<lb/>That Questioner is wiser than thou art,
<lb/>And one more potent in all good and ill.

<pb n="19"/>
<lb/>The miscreants that stand before thee now
<lb/>Are not thy friends or kin, and what they say
<lb/>Of me that also will they say of thee
<lb/>Before thy foes. They are but slaves of gold
<lb/>And silver: thou wilt find in them no helper.
<lb/>They have possessed thy heart and there instilled
<lb/>Each fault of mine. Such words as these are not
<lb/>In thy philosophy and will not profit
<lb/>Those miscreants’ minds, but I have uttered them
<lb/>For my foes’ sake that they who read this letter,
<lb/>Writ in the ancient tongue, may know that lies
<lb/>Lack lustre even from the mouths of Shahs.
<lb/>Twill be too a memorial in the world,
<lb/>A consolation to the man of wisdom,
<lb/>And after our decease whoever shall read
<lb/>These words of ours will learn our policy.
<lb/>I gathered armies from Bartas and Chin,
<lb/>And everywhere appointed generals,
<lb/>Then made attacks upon mine enemies
<lb/>Till none dared raise his head. When they were scattered,
<lb/>Our treasuries were all filled. The whole land toiled
<lb/>For us, and from the sea so many gems
<lb/>Were brought us that the shipmen grew aweary.
<lb/>Plain, sea, and mountain, all were mine. Now when
<lb/>The treasury of drachms had been expended
<lb/>The coffers were refilled with new dinars,
<lb/>With precious stones and royal jewelry,
<lb/>As well as clothes and implements of war,
<lb/>And when our crown was twenty-six years old
<lb/>Our treasuries were rich with many gems.
<lb/>I struck a new die for my drachms and turned
<lb/>To joy and merriment. That year when I
<lb/>Had ta’en account I found the total sum
<lb/>Ten million of dinars. Paidawasis,<note>See Vol. vii., p. 95 note.</note>

<pb n="20"/>
<lb/>In Persian reckoning, I spent and squandered.
<lb/>Each purse contained twelve thousand in dinars,
<lb/>And those thus spent were royal, while besides
<lb/>The tribute and dinars from Hindustan,
<lb/>The realm of Rum and land of sorcerers;
<lb/>Besides from every province gifts and tribute
<lb/>From all the sovereigns and potentates;
<lb/>Besides New Year and Autumn offerings,
<lb/>The gifts of horses and of fair-faced slaves;
<lb/>Besides cuirasses, helmets, axes, swords,
<lb/>Which everyone sent to us liberally;
<milestone unit="calced" n="2035"/>
<lb/>Besides musk, camphor, sables, beaver-skins,
<lb/>Red weasels’ and white wolves’, our subjects all
<lb/>Set suchlike loads upon their beasts and sought
<lb/>Our court in haste; none was recalcitrant.
<lb/>Abundant toil of all sorts have we spent
<lb/>To amass a treasure—one additional
<lb/>To those known as Khuzra and as ’Arus,<note>See Vol. viii., p. 406.</note>
<lb/>Reserved by me against an evil day.


<lb/>We long discussed what name the hoard should have,
<lb/>And in the end we called it Bad Awar.<note>See Vol. viii., p. 406.</note>
<lb/>Thus in my six and twentieth year of reign
<lb/>Heaven till the eight and thirtieth favoured me;
<lb/>My chieftains were all safe, my foes all quaked,
<lb/>And now I hear that thou art sovereign—
<lb/>An evil juncture this for all the world,
<lb/>Which reft of pleasure must perforce be mute.
<lb/>Thou wilt make earth calamitous, fulfilled
<lb/>With suffering and profitless. Moreover,
<lb/>Those same injurious persons that surround thee,
<lb/>And are the Light<note>Urmuzd in text.</note> of thy dark nights, will give
<lb/>Thy throne up to the wind that thou mayst not
<lb/>Enjoy the world. Were there with thee a sage,
<lb/>So that thy darkened mind might be illumed,
<lb/>Thou wouldst not do amiss in giving gifts

<pb n="21"/>
<lb/>So that thy wealth might reach the poor. My son,
<lb/>Whose days are few, whose wisdom is but scant!
<lb/>Solicitude will rob thy soul of joy.
<lb/>This know, that these our treasures are thy stay;
<lb/>The opportunity is in thy grasp.
<lb/>They are the appanage of royalty;
<lb/>A world that is all moneyless is lost.
<lb/>A pauper Shah will be unjust, and he
<lb/>Whose hand is empty hath no strength or worth.
<lb/>Without the means of largess he by all
<lb/>Will be declared a fraud and not a Shah.
<lb/>Moreover, if thy riches reach thy foes,
<lb/>And all the idols come to Brahmans’ hands,
<lb/>The worshippers will turn from God, thy name
<lb/>And fame be spurned. If thou art treasureless
<lb/>Thou wilt not have an army, and thy subjects
<lb/>Will hail thee not as Shah. The dog is good
<lb/>At begging bread, but if thou fillest him
<lb/>He threateneth thy life. Again, thou said’st
<lb/>About my strategy that I have stationed
<lb/>The troops along the roads, and blamest me
<lb/>Through ignorance, not knowing gain from loss.
<milestone unit="calced" n="2036"/>
<lb/>The answer is that by my toil I gathered
<lb/>My splendid treasures, captured foreign cities,
<lb/>And shattered all my foes that we might sit
<lb/>Without vexation, toil, or injury
<lb/>In peace upon the pleasant throne. I scattered
<lb/>My horse about the frontier, and (to show
<lb/>The difference ’twixt the worthless and the worthy)
<lb/>When thou recall’st the troops from every side
<lb/>The foe will see the road clear, for Iran
<lb/>Is like a garden in the jocund Spring,
<lb/>Whose happy blossoms never fail to flower,
<lb/>A garden of pomegranate and narcissus,
<lb/>Of apples and of quince; but when the orchard
<lb/>Becometh void of men the enemy

<pb n="22"/>
<lb/>Will root up all the marjoram and snap
<lb/>All branches of pomegranate and of quince.
<lb/>Iran's walls are its troops and gear of war,
<lb/>Its thorns all arrows on its battlements,
<lb/>And if in wantonness thou flingest down
<lb/>The garden-wall the garden is as waste,
<lb/>As sea or upland. Cast not down its wall
<lb/>Or thou wilt break the Iranians’ hearts and backs,
<lb/>For then will raid and ravage, horsemen’s shouts,
<lb/>And all the incidents of war ensue.
<lb/>Expose not thou our children, wives, and land
<lb/>To trouble: let but one such year elapse,
<lb/>And sages will describe thee as a fool.
<lb/>Now I have heard that thou dost give high place
<lb/>To men unworthy. Know that Nushirwan,
<lb/>Son of Kubad,<note>Reading with P. and T.</note> recorded in his Letter
<lb/>Of Counsel that whoever doth give his arms
<lb/>To foes doth give himself to slaughtering,
<lb/>Since, when he asketh back those arms for use,
<lb/>The enemy will fight.<note>See Vol. viii. p. 27.</note> As for the message
<lb/>Of Caesar, which hath made thee call me heartless,
<lb/>And self-willed. thou recallest not the facts:
<lb/>Thy words were prompted by some counsellor.
<lb/>As for my tyranny and his good faith,
<lb/>Canst thou discern good faith from tyranny?
<lb/>Receive mine answer, thou of little wit!
<lb/>But let me say withal, as is but right,
<lb/>Thou art the plaintiff and the witness too—
<lb/>A thing no man of wisdom would allow.
<lb/>When Caesar washed off from his face the dust
<lb/>Of bale he chose me as his son-in-law
<lb/>For valour’s sake. Whoever walketh not
<lb/>The earth for ill, and hath some share of wisdom
<lb/>Within him, knoweth that Bahram Chubina
<lb/>Began the feud and that the Iranians

<pb n="23"/>
<lb/>Took sides with him. The Romans did not triumph
<lb/>Over him; the drifting sand cannot bind fast
<lb/>The mountain! But in that fight God vouchsafed
<lb/>To aid me, and the armies of the world
<lb/>Were naught to me. The Iranians have heard <milestone unit="calced" n="2037"/>
<lb/>Of those events, and thou shouldst hear from them.
<lb/>As for myself, I did whatever I could,
<lb/>Upon the day of fight, for Niyatus
<lb/>With kindness and with magnanimity,
<lb/>But have not reckoned that day’s recompense,
<lb/>And Farrukhzad will tell thee just the same:
<lb/>Look not upon the world with boyish eyes.
<lb/>Gashasp, who was our treasurer, can tell,
<lb/>And that good archmage, our minister,
<lb/>That I bestowed upon the Roman troops
<lb/>A hundred thousand purses from our treasures:
<lb/>I gave to Niyatus a thousand nuggets,
<lb/>With earrings and red gold. Each nugget’s weight
<lb/>Was as a thousand treasury-miskals
<lb/>I reckoned. I bestowed on him withal
<lb/>Fine watered pearls that experts had found flawless,
<lb/>And every one worth thirty thousand drachms
<lb/>To jewellers, and five score noble steeds,
<lb/>Selected from my stables—fifty saddled,
<lb/>The others very choice, housed in brocade,
<lb/>Mates for the wind upon the waste. I sent
<lb/>All these to Caesar with my thanks withal.
<lb/>For what thou said’st about the Cross of Christ,
<lb/>That bit of old wood flung among my treasures—
<lb/>A matter of no loss or gain to me—
<lb/>Thou hast been listening to some Christian’s talk.
<lb/>I mused that one like Caesar, great and mighty,
<lb/>Surrounded as he is by learned men—
<lb/>Philosophers and potentates and priests—
<lb/>Should call one that was executed God!
<lb/>While as for this dry, rotten wood, if this

<pb n="24"/>
<lb/>Mere useless Cross were God it would be Urmuzd,
<lb/>Whose name we give to every month’s first day,
<lb/>And would have vanished from our treasury
<lb/>As Christ himself departed from the world.
<lb/>Again for what thou said’st: <q>Make thine excuse,
<lb/>Amend thy conduct and ensue God's path,</q>
<lb/>I answer: <q>May the two hands of Kubad,
<lb/>His feet and lips and tongue rot! It was God
<lb/>Who placed the crown upon my head: I took,
<lb/>And revelled in the gift. I have returned it
<lb/>Since He demanded it. What next I wonder?
<lb/>To Him will I confess, not to a boy
<lb/>Scarce able to distinguish good and ill.</q>
<lb/>All that God doth is welcome unto me
<lb/>Though I have seen much woe and bitterness.
<lb/>For eight and thirty years have I been Shah,
<lb/>And none among the kings hath been my peer.
<lb/>He that bestowed this world on me may give
<lb/>Another but will have no thanks of mine!
<milestone unit="calced" n="2038"/>
<lb/>I will pronounce a blessing on the realm:—
<lb/><q>May earth be ever teeming with the wise.</q>
<lb/>So long as God shall help and succour us
<lb/>None will dare curse.</q>
</p>
<p>
<lb/>Then said he to Kharrad:—
<lb/><q>O Memory of the great ones of the world!
<lb/>Say to that foolish and impetuous boy:—
<lb/><q>The lustre of our countenance is dimmed:
<lb/>Farewell to thee for ever. As for me,
<lb/>May all our converse be henceforth with sages.</q>
<lb/>As for yourselves, illustrious messengers,
<lb/>Ye Persians eloquent and eminent!
<lb/>To both of you I also bid farewell.
<lb/>Say nothing but the words that ye have heard.
<lb/>I give my blessing to the world at large,
<lb/>Which we have looked on as a passing thing.
<lb/>All mother-born must die—whome’er thou hast

<pb n="25"/>
<lb/>In mind—Khusrau Parwiz back to Kubad.
<lb/>So too Hushang, Jamshid, and Tahmuras—
<lb/>To all the world the founts of fear and hope—
<lb/>Whom div and beast acknowledged, passed and died
<lb/>When their day ended. Faridun, the blest,
<lb/>Who banned ill, close or open, from the world,
<lb/>And stayed Zahhak the Arab’s hand from evil,
<lb/>Escaped not by bravery the clutch of fate.
<lb/>So was it with Arish whose arrow’s flight
<lb/>Was one farsang;<note>Much further according to the legend. See Vol. v., p. 12.</note> victorious Karan,
<lb/>The capturer of cities; Kai Kubad,
<lb/>Who having come from Mount Alburz became
<lb/>Through manhood world-lord over all the folk,
<lb/>And built himself a world-famed house of crystal,<note>This is attributed to Kai Kaus elsewhere. See Vol. ti., pp. 81, 1017.</note>
<lb/>Adorned with lustrous pearls and gates of gems.<note>This line occurs three couplets too low in C.</note>
<lb/>So was it with Kaus, that man of might,
<lb/>Who took the world by skill and policy,
<lb/>He that adventured toward the sky above,
<lb/>Unwitting of the processes of time;
<lb/>So too with Siyawush, that lion famed,
<lb/>Who slew two tigers in his youthful days,<note>This is not mentioned elsewhere in the poem.</note>
<lb/>And built Gang-dizh<note>See Vol. ii., pp. 189, 279.</note> with toil but got therefrom
<lb/>No treasure. Where are now Afrasiyab,
<lb/>The Turkman king, whose semblance e’en in dream
<lb/>None seeth; where Rustam, Zal, Asfandiyar,
<lb/>Whose fame is their memorial with us;
<lb/>Gudarz and his choice sons, three score and ten,
<lb/>Those cavaliers upon the riding-ground,
<lb/>And lions of the fray; where Kai Khusrau,
<lb/>The noble lion-man who in the fight
<lb/>Made lions prisoners; and Shah Gushtasp,
<lb/>The convert to <q>The Good Faith,</q> he by whom

<pb n="26"/>
<lb/>Grace was renewed; where went renowned Alexander,
<lb/>Who overturned the world, and where Jamasp,
<lb/>Who shone in astrologic lore more brightly
<milestone unit="calced" n="2039"/>
<lb/>Than Sol or Venus? Where is that famed Shah,
<lb/>Bahram Gur, matchless in his strength and courage?
<lb/>No Shah was like him in munificence;
<lb/>The turning heaven dared not to touch his head.
<lb/>Where is that Shah, my grandsire, bright of soul
<lb/>Who ruled the world as Kisra Nushirwan?
<lb/>Where are the seven and forty world-lords?<note>Khusrau Parwiz was only the forty-third Shah. Perhaps some, who never became Shahs, such as Siyawush and Asfandiyar, are included, or it may be that the author of this defence (see p. 4) wrote from his own point of view, not that of the supposed speaker.</note> Gone
<lb/>Is all their work, gone are the Great and Wise,
<lb/>The warrior-horsemen and the men of lore,
<lb/>These passing those in prowess and those these
<lb/>In years? They all have left this spacious world,
<lb/>Left palace, hall, and riding-ground. Midst Shahs,
<lb/>Though some were older far, I had no peer.
<lb/>I walked the world for good and ill, and held
<lb/>The evil day aloof. 'Twas mine to traverse
<lb/>Full many a rugged path and sweep away
<lb/>Full many a foe. My treasures fill all lands;
<lb/>Where earth and water are my toil is seen.
<lb/>When with me too the world shall cease, and all
<lb/>The nobles’ hopes grow dim, with my son also
<lb/>The throne will not abide, for he will quit it,
<lb/>And all his fortune end. What time the angel
<lb/>That taketh souls approacheth I shall say:—
<lb/><q>Take my soul gently.</q> I will clear my heart
<lb/>By penitence, and freedom from offence
<lb/>Shall be my breastplate. Well have men of wisdom,
<lb/>Good, veteran, learned, declared: <q>If wakeful fortune
<lb/>Decline one must expect fears manifold,
<lb/>And he whose day of greatness hath gone by

<pb n="27"/>
<lb/>Is foolish if he asketh its return.</q>
<lb/>This is my message to the world, to mean
<lb/>And mighty too: ere long the Shah and all
<lb/>His famous troops will fall to slaughtering
<lb/>Each other and fling fire on field and fell;
<lb/>Then sires will fall by sons and sons by sires;
<lb/>Our enemies, the people that discoursed
<lb/>Of evil deeds and chilling words, will pay
<lb/>The smart when we are gone and not for long
<lb/>Enjoy the world. Since rule and greatness end
<lb/>With me what reck if Lion or another
<lb/>Shall have the sway?</q>
</p>
<p>
<lb/>Ashtad and brave Kharrad,
<lb/>Son of Barzin, those sages, when they heard
<lb/>The message of that leader, were heart-pierced,
<lb/>And smote their heads. Both sorrowed for their words;
<milestone unit="calced" n="2040"/>
<lb/>They buffeted their faces, rent their robes
<lb/>In grief, and scattered dust upon their heads.
<lb/>Those ancients fared forth from his presence, weeping,
<lb/>In anguish, with their hearts all arrow-points.
<lb/>With furrowed faces and in sore distress
<lb/>They went before Shiruwi and every whit
<lb/>To that man brainless and incompetent
<lb/>Detailed the message that the Shah had sent.
</p>

</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><head>How Shirwi grieved for Khusrau Parwiz and how the Chiefs were displeased thereat</head>
<p>
<lb/>Shirwi wept bitterly on hearing this;
<lb/>His heart quaked for the crown and throne, and when
<lb/>The company dispersed that had dismayed him

<pb n="28"/>
<lb/>With foul words clamouring for his father’s blood,
<lb/>And burning the youth’s heart, he left the throne
<lb/>Of kingship, clasped with honoured hands his head,
<lb/>And wept blood on his breast. News of that weeping
<lb/>And of the lamentation of the king,
<lb/>Came to the host and all were in dismay.
<lb/>They met, discussed Khusrau Parwiz, and cried:—
<lb/><q>If he shall sit upon the throne again
<lb/>He will disgrace the captains of the host.</q>
</p>
<p>
<lb/>Whenas the sun rose o’er the darksome hills
<lb/>The malcontents awoke and went to court.
<lb/>The Shah, on hearing of it, took his seat
<lb/>Upon the throne, and those of high degree,
<lb/>Akin or alien, approached the presence.
<lb/>They took their seats with scowls but no one spoke.
<lb/>The king said: <q>Gibbeting is the desert
<lb/>Of him that mourneth not my father’s woes.
<lb/>I call such misbegotten and a knave.
<lb/>Let none depend on such because that man
<lb/>Is rottener than a rotten willow-tree.</q>
</p>
<p>
<lb/>He got this answer from the men in fault:—
<lb/><q>Call whosoever saith: <q>I serve two Shahs</q>
<lb/>A fool at heart and vile whate’er his rank.</q>
</p>
<p>
<lb/>Shirwi rejoined: <q>For Shahs no wealth, no troops!
<lb/>For one month we will utter pleasant words,
<lb/>And give no hint of duress to my sire;
<lb/>He may make statements that will gladden us
<lb/>Because his treasures are in every coast.</q>
<milestone unit="calced" n="2041"/>
<lb/>On hearing this they rose to seek their homes.
<lb/>Then Shah Shirwi gave orders to the cooks:—
<lb/><q>Let nothing be denied Khusrau Parwiz:
<lb/>Serve up his food upon a golden service,
<lb/>And let the food itself be rich and grateful.</q>
</p>
<p>
<lb/>The servers brought it but he would not eat
<lb/>The viands that were proffered, hot or cold.
<lb/>Shirin’s hand brought to him all that he ate

<pb n="29"/>
<lb/>Because she sorrowed with him in his grief.
<lb/>She was his sole good friend and soothed his woes
<lb/>Both day and night, shared all his hopes and fears,
<lb/>And quaked for him like willow in the wind.
</p>
<p>
<lb/>A month passed and meanwhile Khusrau Parwiz
<lb/>Was full of pain and anguish night and day,
<lb/>His faults and crimes recalled to memory,
<lb/>And little relish of that life had he.
</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><head>How Barbad lamented Khusrau Parwiz, cut off his own Fingers, and burned his Instruments of Music</head>
<p>
<lb/>Now list the lamentation of Barbad,<note>For the story of Barbad see Vol. viii., p. 396 seq.</note>
<lb/>And grow forgetful of the world at large.
<lb/>On hearing that the Shah, not by advice
<lb/>And ’gainst his will, no longer filled the throne,
<lb/>That <q>men are seeking how to murder him;
<lb/>The soldiers are renouncing fealty,</q>
<lb/>Barbad came from Chahram to Taisafun
<lb/>With tearful eyes and heart o’ercharged; he came
<lb/>To that abode and saw the Shah whereat
<lb/>His tulip-cheeks became like fenugreek.
<lb/>He bode awhile in presence of the Shah,
<lb/>Then went with wailing to the audience-hall.
<lb/>His love flamed in his heart, his heart and soul
<lb/>Burned in his anguish for Khusrau Parwiz;
<lb/>His eyes rained like a cloud in Spring and made
<lb/>His bosom as the margent of the sea.
<lb/>He fashioned him a dirge upon the harp,
<lb/>And to that dirge he sang a mournful plaint.
</p>
<p>
<pb n="30"/>
<lb/>With visage wan and heart fulfilled with grief
<lb/>He thus lamented in the olden tongue:—
</p>
<q>
<lg>
<l>O Shah! O noble chieftain! O Khusrau!</l>
<l>My great! O strong! O hero ne’er cast down!</l>
<l>Where are thy mastery and greatness now,</l>
<l>Where all thy Grace, thy fortune, and thy crown?</l>
</lg>
<lg>
<l>Where that imperial circlet, towering height?</l>
<l>Where are thine armlets and thine ivory throne?</l>
<l>Where all thy manliness, thy Grace, and might,</l>
<l>Who ’neath thy wings hadst this world for thine own?</l>
</lg>
<lg>
<l>Oh! whither are thy dames and minstrels gone,</l>
<l>Gate, audience-hall, and leaders of thy day,</l>
<milestone unit="calced" n="2042"/>
<l>The diadem and Kawa’s gonfalon,</l>
<l>And all the blue-steel falchions, where are they?</l>
</lg>
<lg>
<l>Where are the head, the crown that loved it well—</l>
<l>Mate of the earrings and the throne of gold?</l>
<l>Where are Shabdiz, his stirrups and his sell.—-</l>
<l>The steed that ’neath thee ever caracoled?</l>
</lg>
<lg>
<l>Where are thy helmet, head, and habergeon</l>
<l>All golden and compacted gem to gem,</l>
<l>Thy cavaliers in gold caparison,</l>
<l>Whose swords made enemies the sheaths for them?</l>
</lg>
<lg>
<l>Where all the camels for thy progresses,</l>
<l>The golden litters and attendance rife,</l>
<l>Led steeds, white elephants, and dromedaries?</l>
<l>Have one and all grown hopeless of thy life?</l>
</lg>
<pb n="31"/>
<lg>
<l>Where are thy fluent tongue and courteous,</l>
<l>Thy heart, thy purpose, and thine ardent soul?</l>
<l>Why reft of all art thou abandoned thus?</l>
<l>Hast read of such a day in any roll?</l>
</lg>
<lg>
<l>Oh! trust not to this world whose remedy</l>
<l>Is weaker than its bane. 'Twas thy desire</l>
<l>To have a son to aid and succour thee:</l>
<l>Now through the son the gyves are on the sire!</l>
</lg>
<lg>
<l>It is by sons that kings obtain their might,</l>
<l>And are unblemished by time’s travails;</l>
<l>Yet ever as his sons increased in height</l>
<l>Both Grace and vigour failed the king of kings.</l>
</lg>
<lg>
<l>None that shall lend an ear while men recall</l>
<l>The story of Khusrau Parwiz must dare</l>
<l>To trust the world. Account as ruined all</l>
<l>Iran and as the pards’ and lions’ lair.</l>
</lg>
<lg>
<l>Of the Sasanian race the Shah was head—</l>
<l>One peerless in the sight of crown and state:</l>
<l>The foeman’s wishes are accomplished,</l>
<l>And, like Iran, the race is desolate.</l>
</lg>
<lg>
<l>No man possessed a larger host than he,</l>
<l>Yet who had cause for justice to beseech?</l>
<l>The great protector brought the misery,</l>
<l>And now the wolves are making for the breach!</l>
</lg>
<lg>
<l><q/>O Shah devoid of shame!<q/> thus tell Shirwi,</l>
<l><q/>Such conduct is not worthy of this court.</l>
<l>Count not upon thy troops’ fidelity</l>
<l>When war is rife on all sides.<q/> God support</l>
</lg>
<pb n="32"/>
<lg>
<l>Thy soul, my master! and it is my prayer</l>
<l>That He thy foemen’s heads may headlong fling.</l>
<l>By God and by thy life, my king! I swear</l>
<l>By New Year’s Day, by sun, and jocund Spring,</l>
</lg>
<lg>
<l>If e’er this hand of mine again shall turn</l>
<l>To harping may no blessing light on me;</l>
<l>Mine instruments of music will I burn</l>
<l>That I may ne’er behold thine enemy.</l>
</lg>
</q>
<p>
<lb/>He cut four fingers off and grasped the stumps
<lb/>Within his other palm. Returning home
<lb/>He kindled fire and burned his instruments,
<lb/>While those about Kubad both day and night
<lb/>At all that might befall them quaked with fright.
</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><head>How the Chiefs demanded from Shirwi the Death of Khusrau Parwiz and how he was slain by Mihr Hurmuzd</head>
<p>
<milestone unit="calced" n="2043"/>
<lb/>Shirwi, a timid, inexperienced youth,
<lb/>Found that the throne beneath him was a snare,
<lb/>While readers of mankind saw that ’twas time
<lb/>For men of might. Those that had done the ill,
<lb/>And had produced that coil, went from the hall
<lb/>Of audience to the presence of Kubad
<lb/>To mind him of their infamous designs:—
<lb/><q>We said before and now we say again
<lb/>Thy thoughts are not on government alone.
<lb/>There are two Shahs now seated in one room,
<lb/>One on the throne and one on its degree,

<pb n="33"/>
<lb/>And when relations grow ’twixt sire and son
<lb/>They will behead the servants one and all.
<lb/>It may not be, so speak of it no more.</q>
<lb/>Shirwi was frightened and he played poltroon
<lb/>Because in their hands he was as a slave.
<lb/>He answered: <q>None will bring him to the toils
<lb/>Except a man whose name is infamous.
<lb/>Ye must go homeward and advise thereon.
<lb/>Inquire: <q>What man is there that will abate
<lb/>Our troubles secretly?</q></q>
<lb/>The Shah’s<note>Khusrau Parwiz</note> ill-wishers
<lb/>Sought for a murderer to murder him
<lb/>By stealth, but none possessed the pluck or courage
<lb/>To shed the blood of such a king and hang
<lb/>A mountain round his own neck. Everywhere
<lb/>The Shah’s foes sought until they met with one
<lb/>Blue-eyed, pale-cheeked, his body parched and hairy,
<lb/>With lips of lapis-lazuli, with feet
<lb/>All dust, and belly ravenous; the head
<lb/>Of that ill-doer was bare. None knew his name
<lb/>Midst high and low. This villain (may he never
<lb/>See jocund Paradise!) sought Farrukhzad,
<lb/>And undertook the deed. <q>This strife is mine,</q>
<lb/>He said. <q>If ye will make it worth my while
<lb/>This is my quarry.</q>
<lb/><q>Go and do it then
<lb/>If thou art able,</q> Farrukhzad replied.
<lb/><q>Moreover open not thy lips herein.
<lb/>I have a purse full of dinars for thee,
<lb/>And I will look upon thee as my son.</q>
</p>
<p>
<milestone unit="calced" n="2044"/>
<lb/>He gave the man a dagger keen and bright,
<lb/>And then the murderer set forth in haste.
<lb/>The miscreant, when he approached the Shah,
<lb/>Saw him upon the throne, a slave attending.
<lb/>Khusrau Parwiz quaked when he saw that man,

<pb n="34"/>
<lb/>And shed tears from his eyelids on his cheeks
<lb/>Because his heart bare witness that the day
<lb/>Of heaviness was near. He cried: <q>O wretch!
<lb/>What is thy name? Thy mother needs must wail
<lb/>thee.</q>
<lb/>The man replied: <q>They call me Mihr Hurmuzd,
<lb/>A stranger here with neither friend nor mate.</q>
<lb/>Thus said Khusrau Parwiz: <q>My time hath come,
<lb/>And by the hand of an unworthy foe,
<lb/>Whose face is not a man’s, whose love none seeketh.</q>
<lb/>He bade a boy attending him: <q>Go fetch,
<lb/>My little guide! an ewer, water, musk,
<lb/>And ambergris, with cleaner, fairer robes.</q>
<lb/>The boy-slave heard, unwitting what was meant,
<lb/>And so the little servant went away,
<lb/>And brought a golden ewer to the Shah
<lb/>As well as garments and a bowl of water,
<lb/>Whereon Khusrau Parwiz made haste to go,
<lb/>Gazed on the sacred twigs and muttered prayers:
<lb/>It was no time for words or private talk.
<lb/>The Shah put on the garments brought, he made
<lb/>Beneath his breath confession of his faults,
<lb/>And wrapped a new simarre about his head
<lb/>In order not to see his murderer’s face.
<lb/>Then Mihr Hurmuzd, the dagger in his hand,
<lb/>Made fast the door and coming quickly raised
<lb/>The great king’s robe and pierced his liverstead.
<lb/>Such is the process of this whirling world,
<lb/>From thee its secret keeping closely furled!
<lb/>The blameless speaker and the boastful see
<lb/>That all its doings are but vanity,
<lb/>For be thou wealthy or in evil case
<lb/>This Wayside Inn is no abiding-place;
<lb/>Yet be offenceless and ensue right ways
<lb/>If thou desirest to receive just praise.
</p>
<p>

<lb/>When tidings reached the highways and bazars;—
<pb n="35"/>
<lb/><q>Khusrau Parwiz was slaughtered thus,</q> his foes
<lb/>Went to the palace-prison of the sad,
<lb/>Where fifteen of his noble sons were bound,
<lb/>And slew them there, though innocent, what a
<lb/>The fortune of the Shah was overthrown.
<lb/>Shirwi, the world-lord, dared say naught and hid
<lb/>His grief though he wept sorely at the news,
<lb/>And afterwards sent twenty of his guards
<milestone unit="calced" n="2045"/>
<lb/>To keep his brothers’ wives and children safe
<lb/>Now that the Shah had been thus done to death.
</p><p>
<lb/>So passed that reign and mighty host away,
<lb/>Its majesty, its manhood, and its sway
<lb/>Such as no kings of kings possessed before,
<lb/>Or heard of from the men renowned of yore.
<lb/>It booteth nothing what the wise man saith
<lb/>When once his head is in the dragon’s breath.
<lb/>Call this world “crocodile” for it doth gnaw
<lb/>The prey that it hath taken with its claw.
<lb/>The work of Shah Khusrau Parwiz is done;
<lb/>His famous hoards and throne and host are gone.
<lb/>To put one’s trust in this world is to be
<lb/>In quest of dates upon a willow-tree.
<lb/>Why err in such a fashion from the way
<lb/>Alike by darksome night and shining day?
<lb/>Whate’er thy gains let them suffice thee still
<lb/>As thou art fain to save thy soul from ill,
<lb/>And in thy day of strength hold thyself weak;
<lb/>For kindly impulses and justice seek,
<lb/>And be intent on good. For what is thine
<lb/>To give or spend do as thou dost incline;
<lb/>All else is pain and toil. How goodlier
<lb/>Than we are friends whose faithfulness is clear!
<lb/>Such faithfulness of friends is greatly dear.
</p>

</div>

<pb n="36"/>

<div>   <head>§ 6 How Shirwi asked Shirin in Marriage, how Shirin killed herself, and how Shirici was slain</head>
<p>
<lb/>Since I have ended with Khusrau Parwiz
<lb/>I speak next of Shirwi and of Shirin.
<lb/>As soon as three and fifty days had passed
<lb/>Since that whereon that glorious Shah was slain
<lb/>Shirwi dispatched Shirin a messenger
<lb/>To say: <q>Thou wicked, potent sorceress,
<lb/>Learned but in necromancy and black arts!
<lb/>In all Iran thou art the guiltiest.
<lb/>By necromancy didst thou gain the Shah,
<lb/>And by thy craft thou bringest down the moon.
<lb/>Quake, guilty one! and come to me. Abide not
<lb/>Thus in thy palace, joyful and secure.</q>
<lb/>Shirin raged at his message and abuse
<lb/>So foul and senseless. Thus she said: <q>God grant
<lb/>That parricides possess not Grace or presence.
<lb/>I will not see the wretch e’en from afar
<lb/>At funeral or feast.</q>
<lb/>That mournful dame
<lb/>Sent for a scribe and had a document
<lb/>Drawn in the olden tongue, instructing him
<lb/>Regarding her last wishes and estate.
<milestone unit="calced" n="2046"/>
<lb/>She kept a little poison in a pyx;
<lb/>She could not well procure it in the city.
<lb/>She kept it on her, sewed a winding-sheet
<lb/>To wrap her form—that cypress of the garden—
<lb/>And then returned this answer to Shirwi:—
<lb/><q>Exalted Shah, the wearer of the crown!
<lb/>Now perish all thy words and perish too
<lb/>The villain’s heart and spirit that hath heard
<pb n="37"/>
<lb/>Of witchcraft save by name and joyed therein.
<lb/>Had Shah Khusrau Parwiz been one to cheer
<lb/>His soul with sorcery there would have been
<lb/>A sorceress within his bower, and she
<lb/>Had seen his face.</q><note n="1">Reading with P.</note> <q>He kept me for his pleasure,
<lb/>And when the dawn was peeping he was wont
<lb/>To call me from the golden bower and joy
<lb/>At sight of me. Shame on thee for such words!
<lb/>Such knavish talk becometh not a king.
<lb/>Remember God, the Giver of all good,
<lb/>And utter not such words in others’ hearing.</q>
<lb/>They brought the answer to the Shah. Shirwi
<lb/>Raged ’gainst the guiltless dame<note n="2">So far as the charge of witchcraft was concerned. Shirin (Vol.
<lb/>viii., p. 389) had murdered Maryam, Kubäd's mother.</note> and said: <q>Thou
<lb/>needs 
<lb/>Must come. None is blood-thirstier than thou.
<lb/>Come and behold my crown’s top. If it be
<lb/>Magnifical then do it reverence.</q>
<lb/>Shirin, on hearing this, was full of pain;
<lb/>She writhed; her cheeks grew wan. She thus
<lb/>replied:—
<lb/><q>I will not come to thee save in the presence
<lb/>Of those wise men that are about thy court,
<lb/>Men of experience and clerkly skill.</q>
<lb/>Shirwi dispatched and summoned fifty men
<lb/>Both wise and old, then sent one to Shirin,
<lb/>To say: <q>Arise and come. Enough of talk.</q>
<lb/>Thereat she robed herself in blue and black,
<lb/>And drew anear the Shah, approached apace
<lb/>The Rosary of Revellers<note><cit><quote xml:lang="fra">elle alla droit à la salle de féte de Schadegin.</quote> <bibl>Mohl</bibl></cit> Or, more strictly, Barbier de Meynard, who completed the translation from §4 to the end of the poem.</note>—the spot
<lb/>Wherein those fluent Persians were—and sat
<lb/>Behind the great king’s curtain as became
<pb n="38"/>
<lb/>The virtuous. He sent to her to say:—
<lb/><q>Two months</q><note n="3">Reading with P.</note> <q>of mourning for Khusrau Parwiz
<lb/>Are o’er. Now be my wife that thou mayst take
<lb/>Thy pleasure and avoid a mean estate.
<lb/>I will maintain thee as my father did,
<lb/>And e’en with more respect and tenderness.</q>
<lb/>Shirin replied: <q>Let me be righted first,
<lb/>And then my life shall be at thy dispose.
<lb/>I will not hesitate in answering
<lb/>The hest and purpose of thy glorious heart.</q>
<lb/>Shirwi agreed to that fair dame’s request,
<milestone unit="calced" n="2047"/>
<lb/>Whereat the noble lady raised her voice
<lb/>Behind the royal curtains, saying: <q>O Shah!
<lb/>Be happy and victorious. Thou said’st
<lb/>That I was a bad woman and a witch,
<lb/>Remote from purity and rectitude.</q>
<lb/>Shirwi replied: <q>'Twas so, but generous folk
<lb/>Do not take dudgeon at mere hastiness.</q>
<lb/>Shirin addressed the other Persians present
<lb/>Within the Rosary of Revellers,
<lb/>And asked: <q>What have ye seen in me of ill,
<lb/>Guile, folly, and dark ways? For many a year
<lb/>I was the mistress of Iran and helped
<lb/>The Brave in everything. I ne’er ensued
<lb/>Aught but the right; fraud and deceit I banned.
<lb/>Through my word many were made governors,
<lb/>And took their portions of the world full oft.
<lb/>Who hath beheld my shadow in Iran
<lb/>Away from home? If any one hath marked
<lb/>My shadow, crown, and state let such declare
<lb/>What he hath seen or heard and by his answer
<lb/>Reveal the truth.</q>
<lb/>The magnates in attendance
<lb/>All spake her fair. <q>In all the world,</q> they said,
<lb/><q>She hath no peer in public and in private.</q>
<pb n="39"/>
<lb/>Shirin proceeded thus: <q>Ye lords and chiefs
<lb/>Both veteran and redoubted! three things make
<lb/>The worth of women that bedeck the throne
<lb/>Of greatness: one is modesty and wealth
<lb/>Wherewith her husband may adorn his house;
<lb/>The next is bearing blesséd sons, that she
<lb/>May e’en exceed her spouse in happiness;
<lb/>The third is having beauty and fine form,
<lb/>Joined with the love of a sequestered life.
<lb/>When I was mated to Khusrau Parwiz,
<lb/>And entered on seclusion, he had come
<lb/>Weak and dispirited from Rum to live
<lb/>Within our land, but after reached such power
<lb/>As none had heard of or had looked upon.
<lb/>Moreover I have had four sons by him
<lb/>To his great joy—Nastur, Shahryär, Farüd,
<lb/>And Mardänshäh, blue heaven’s coronal.
<lb/>Jamshid and Faridun had not such sons;
<lb/>May my tongue perish if I lie herein!
<lb/>Their bodies all are now beneath the dust,
<lb/>Their spirits roaming in pure Paradise.</q>
<lb/>Unveiling then her lovely countenance,
<lb/>And musky hair, <q>There is my face,</q> she added,
<lb/><q>Such as it is. If there be falsehood show it.
<lb/>My hair was all my hidden excellence,
<lb/>For none on earth e’er used to look thereon.
<lb/>What I display is all my sorcery,
<lb/>Not necromancy, fraud, and evil bent.</q>
<milestone unit="calced" n="2048"/>
<lb/>None had beheld her hair before, no chief
<lb/>Had heard thereof. The elders were astound,
<lb/>And their mouths watered. When Shirwi beheld
<lb/>The visage of Shirin his spirit flew
<lb/>Unmarked away from him. Her face so dazed him
<lb/>That love of her filled all his heart. He cried:—
<lb/><q>I want none but thyself. If I have thee
<lb/>For wife Iran can give me nothing more.

<pb n="40"/>

<lb/>I will not go from thy commands, but limn
<lb/>My loyalty to thee upon mine eyes.</q>
<lb/>The lady of the lovely face replied:—
<lb/><q>I still need somewhat of the Iranian king.
<lb/>I have two wants if thou wilt bid me speak,
<lb/>And may thy kingship last forever.</q>
<lb/>Shirwi replied: <q>My soul is thine, thy wish,
<lb/>Whate’er it be, is granted.</q>
<lb/>Said Shirin:—
<lb/><q>All treasures laid up by me in this land
<lb/>Thou shalt assign me as mine own before
<lb/>This noble company and write thyself
<lb/>Upon this roll that thou renouncest all,
<lb/>Both small and great.</q>
<lb/>Shirwi made haste to do
<lb/>Her bidding. Having gained her wish she quitted
<lb/>The Rosary of Revellers, the chiefs
<lb/>And noble Persians, went home, freed her slaves,
<lb/>And made them happy with that wealth of hers
<lb/>Whereof she gave a part to mendicants,
<lb/>And to her family a larger share.
<lb/>She gave too somewhat to the Fanes of Fire,
<lb/>The feasts of New Year’s Day and Mihr and Sada,
<lb/>To ruined homes and caravansarais
<lb/>Then turned to lions’ lairs. All this she gave
<lb/>As offerings from Khusrau Parwiz, the world-lord,
<lb/>And joyed his soul thereby. She sought the garden
<lb/>And taking off her veil sat unadorned
<lb/>Upon the ground and summoning her folk
<lb/>Assigned with courtesy a place to each,
<lb/>Then cried thus loudly: <q>Hear, ye unaggrieved!
<lb/>For none will ever see my face again.
<lb/>Fear ye the Judge of those that seek for justice,
<lb/>The Lighter of the sun and moon and stars,
<lb/>And speak but truth; deceit is not for sages.
<lb/>Since first I came before Khusrau Parwiz,
<pb n="41"/>
<lb/>First made mine entry to his golden bower,
<lb/>And was chief wife and Glory of the Shah,
<lb/>Hath any fault at all appeared in me?
<lb/>There is no need to speak to save my face:
<lb/>What booteth that to woman in her need?</q>
<milestone unit="calced" n="2049"/>
<lb/>All rose to make reply: <q>Famed dame of dames,
<lb/>So eloquent and wise and bright of soul!
<lb/>By God! none ever saw thee, ever heard
<lb/>Thy voice behind the curtains. Verily
<lb/>Thy like hath sat not on the goodly throne
<lb/>Since Shah Hushang.</q>
<lb/>Then all the servitors,
<lb/>Slaves emulous and vigilant of heart,
<lb/>Exclaimed: <q>Exalted lady praised in Chin,
<lb/>In Rum and in Taraz! who would presume
<lb/>To speak aught ill of thee? Could evil-doing
<lb/>Befit that face of thine?</q>
<lb/>Thus said Shirin:—
<lb/><q>This reprobate, whom heaven above will curse,
<lb/>Slew his own sire to compass crown and throne,
<lb/>And may he never more see fortune’s face!
<lb/>Hath he himself shut death out by a wall
<lb/>Who lightly recked thus of a father’s blood?
<lb/>He sent a message to me that bedimmed
<lb/>Mine own shrewd soul. I answered: <q>While I live
<lb/>My heart shall serve my Maker.</q> I declared
<lb/>My purpose fully, fearful of my foe:
<lb/>He may defame me publicly when dead.
<lb/>Ye are free agents and my slaves no longer.</q>
<lb/>They wept much at her words and furthermore
<lb/>Consumed with anguish for Khusrau Parwiz.
<lb/>Informants went before the Shah and told
<lb/>What they had heard about that guiltless dame.
<lb/><q>He asked: <q>Hath that good lady further wishes?</q></q>
<lb/>She sent to say: <q>I have one wish, no more:
<lb/>I fain would ope the late Shah’s charnel-house;
<pb n="42"/>
<lb/>I have a great desire to look on him.</q>
<lb/>Shirwi replied: <q>So do, ’tis natural.</q>
<lb/>The keeper oped the door. That pious lady
<lb/>Began her wailing, went and laid her face
<lb/>Upon the visage of Khusrau Parwiz,
<lb/>Spake of the past and took the mortal bane:<note>Cf. p. 36.</note>
<lb/>She sent the dust up from her own sweet life.
<lb/>She sat beside the Shah with visage veiled,
<lb/>Clad in a single camphor-scented robe;
<lb/>She set her back against the wall and died;
<lb/>She died and won the plaudits of the world.
<lb/>Shirwi fell sick when he had heard the news,
<lb/>For such a spectacle affrighted him.
<lb/>He bade construct another sepulchre,
<lb/>And make her diadem of musk and camphor.
<milestone unit="calced" n="2050"/>
<lb/>He shut the old Shah’s charnel. Soon they gave
<lb/>Shirwi the bane; the world had had its fill
<lb/>Of Shahs! Thus luckless both in birth and death
<lb/>He left the throne of kingship to his son.
<lb/>One reigneth seven months, and in the eighth
<lb/>Doth don the camphor crown! Of earth’s good things
<lb/>To have possession of the throne is best,
<lb/>Of evils life cut short is evilest.
</p>

</div>


</div>

<div><head>XLV. ARDSHIR, SON OF SHIRWI: HE REIGNED SIX MONTHS</head>

<div>
<head>ARGUMENT</head>
<p><pb n="43"/>Ardshir’s accession is well received by the people. He makes Piruz, son of Khusrau, the captain of the host. Gurdez, on the pretext of avenging Khusrau Parwiz, but really with the intention of seizing the kingship for himself, schemes to bring about the death of the Shah who is murdered at a banquet by Piruz.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>NOTE</head>
<p>Ardshir (Artaxerxes III., September, A.D. 628—April, A.D. 630) was, according to Tabari, only seven years old at his accession. By some accounts, he was only one year old at the time.<note n="1">NT, p. 386. ZT, ii., 347.</note> He was of course a mere puppet in the hands of the nobles. The <q>True Cross,</q> if the date of its elevation at Jerusalem—Sept. 14th, A.D. 629—be correct, must have been restored during his reign.<note n="2">NT, p. 392 note.</note></p>
<p>§1. The Arabic Tabari says that the realm was administered by Mih-Azar-Gushnasp (Mihr Gushasp in the Persian version), the High Steward, who had charge of the Shah’s person. This may account for his being made out to be a regicide in the Shahnameh. He really seems to have been a well-intentioned man who did his best in very difficult circumstances. At all events, according to the Persian Tabari, Shahrbaraz, after taking possession of Ctesiphon, slew him and other nobles on the pretext of avenging the death of Khusrau Parwiz.</p>

<pb n="44"/>

<p>§2. It appears that Shahrbaraz (Gurdez) was not consulted when Ardshir was raised to the throne, and he made this an excuse for taking violent measures. The occasion was a favourable one for an ambitious general in command of an army. Moreover, he had an understanding, confirmed by matrimonial alliances, with Heraclius, who no doubt promised to recognize him if he became Shah. He accordingly marched upon Ctesiphon with 6,000 or, according to another account, 60,000 troops. The High Steward made an attempt at resistance, but Shahrbaraz, with the connivance of the captain of the guard and other chiefs, was successful and the usual scenes of outrage and massacre ensued.<note n="3">NT, p. 386 notes. RSM, p. 541</note></p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><head>How Ardshir, Son of Shirwi, ascended the Throne and harangued the Chiefs</head>
<p>
<lb/>Now as the next confronting me I voice
<lb/>The reign of Shah Ardshir, I have no choice.
<lb/>When Shah Ardshir sat on the throne both young
<lb/>And old flocked to him from Iran, for many
<lb/>Were chiefs grown old, to hear what he would say.<note n="1">Couplet omitted.</note>
<lb/>The young Ardshir then loosed his tongue and thus
<lb/>He spake: <q>Ye well-tried warriors! may one,
<lb/>Whoe’er he be, that sitteth on the seat
<lb/>Of sovereignty possess an open mind,
<lb/>And worship God. We will ensue the course
<lb/>Of former Shahs, ensue too Grace and Faith.
<lb/>May we remember God who giveth good,
<lb/>May all our acts be just! I will advance
<lb/>The pious and make tyrants bleed. I trust
<lb/>The army to Piruz, son of Khusrau,
<lb/>Who loveth equity and loyal lieges.
<pb n="45"/>
<lb/>They for their part with such a paladin
<lb/>Still will be happy and serene of soul.</q>
<lb/>Full many were contented with his speech;
<lb/>A peaceful ruler was the wish of each.
</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><head>How Gurdz was displeased at Ardshir being Shah and how he caused Ardshir to be slain by Piruz, Son of Khusrau</head>
<p>Then tidings reached Gurdez, who had involved
Khusrau Parwiz in sorrow and distress,
<lb/>And he dispatched from Rum a man to say:—
<q>The crown of vile Shirwi is in the dust.
<milestone unit="calced" n="2051"/>
<lb/>Hell take his soul and be his charnel-house
<lb/>O’erturned! Who ever knew a lofty cypress
<lb/>Wrecked in the garden by the grass, and one
<lb/>Like to Khusrau Parwiz, whose peer as king
<lb/>Time’s eye and heart perceive not, who bestowed
<lb/>My greatness on me, and I have not turned
<lb/>From his behest? Now fate dethroneth him,
<lb/>And fortune’s face is utterly averse;
<lb/>The circling heaven is his foe and maketh
<lb/>His portion to be hidden in the earth;
<lb/>The sun and moon amerce him of his sway,
<lb/>And take the crown and throne from such a king,
<lb/>Bestow the sovereignty upon Shirwi,
<lb/>And give up all Iran to wretchedness!
<lb/>When he passed and Ardshir assumed the crown
<lb/>Both young and old rejoiced in him, but I,
<lb/>If I have any portion in Iran,
<lb/>Will suffer not our country’s air to breathe
<pb n="46"/>
<lb/>Upon him. Have I not received the news
<lb/>Of Shah Khusrau Parwiz wrecked by the words
<lb/>Of one of evil mark? I will not have
<lb/>A king like this one though the age be Shahless,
<lb/>For there is much contention in his head,
<lb/>And he adviseth with another host.
<lb/>Now will I come in force with chosen chiefs
<lb/>Of Rum and of Iran, and we shall see
<lb/>What sort of Head that is to whom such schemes
<lb/>Appeal. I will uproot him so that never
<lb/>Shall he name kingship more.</q>
<lb/>He sent a runner
<lb/>To seek the ancients of the Iranian host,
<lb/>And strove in other fashion to advance
<lb/>His ill designs by writing to Piruz,
<lb/>Son of Khusrau, thus: <q>The Sasanians’ fortune
<lb/>Is louring and we need a world-aspirant
<lb/>To gird himself for action. Haply thou
<lb/>Art ware of what to do and how to take
<lb/>The needful steps, wilt seek for many helpers,
<lb/>Both young and old, wilt clear away Ardshir,
<lb/>And afterwards attain thy whole desire,
<lb/>Be safe and well contented; but if thou
<lb/>Reveal this plot, and feed the sword of war
<lb/>With blood, I will lead forth such hosts from Rum
<lb/>That I shall make the world dark in thine eyes.
<lb/>Heed well my words, and mayst thou think no scorn
<lb/>Of mine intent: thou must not fall through folly.
<lb/>Oh! pass not from the throne of majesty
<lb/>To underneath the dust. Repentance then
<lb/>Will not avail thee when in wreak my sword
<lb/>Is reaping heads.</q>
<lb/>Piruz, son of Khusrau,
<lb/>When he had read that letter and perceived
<lb/>The whole intendment of that self-willed man,
<milestone unit="calced" n="2052"/>
<lb/>Much pondered on the matter and consulted
<pb n="47"/>
<lb/>The ancient magnates, saying: <q>This affair
<lb/>Hath come upon me unawares and like
<lb/>A revelation!</q>
<lb/>This was their reply:—
<q>Famed and redoubted chieftain! if our Shah
<lb/>Shall perish we shall rightly perish too
<lb/>For such a crime. Let not Gurdez’ words move thee
<lb/>To perpetrate such ill, but take occasion
<lb/>For doing good. Write him a fitting answer,
<lb/>And wake him from his dream. Say: <q>Thwart not
<lb/>thou
<lb/>God’s purposes; give not the Div a way
<lb/>To thine own heart. Reflect upon the case
<lb/>Of Shah Khusrau Parwiz and all the wrong
<lb/>That led to his undoing, for what time
<lb/>Thou didst depose him the Sasanian fortune
<lb/>Went at one blow, and when Shirwi ascended
<lb/>The royal throne and girt his kingly loins
<lb/>Folk hoped such days as when Khusrau Parwiz
<lb/>Was Shah whose wits were keen in all regards,
<lb/>And if the world became what it became,
<lb/>And gat no profit from the state of things,
<lb/>It was because the world dealt foolishly,
<lb/>And by one stroke lost its advantages.
<lb/>Now that Ardshir, succeeding to Kubad,
<lb/>Is seated as the Shah upon the throne,
<lb/>The world rejoicing in his majesty,
<lb/>And earth and time exulting in his Grace,
<lb/>Why should the world, now tranquil, be convulsed
<lb/>By pain and war? Knock not at evils’ door;
<lb/>Those that slay blameless kings will prosper not.
<lb/>In this strife circling heaven must not raise
<lb/>Iran in dust. I fear that God will end
<lb/>The Iranians’ term for ills more heinous still.</q></q>
<lb/>Piruz, on this wise counselled, wrote Gurdez—
<lb/>That villain of vile race (may none like him
<pb n="48"/>
<lb/>Be ever chief!) —a profitable letter,
<lb/>And thou hadst said that one had got his heart
<lb/>Between the shears when he had read those words.
<lb/>In fierce wrath with Piruz, son of Khusrau,
<lb/>He gathered all his baggage and commanded
<lb/>The host to march forth plainwards. At the news
<lb/>Piruz dispatched a cameleer to go
<lb/>In all haste to Tukhar to summon him,
<lb/>Informing him at large of the affair,
<lb/>Of what Gurdez was doing and the strife
<lb/>About the imperial throne. Then from Tukhar
<lb/>This answer reached Piruz, son of Khusrau:—
<milestone unit="calced" n="2053"/> 
<q>Risk not the blood of the Iranian chiefs,
<lb/>O noble man! but hear what saith Gurdez.
<lb/>Since thou hast written on such wise, perchance
<lb/>He may not come to fight with thee.</q>
</p>
<p>Now when
<lb/>Piruz, son of Khusrau, had seen that letter
<lb/>His heart had no repose from evil thoughts,
<lb/>But gloomed with thinking how to harm the Shah,
<lb/>Whose wont it was to summon him, for he
<lb/>Was an observant man and eloquent,
<lb/>And served as minister and treasurer.
<lb/>He came one dark night for an audience,
<lb/>And found the wine bright and the welcome warm.
<lb/>Ardshir was seated in his palace-hall
<lb/>In company with many young and old,
<lb/>And when Piruz, son of Khusrau, came raised,
<lb/>Thou wouldst have said, his head to heaven, called
<lb/>For harp, and all the hall was filled with music.
<lb/>Piruz, son of Khusrau, when midnight came,
<lb/>Had drunk one man<note n="1">See Vol. i., p. 290 note.</note> of wine while the companions
<lb/>Of Shah Ardshir were all bemused; no minstrel
<lb/>Was left that kept his wits. The miscreant
<lb/>Dismissed the company: he and the Shah
<pb n="49"/>
<lb/>Alone remained. That man of outrage rose,
<lb/>Laid hand upon the Shah’s lips unawares,
<lb/>And held it there until Ardshir was dead.
<lb/>The palace filled with scimitars and arrows.
<lb/>All there—ambitious youths and warriors—
<lb/>Were fautors of Piruz, son of Khusrau.
<lb/>Upon this manner ceased Ardshir to be
<lb/>When he had had six months of sovereignty.
</p>


</div>
</div>

<div><head>XLVI. GURAZ (ALSO CALLED FARAYIN): HE REIGNED FIFTY DAYS</head>

<div>
<head>ARGUMENT</head>
<p><pb n="50"/>
Guraz, hearing of Ardshir’s death, marches on Talikan and
urged on by his younger, though dissuaded by his elder son,
usurps the throne. His rule described. A plot is formed
against him and he is slain while returning from the chase.
The throne remains vacant for a while.
</p>
</div>
<div>
<head>NOTE</head>
<p>
Cf. note to previous reign. Guraz (Shahr-Barz, April
27th—June 9th, A.D. 630) reigned for forty days.<note n="1">NT, p. 390 and note.</note> He was
one of the three chief generals employed by Khusrau Parwiz
in his long war against the Eastern Roman Empire. His
real name, according to Tabari, was Farruhân. This in
Pahlavi would be Farrukhän, which by a misreading has
become Farayin in the Shahnama. Shahrbardz (Shahrwaraz,
or Shahrbaraz) is, says Tabari, a title. Firdausi uses the
shortened form Guraz, which means <gloss>boar,</gloss> because it
is more convenient metrically. The title may have been
appropriate enough. In the Shahnama the general is split
up into two personalities—Guraz or Farayin, the usurper,
and Shahrbaraz, the avenger of the breach made by the
upstart in the sacred line of Sasanian succession.<note n="2">NT, pp. 292 and note. 388 and note.</note> In Tabari,
the leader of the revolt is a native of Istakhr named Purmuz.<note n="3">NT, pp. 292 and note. 388 and note.</note> Shahrbaraz in the Shahnama is also of the same
City.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><head>How Gurdz (also called Fardyin) received News of the Slaying of Ardshir, hastened to Iran, took Possession of the Throne, and was killed by Shahränguräz?</head>
<p><pb n="51"/>
<lb/>Piruz, son of Khusrau, dispatched a post,
<lb/>And letter too, in secret to Guraz,
<lb/>Whose sombre soul, what time the messenger
<lb/>Arrived, grew like the sun, and from those forts
<lb/>He led forth such an army that the way
<lb/>Was barred to fly and emmet. Like the wind
<lb/>He sped to Talikan, his soldiers’ hands
<lb/>All had been bathed in blood. When he arrived
<lb/>The chiefs went out to welcome him, but none
<milestone unit="calced" n="2054"/>
<lb/>Among the troops dared breathe for they were few.
<lb/>Guraz, on entering the city, stayed not
<lb/>For minister and counsellor but chose
<lb/>A void place, and the magnates privily
<lb/>Conferred with him. Piruz, son of Khusrau,
<lb/>Set loose his tongue and said: <q>Famed paladin!
<lb/>Whom hast thou chosen to be king of kings,
<lb/>And illustrate the crown of majesty?</q>
<lb/>The warrior Guraz made answer thus:—
<lb/><q>I have not any secrets from Iran.
<lb/>To-morrow look ye out for some new Shah
<lb/>To sit like some new moon upon the throne.</q>
<lb/>Since knowledge is the glory of a man
<lb/>Walk not, if thou canst help it, foolishly.
<lb/>He that hath wisdom speaketh goodly words,
<lb/>And as it groweth he deserteth ill.
</p>

<pb n="52"/>

<p>
<lb/>It is the best of man’s accomplishments,
<lb/>The world’s endeavour and the way of God.
<lb/>Of things that grace one not there is no need
<lb/>To speak at large for he will foolishly
<lb/>Disgrace himself howe’er he may exalt
<lb/>The case in point. When wisdom hath deserted
<lb/>The head, and shame the eye, fame and disgrace,
<lb/>And cold and hot, are one—no terror this
<lb/>To any coward whether quick or dead.
<lb/>Make, if thou canst, all good thy business
<lb/>Because the world abideth not with any.
<lb/>Let all thy usance be humanity,
<lb/>Munificence and uprightness thy Faith.
<lb/>When Farayin assumed the royal crown
<lb/>He uttered what was in his mind and said:—
<lb/><q>Let me assume the kingship for a while,
<lb/>And sit upon the throne of gold in joy.
<lb/>Far better scatter wealth and be exalted
<lb/>Than purchase sixty years of servitude.
<lb/>Thus will I sit a while in sovereignty,
<lb/>Arrayed in satin<note n="1">Or <gloss>beaver-skins.</gloss></note> and in painted silk,
<lb/>And after me my son shall take my throne,
<lb/>Assume this royal crown, be king as was
<lb/>His sire, and be exalted and renowned.
<lb/>Whoe’er shall minister to our delight
<lb/>Shall be a happy man among mankind.
<lb/>In feast-time we will drink with joyful hearts,
<lb/>In war-time we will hunt our enemies.</q>
<lb/>His elder son said privily to him:—
<lb/><q>Who of us, father! ever wore the crown?
<lb/>Feel not secure, take means to compass wealth;
<lb/>Thou wast the world’s protector; keep to that.
<lb/>If any member of the royal race
<lb/>Shalt come thou wilt not long be here; thy heart
<lb/>Will keep of kingship only grief and pain;
<pb n="53"/>

<lb/>Thou wilt be wretched, destitute, and wan.</q>
<milestone unit="calced" n="2055"/>
<lb/>Then said the younger son: <q>Thou hast become
<lb/>Crowned in the world and hast both troops and
<lb/>treasures
<lb/>Befitting royalty, but treasureless
<lb/>Wilt have to labour still. What ancestor
<lb/>Of Faridun, who had Abtin to sire,
<lb/>E’er wore the crown? Hold fast the world by courage
<lb/>And treasure. Nobody is born a king.</q><note n="2">But cf. Vol. vi., p. 320.</note>
<lb/>The younger’s words pleased Farayin the best,
<lb/>Who bade his elder son: <q>Be not so raw.</q>
<lb/>He laid out in the royal offices
<lb/>The muster-roll and called all troops to court.
<lb/>He gave drachms night and day and many robes
<lb/>Of honour ill-deserved. Within two weeks
<lb/>Of all the treasury of Shah Ardshir
<lb/>Remained not what would buy an arrow’s plume!
<lb/>Whene’er Guraz would go forth to the pleasance
<lb/>The lights were torches made of ambergris,
<lb/>Four score before and four score after him:
<lb/>Behind them came his friends and partisans.
<lb/>Of gold and silver were the goblets all,
<lb/>The golden gem-encrusted.<note>The above couplets transposed.</note> 'Twas his use
<lb/>To feast all night. The nobles’ hearts were full
<lb/>Of vengeance on him. 'Twas his wont to roam
<lb/>A-nights the gardens and the riding-ground.
<lb/>Save but to sleep and wake, to eat and plunder,
<lb/>That slight, weak-witted one knew naught. He went
<lb/>Drunk ever to repose and with a sash
<lb/>From Chin about his head. The troops were all
<lb/>Vexed to the heart at him while all the province
<lb/>Was full of turmoil and distress. He lost
<lb/>All trace of generosity and grew
<lb/>Unjust, unfortunate, and good for naught.
<lb/>The world was wrecked by his iniquity,
</p>

<pb n="54"/>

<p>
<lb/>And at his handling people smote their heads.
<lb/>He shed the blood of innocents until
<lb/>The troops grew wroth with him. He used to shut
<lb/>His eyes for gold and would have sold the world
<lb/>To win dinars. Folk cursed him. All desired
<lb/>His death and meeting privily discussed
<lb/>His deeds. Hurmuz Shahränguraz, a horseman
<lb/>Redoubted of the city of Istakhr—
<lb/>The glory of the chieftains—thus addressed
<lb/>One night the Iranians secretly: <q>Ye chiefs!
<lb/>The time of Farayin is proving grievous;
<lb/>He holdeth all the chiefs in light esteem.
<lb/>Why have your brains and hearts become thus straitened?
<lb/>Through him all eyes are tearful, livers charged
<lb/>With blood. Is no physician to be found?
<lb/>He is not royal or Sasanian;
<lb/>Why gird the loins before him? Of a truth
<milestone unit="calced" n="2056"/>
<lb/>Your hearts have flown out of your breasts or else
<lb/>Your pluck hath disappeared!</q>
<lb/>The folk replied:—
<lb/><q>Since there was no one left fit for the throne
<lb/>None is inspired by jealousy to take
<lb/>This base-born’s heart away; but we adopt
<lb/>Thy counsel. Tell us from thy stores of lore
<lb/>How to release Iran from this insane
<lb/>And hot-brained Shah ill both in word and deed.
<lb/>May he be never blessed!</q> Shahranguraz
<lb/>Replied: <q>The Iranians have suffered long.
<lb/>If ye will harm me not but play the Persian
<lb/>E’en now by holy God’s aid will I bring him
<lb/>Down from his throne to dust.</q>
<lb/>He gat this answer:—
<lb/><q>May no harm come to thee! All we the host
<lb/>To-day are thy supporters and thy stronghold
<pb n="55"/>

<lb/>If ill herefrom befall thee.</q>
<lb/>Hearing this
<lb/>That royal warrior sought how to set
<lb/>Hands on the worthless Shah. Now he one day
<lb/>Took order and departed from the city
<lb/>To hunt, and of the Iranians a troop
<lb/>Of lords and lieges fared, escorting him.
<lb/>He urged his courser on and rode about
<lb/>As ’twere Azargashasp, the cavaliers
<lb/>Encircling him and beating up the game.
<lb/>Now at what time they turned back city-wards
<lb/>Shahranguraz looked at the hapless Shah
<lb/>With boldness, chose an arrow from his quiver,
<lb/>One that was straight and had a point of steel,
<lb/>And urged his black steed while the host looked on.
<lb/>He stretched the bow and drew it out at whiles
<lb/>To chest or head, then notched, as if in sport,
<lb/>An arrow on the string and drew the bow
<lb/>Till it concealed the point, and loosed his thumb.
<lb/>Forthwith the shaft struck on the monarch’s back,
<lb/>Who dropped his whip. The arrow was all blood
<lb/>Up to the feathers and the iron head
<lb/>Protruded from his navel. All the troops
<lb/>Unsheathed and all that night while dust-clouds rose
<lb/>They plied their swords and knew not whom they fought,
<lb/>But took and gave back blows and cursed or blessed
<lb/>That deed. Now when the yellow Veil appeared,
<lb/>So that the world seemed like a leopard’s back,
<lb/>There was a multitude of slain and maimed,
<lb/>And cavaliers and leaders were astound.
<milestone unit="calced" n="2057"/>
<lb/>That great host was dispersed like timid sheep
<lb/>When they perceive a wolf. Long they remained
<lb/>Without a king: none cared to claim the crown.
<lb/>For long they sought and sought in vain to trace
<lb/>Some royal scion of the noble race.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div><head>XLVII. PURANDUKHT: SHE REIGNED SIX MONTHS</head>

<div>
<head>NOTE</head>
<p><pb n="56"/>
Purandukht (Purandokht, summer A.D. 630—autumn
A.D. 631), reigned, according to Tabari, for one year and
four months. Her name, it appears, should be spelled with a
B, not with a P. She is said to have restored the <quote>True
Cross,</quote> but it seems more probable that this was done in the
reign of Ardshir. She made the leader of the successful
conspiracy against Shahrbaraz her prime minister.<note n="1">For the above see NT, p. 390 seq. and notes, ZT, i1., 349.</note> She
was the first historical female Shah, and it was in allusion to
her reign and that of her sister Azarmidokht that the distich
is quoted in Mir Khand:

<cit>
<quote>
<l>No dignity remains in a household</l>
<l>In which the hens are crowing like cocks.</l>
</quote>
<bibl>RM, Pt. II, vol. iii, p. 101.</bibl>
</cit>
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><head>How Purandukht ascended the Throne and slew Piruz, Son of Khusrau, and how her own Life ended</head>
<p>
<lb/>Tis but crude policy when women rule,
<lb/>But yet there was a lady—Purandukht—
<lb/>Surviving of the lineage of Sasan,
</p>

<pb n="57"/>

<p>
<lb/>And well read in the royal volume: her
<lb/>They seated on the throne of sovereignty,
<lb/>The Great strewed jewels over her, and then
<lb/>She spake upon this wise: <q>I will not have
<lb/>The people scattered,<note n="1">Through misgovernment.</note> and I will enrich
<lb/>The poor with treasure that they may not bide
<lb/>In their distress. God grant that in the world
<lb/>There may be none aggrieved because his pain
<lb/>Is my calamity. I will expel
<lb/>Foes from the realm and walk in royal ways.</q>
<lb/>She made search for Piruz, son of Khusrau,
<lb/>Who was delated by an alien,
<lb/>Whereat she chose some warriors from the host
<lb/>Who brought Piruz before her. She exclaimed:—
<lb/><q>Foul-purposed miscreant!<note n="2">One couplet omitted</note> thou shalt receive,
<lb/>As infamous, the guerdon for thy deeds.</q>
<lb/>She bade bring from the stalls a colt unbroken,
<lb/>And bound, firm as a rock, Piruz thereto
<lb/>Without a saddle and with yoke on neck.
<lb/>The vengeful lady had that untamed steed
<lb/>Brought to the riding-ground and thither sent,
<lb/>With lassos coiled up in their saddle-straps,
<lb/>A band of warriors to urge the colt
<lb/>To utmost speed, to strive from time to time
<lb/>To throw Piruz and ever roll itself
<lb/>Upon the ground. That colt won much applause
<lb/>Until with skin in shreds and dripping blood
<milestone unit="calced" n="2058"/>
<lb/>Piruz gave up the ghost right wretchedly.
<lb/>Why having done wrong seekst thou for justice?
<lb/>Nay, ill for ill; that is the course of right.
<lb/>Purandukht ruled the world with gentleness;
<lb/>No wind from heaven blew upon the dust,
<lb/>But when six months had passed beneath her sway
<lb/>The circle of her life bent suddenly;
<lb/>For one week she was ailing, then expired,
</p>

<pb n="58"/>

<p>
<lb/>And took away with her a fair renown.
<lb/>Such is the process of the turning sky,
<lb/>So potent while so impotent are we!
<lb/>If thine be opulence or poverty,
<lb/>If life affordeth gain or loss to thee,
<lb/>If thou shalt win what thou desirest so,
<lb/>Or disappointed be in wretchedness,
<lb/>And whether thou be one of wealth or woe,
<lb/>Both woe and wealth will pass away no less.
<lb/>Reign as a Shah a thousand years, five score,
<lb/>For sixty years or thirty, ten or four,
<lb/>It cometh to one thing, when all is done,
<lb/>If thou hadst many years or barely one.
<lb/>Oh! may thine actions thine own comrades be,
<lb/>For they in every place will succour thee.
<lb/>Let go thy clutch upon this Wayside Inn
<lb/>Because a goodlier place is thine to win.
<lb/>If thine endeavour be to learning given
<lb/>Thou wilt by knowledge roam revolving heaven.
</p>
</div>    

</div>

<div><head>XLVIII. AZARMIDUKHT: SHE REIGNED FOUR MONTHS</head>

<div><head>NOTE</head>
<p><pb n="59"/>
Before Azarmidukht (Azarmidokht, end of A.D. 631—
beginning of A.D. 632) came to the throne, there seems to
have been a short interval during which a distant scion of the
royal House, who took the name of Piruz, ruled for less than a
month. The chief noble of the time, who was governor of
Khurasan, wished to make Azarmidukht his wife, upon which she
had him privately executed. This noble’s son was the Rustam
that fought and fell at Qadisiyah some years later. On
hearing of his father’s fate, Rustam, who was in temporary
authority in Khurasan, marched with a great army against
Azarmidukht, overthrew her, and put her to death after she
had reigned six months. Her name probably means <gloss>modest
girl.</gloss><note n="1">For the above see NT, p. 393 and notes, ZT, ii, 350 seq.</note>
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><head>How Azarmdukht ascended the Throne and how she died</head>
<p>
<lb/>There was another dame hight Azarmdukht,
<lb/>Who had fruition of the crown of greatness.
<lb/>She came, sat down upon the royal throne,
<lb/>And made herself the mistress of the world.
<lb/>Her first words were: <q>O sages, veterans,
<lb/>And masters of affairs! be just in all,
<pb n="60"/>

<lb/>And follow precedent, for ye hereafter
<lb/>Must make the bricks your pillow. I will foster
<lb/>The loyal liege, assist him with dinars,
<lb/>And if he erreth be longsuffering;
<lb/>But him that is disloyal and deserteth
<lb/>The way of wisdom and of precedent
<lb/>Will I suspend in shame upon the gibbet,
<lb/>Be he an Arab, Roman cavalier,
<lb/>Or Persian thane.</q>
<lb/>She filled the throne four months,
<lb/>But with the fifth disaster came thereto,
</p>

<milestone unit="calced" n="2059"/> 

<p>
<lb/>For she too died, the throne had not a Shah,
<lb/>But was the plaything of the ill-disposed.
<lb/>With the revolving sky 'tis everything
<lb/>To be all vengeful with its fosterling.
</p>
</div>    
</div>
<div><head>XLIX. FARRUKHZAD: HE REIGNED ONE MONTH</head>

<div><head>NOTE</head>
<p><pb n="61"/>
Between, and even earlier than, the death of Azarmidukht
and the accession of Yazdagird III, the order of the dynastic
succession becomes very confused. The names of the Shahs
vary in the different lists. The reason is that it was a period
of great internal unrest and various aspirants to the throne
held contemporaneously some short-lived authority in different
provinces of the empire. One of these princes, Farrukhzad
(Farrukhzad-Khusrau) has received the honour of being
included in the list of the Shahs as recorded in the Shahnama.
Two accounts of the length of his reign are given in Tabari.
According to one, it lasted for six months, according to the
other, for a year. Both agree that he did not die a natural
death, and one of them states that his death was instigated
by the adherents of Yazdagird.<note n="1">NT, p. 397 and note. Cf. RSM, p. 544.</note>
</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><head>How Farrukhzad ascended the Throne and how he was slain by a Slave</head>
<p>
<lb/>Then from Jahram they summoned Farrukhzad,
<lb/>And seated him upon the throne of kingship.
<lb/>There with a pious soul he praised the Maker,
</p>

<pb n="62"/>
<milestone unit="calced" n="2060"/>

<p>
<lb/>And said: <q>Son of the kings of kings am I,
<lb/>And would have naught but quiet in the world.
<lb/>The mischief-maker shall not be exalted
<lb/>While I am Shah, but him that from his heart
<lb/>Ensueth right, and is not mischievous,
<lb/>Will I hold dear as my pure soul, and seek not
<lb/>To harm the harmless. Him that beareth toil
<lb/>On our behalf we will reward with treasure.
<lb/>We will hold dear all friends and raise the fame
<lb/>Of chieftains everywhere, but all my subjects,
<lb/>Both friends and enemies, are safe with me.</q>
<lb/>The troops all blessed him: <q>Ne’er may earth and time
<lb/>Lack thee.</q> Yet when his throne was one month old
<lb/>The head of all his fortune came to dust.
<lb/>He had a slave, a cypress-tree in stature,
<lb/>Fair, lusty, and well-liking. That knave’s name
<lb/>Was Siyah Chashm.<note n="1">Black-eyed.</note> May heaven ne’er bring his like!
<lb/>The Shah too had a handmaid whom he loved.
<lb/>She chanced on Siyah Chashm all unawares
<lb/>One day, who sent to say: <q>If thou wilt meet me
<lb/>At such a place thou shalt have endless gifts,
<lb/>And I will deck thy crown with jewelry.</q>
<lb/>The handmaid heard, made no reply, but went
<lb/>And told the thing to Farrukhzad who raged,
<lb/>And could not eat or sleep in his concern.
<lb/>He put the feet of Siyah Chashm in fetters,
<lb/>And cast him into prison. When the knave
<lb/>Had been confined awhile the Shah released him,
<lb/>For many pled for him. The slave returned
<lb/>To serve the Shah and cut his lifetime short,
<lb/>For just as such a bad malignant slave
<lb/>Would do he sought revenge upon the Shah,
<lb/>And seizing on a time when Farrukhzad
</p>

<pb n="63"/>

<p>
<lb/>Reposed himself put poison in the wine.
<lb/>The Shah drank, lived one week, and all that heard
<lb/>About his fate lamented him. The kingship
<lb/>Was in extremities and foes appeared
<lb/>On every side. The throne of king of kings,
<lb/>Through these ill doings of the Iranians,
<lb/>Was overturned.
<lb/>Of such a fashion are
<lb/>Time’s revolutions! Let it be thy care
<lb/>To gather for thyself therefrom thy share.
<lb/>Eat what thou hast and trust the morrow not,
<lb/>For it may hold for thee a different lot:
<lb/>To give to others it may take from thee.
<lb/>Thou callest this a world and verily
<lb/>It doth whirl! So enjoy thine own, let go
<lb/>The surplusage that thou hast toiled for so
<lb/>To other folk but never to thy foe,
<lb/>Else whensoe’er thy day is overpast
<lb/>Thy hoards will be as is the desert-blast,
<lb/>Thy treasures all become thine enemy’s;
<lb/>So give away to set thy mind at ease.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div><head>L. YAZDAGIRD: HE REIGNED TWENTY YEARS</head>

<div>
<head>ARGUMENT</head>
<p><pb n="64"/>
Yazdagird becomes Shah. The country is invaded by the
Arabs. He sends Rustam, the captain of the host, to oppose
them. Rustam takes a despondent view of the situation,
and after some attempt at negotiations, is defeated by the Arabs
at Qadisiyah and slain. The war continues, and Yazdagird
withdraws to Khurasan to get help from Mahwi of Sur, the
governor. Mahwi plots with Bizhan, a Turkish prince,
against Yazdagird, who is betrayed in battle and takes refuge
in a mill, where he is slain by the miller at the bidding of
Mahwi. Mahwi assumes the crown, makes war on Bizhan,
is taken prisoner, and put to death. The poem ends with a
brief passage, in which Firdausi gives some account of the
completion of his undertaking, of help afforded him and of
discouragements undergone, and concludes with a well-founded
assurance of his own future fame.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>NOTE</head>
<p>Yazdagird (Yazdegerd III, A.D. 632-652 or 653) has given
his name to a chronological era which still obtains among the
Parsis. It dates from June 16th, A.D. 632. He was the son
of Shahryar, son of Khosrow Parviz, and was an infant at
the time when that Shah and his sons were put to death
after the accession of Sheroe (Kavadh;<note>See p. 34, 35.</note>) On that occasion he was taken for safety to Istakhr. Tabari says that he was

<pb n="65"/>
murdered at the age of twenty-eight after a reign of twenty
years. He was therefore only eight years old when a party
among the nobles set him up as a puppet king at Istakhr
(Persepolis), the old seat of empire, Ctesiphon at that time
being in the hands of a rival claimant of the throne. In the
contention that followed Yazdagird was successful, and in
the course of A.D. 633 he became recognised as sole Shah,
the administration remaining in the hands of the chiefs.<note>NT, p. 397 seq. and notes.</note>
He had succeeded to a heritage of woe. His empire was
ill-prepared for the troubles that were in store for it. Exhausted by long wars, torn by domestic dissensions, and
lately devastated by plague, it had to confront a new and
vigorous organization inspired by religious enthusiasm and
impelled thereby to extend its borders on every side. Had
Yazdagird been a born leader of men and come to the throne
in the prime of life, he might for the time at least have been
successful, but in the circumstances, and taking into consideration what we can gather as to his own character, we
can now see how hopeless from the outset his prospects were.
Students of Persian, however, have probably reason to feel
grateful to his reign, for even though we put aside as unsatisfactory what tradition tells us on the subject, a reasonable
presumption remains that with the return of settled government to a distracted country there was a revival of interest
in the story of the Iranian race and its heroes, and that compilations were then made from which we still though indirectly
benefit.<note>Cf. Vol. 1., p. 67.</note></p>



<p>§§ 2-11. The following is intended to supplement Firdausi's inadequate account of the Arab conquest of the Sasanian empire. He appears to assign it to the last years of Yazdagird’s then nominal sovereignty. From time immemorial the Iranians and Semites had been at enmity.<note n="1">Cf. Vol. 1., p. 10.</note> In Iranian legend, this feeling had found expression in the story of the wicked Shah Zahhak, who, though originally an Aryan myth,<note n="2">Cf. Vol. 1., p. 7.</note> came to be regarded in succeeding ages as an earthly king with his seat at Babylon. When, later still, the Iranians again felt the weight of Semitic oppression, he was turned into an Arab<note n="3">Cf. Vol. 1., p. 54, 135, 141.</note> Although during Sasanian times the semi-independent kingdom of Hira served to some extent as a buffer state between the Persian empire and the wilder Arab tribes, there was always the liability of raids, and the danger was much increased when Khusrau Parviz was so unwise as to put an end to the long-standing dynasty of the princes of Hira and appointed a governor of his own in their stead.<note>Vol. viii., p. 190.</note></p>

<pb n="66"/>

<p>In his reign too had occurred the disastrous battle of Dhu Qar, in which the smallness of the forces engaged were out of all proportion to the importance of the result. The Arabs celebrated their victory with songs of triumph.<note>NT, p. 342.</note> With that inspiring memory and revelation of Persian weakness, with the prospect of rich spoil to be won, and a nation of infidels to be converted, it is not surprising that hostilities should break out between the young and vigorous and the old and enfeebled empire. Muhammad himself, tradition tells us, addressed a threatening letter to Khusrau Parviz, who tore it up, and the Prophet, on hearing of this, said: “He has rent his own realm.”<note>ZT, ii., 325.</note> Muhammad died in June, A.D. 632— the month of the child Yazdagird’s accession. Abu Bakr, the first Caliph, being apprised by an Arab chieftain, who had embraced Islam, of the state of the Persian empire, sent his great general, Khalid, to begin hostilities. Khalid was very successful in numerous engagements, and temporarily the whole tract bordering the western bank of the Euphrates from the Roman frontier almost to the Persian Gulf came into the hands of the Arabs. Khalid made Hira his headquarters, and was preparing to attack Ctesiphon and invade Iran when he was recalled by Abu Bakr to take command of the forces destined for the Syrian campaign. “This is Umar’s doing,” said Khalid. “He does not want to see me conquer Iraq.”<note>ZT, iii., 348.</note> The departure of Khalid was the Persians’ opportunity. Encouraged by Rustam, who under Yazdagird had become commander-in-chief, the inhabitants of the conquered region rose against the Arabs but unsuccessfully. At this juncture Abu Bakr died and was succeeded by Umar, who began his reign by giving Abu Ubaida the chief command in Syria in the place of Khalid.</p>


<p>Then, it is said, he appealed publicly to the Faithful to volunteer for the invasion of Persia and for two days in vain, the supersession of Khalid having caused great indignation. It may, however, have been thought that the acquisition of so much fertile territory and the consequent proximity to the Persian <pb n="67"/> capital, were a sufficient achievement for the time being.</p>



<p>Nevertheless, on the third day, when Umar made his appeal, Abu Ubaida (not Khalid’s successor) offered himself and Sa’ad, son of Wakas, followed suit. A thousand others imitated their example. Umar gave Abu Ubaida the chief command as he had been the first to volunteer. The Persians in the meantime had withdrawn to Ctesiphon, whence Rustam dispatched a force, which had with it the flag of Kewa,<note>Vol. i., p. 154 seq.</note> to watch the enemy. Abu Ubaida, who was very inferior in numbers, threw a bridge across the Euphrates, attacked the Persians, was defeated and slain. This battle is known as <term>The Battle of the Bridge,</term> and took place in November, A.D. 634. An attack, however, by the Persians on Hira failed, and the Arabs raided the Persian settlement of Baghdad (not of course the well-known city of that name)<note>See Vol. vi., p. 254.</note> where twice a year a fair was held. Umar appointed Sa’ad, son of Wakas, to succeed Abu Ubaida, and both sides made efforts to reinforce their respective armies. The Persian adherents west of the Euphrates again rose. Rustam crossed the river with a great host, and advanced to Kadisiya where the Arabs had concentrated. The battle that ensued is said to have lasted four days with varying fortune till a dust-storm turned the scale in favour of the Arabs. The slaughter was very great and so was the spoil. Umar forbade the Arabs to make any further advance for the present, but as the situation of their camp proved to be very unhealthy, he directed Sa’ad to choose a more suitable site, whereupon Sa’ad founded Kufa. Thenceforth the whole of the region west of the Euphrates was lost to the Persians. To secure the lower course of the Euphrates and Tigris, Umar also founded Basra, west of the Shatt-al-Arab. The battle of Kadisiya seems to have been fought A.D. 636-7, but the chronology of the period is somewhat uncertain. Then came a considerable pause in the Arab advance. The Arabs seem to have spent the interval well in securing what they had gained while the Persians on the other hand appear to have been paralysed by their misfortunes.</p>

<p>At all events, when the invasion was resumed and Sa’ad, crossing the Euphrates, marched on Ctesiphon, no resistance was offered, and Yazdagird, who had lingered there too late to secure the removal of most of his treasures, fled with his court to Hulwan.<note>See Vol. vii., p. 187.</note> His example of flight seems <pb n="68"/> to have been followed by a majority of the inhabitants. The Arabs came in for an immense booty according to Oriental accounts. If, however, we take into consideration the domestic troubles of the years preceding Yazdagird’s accession, and what must have been the financial needs of the short-lived Shahs of that period, we are justified in suspecting that the amount of precious metals and of the more portable forms of wealth generally was not so great as has been affirmed. Sa’ad, when he had established himself in the Persian capital, asked permission of Umar to pursue Yazdagird who had gathered a considerable army under the command of a Mihran<note>See Vol. vii., p. 185.</note> at Jalula in the neighbourhood of Hulwan. Umar refused to allow Sa’ad to go in person and instructed him to send instead Hashim, who was either his brother or his nephew. Hashim was much inferior in point of numbers, and it was six months before he brought the Persians to a decisive engagement. He then won a complete victory, and followed up his success at Jalula by the capture of Hulwan. Yazdagird fled to Rai, and Umar, content for the moment with what had been achieved, forbade any further advance. The next stage of the Arab conquest was made outside the sphere of Sa’ad’s authority, who sent, however, by Umar’s command troops to assist. In the north, Mesopotamia, and in the south, Khuzistan, were invaded and annexed. A raid was made also across the Persian Gulf from Bahrain into Pars, but without lasting results, as the Arab forces got into difficulties and had to be rescued by an expedition sent for the purpose from Basra. About A.D. 640, in consequence, it is said, of complaints made by the people of Kufa, Umar recalled Sa’ad, and Yazdagird seized the opportunity to make a supreme effort to recover his lost possessions. A large army, summoned from the yet unconquered provinces of the empire, was concentrated at Nahavand, some fifty miles south of Hamadan, and placed under a Persian general named Piruzan. On this, Umar ordered Numan, who was in command in Khuzistan, to gather all available forces from the regions already annexed and march against the enemy. Numan, who was greatly inferior in point of numbers, found the Persians strongly encamped at Nahavand and tried in vain to bring on a general engagement. In the end, he managed to effect his purpose by means of a stratagem.</p>
<p>He broke up <pb n="69"/>his camp and made a hasty retreat. Piruzan went in pursuit, on which Numan turned upon him and won what the Arabs call "The Victory of Victories" (A.D. 641-2). Piruzan was taken prisoner and slain, and Numan himself fell in the fight. This was the last effort of the Persians at national resistance. Henceforth, their opposition was merely provincial or local, and wholly ineffective. One after another, the remaining provinces of the Sasanian empire were overtaken by the Arabs and permanently annexed, while Yazdagird, who had fled from Rai after the disaster of Nahavand, remained a fugitive until his death some ten years later.</p>





<p>§2. In Tabari, Rustam’s father is called Farrukh-Hurmuzd,
the governor of Khurasan, who was slain, it is said, by Azarmidukht and avenged by his son.<note n="1">p. 59.</note> Khurasan probably formed
part of the satrapy of Nimruz, one of the four into which Khusrow Anushirwan divided his empire.<note n="2">See Vol. vii., p. 214.</note> Tradition makes the governors
of that satrapy, and their sons play a very important part
during the last few years of the Sasanian dynasty.<note n="3">pp. 5, 6, 59, 87, 95 seq.</note> The
position of commander-in-chief held by Rustam at the battle
of Qadisiyah probably indicates that he had been instrumental
in bringing about the elevation of Yazdagird to the throne.<note n="4">NT, p. 397 note. NIN, p. 13.</note>
</p>
<p>
Rustam’s brother was named Farrukhzad.
</p>


<p>§3. Mughira, son of Shu’ba, was one of the companions
of Muhammad, and played a prominent role in the affairs of
the time. He went on a similar embassy to the Persians
before the battle of Nahavand.<note n="5">ZT, ii., 474.</note> He was governor for a time
at Basra,<note n="6">ZT, ii., 404.</note> Mecca,<note n="7">ZT, iv., 2.</note> and Kufa, where he died in A.D. 670.<note n="8">ZT, iv., 16.</note>
</p>


<p>§4. Sa’ad took no personal part in the battle of Qadisiyah.
He was suffering from sores at the time and had to content
himself with merely directing operations.<note n="9">ZT, iii., 398.</note> Consequently,
he did not slay Rustam in single combat as Firdausi states.
When the dust-storm came on the fourth day of the battle,
Rustam was seated under an awning erected on the bank
of the canal of Qadisiyah and surrounded by the camels that
carried his treasure. The awning was blown into the water,
and Rustam took shelter among them. In the confusion
caused by the storm, the Arabs broke the Persian centre.
One of them, named Hilal, striking in the darkness at random
among the camels, happened to hit the one under which

<pb n="70"/>
Rustam was seated, and cut the cord that secured its load
of treasure which fell on Rustam’s head. Though injured,
he made an attempt to swim across the canal, but was caught
by Hilal and slain.<note n="10">ZT, iii., 396.</note>
</p>



<p>§§9-11.  There is a general agreement in Persian tradition
that Yazdagird did not die a natural death. The scene of it
is mostly laid at Merv, and the most popular version associates
it with a mill. Firdausi's story evidently has been worked up
as the appeals addressed to Mahwi show. The villain’s
guilt too is more emphasized, and he is made more directly
responsible for the tragedy. Elsewhere the miller murders
the Shah for mere greed. Merv appears to be a likely place
for Yazdagird to have chosen to reside in, as he could easily
escape thence across the Oxus in case of need. In some
accounts, he does cross and negotiates to little purpose with
the Turks, but is brought back across the river for the final
scene. What the truth of the matter was seems to be quite
uncertain.
</p>


<p>
§14. 
According to the account in the Persian Tabari,
Mahwi, after the death of Yazdagird, remained at Merv till
he was compelled to leave owing to the approach of the Arabs,
when he fled across the Oxus and took refuge with the Turks.<note n="11">ZT, iii., 505.</note>
Their Khan is the Bizhan of the Shahnama.
</p>


</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><head>How Yazdagird ascended the Throne and addressed the Chiefs</head>
<p>
<lb/>When Farrukhzad departed Yazdagird
<lb/>Became the Shah upon the day of Ard
<lb/>In month Sapandarmad. What said the man
<lb/>Brave, eloquent but weary of life’s span?
<lb/><q>Would that my mother had not brought me forth,
<lb/>High heaven not turned o’er me!
<lb/>The days of greatness and the days of want

<pb n="71"/>
<lb/>For all soon cease to be.
<lb/>Time, as thou lookest, passeth; none can take
<lb/>Arms to contend with it,
<lb/>So furnish forth the board and drain the cup,
<lb/>And sad talk intermit.
<lb/>What though thou ride high heaven yet bricks will prove
<lb/>Thy pillow at the last;
<lb/>If thou be king what of the end? First throne,
<lb/>But what when life hath past?
<lb/>Let not thy heart be troubled, trust not much
<lb/>High heaven as thy support;
<lb/>It acteth as it willeth; elephant
<lb/>And lion are its sport.
<lb/>Twil outlast thee, its tale is long; be not
<lb/>With pride of life o’erflown;
<milestone unit="calced" n="2061"/>
<lb/>Thou canst not better Faridun or be
<lb/>Parviz<note n="1">Khusrau Parviz.</note> with crown and throne.<note n="2">Couplet omitted.</note>
<lb/>From those exalt seven planets do thou well
<lb/>Consider what to Yazdagird befell.</q>
<lb/>When he sat happy on the throne of kingship,
<lb/>And placed upon his head the crown of might,
<lb/>He said: <q>By process of the turning sky
<lb/>I am the true-born son of Nushirwan.
<lb/>Mine is the sway from sire to sire and mine
<lb/>Are Virgo, Sol, and Pisces. I will seek
<lb/>For greatness, wisdom, hardihood, contention,
<lb/>And manliness, for life and fortune stay
<lb/>With none, nor treasure, kingship, crown, and throne.
<lb/>Fame will abide for aye but not desire;
<lb/>Put off desire then and exalt thy fame.
<lb/>It is by fame that man shall live forever
<lb/>While his dead body lieth in the dust.
<lb/>How good are Faith and justice in a Shah!
<lb/>The times are full of blessings on his fame.




<pb n="72"/>

<lb/>I purpose while I live to pluck up ill,
<lb/>Both root and branch.</q>
<lb/>The chiefs applauded him,
<lb/>And hailed him as the monarch of the earth,
<lb/>And thus it was, till sixteen years had sped,
<lb/>That sun and moon revolved above his head.
</p>
</div>







<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><head>How Sa’ad, Son of Wakkas, invaded Iran, how Yazdagird sent Rustam to oppose him, and how Rustam wrote a Letter to his Brother</head>
<p>
<lb/>It was so that Umar, the famous Arab,
<lb/>Commander of the Faithful,<note n="1">He assumed this title.</note> he whose sword
<lb/>Turned day to night, the man approved by God,
<lb/>Who hath no equal, sent the chosen Sa’ad,
<lb/>Son of Wakkas, with troops against the Shah.
<lb/>When Arab fortune worsted Persian,
<lb/>And the Sasanians’ fortune had grown dark,
<lb/>The world had had full measure of its Shahs;
<lb/>Gold was not seen, the mite was manifest,
<lb/>Good turned to evil, evil turned to good,
<lb/>The path lay Hellward, not to Paradise,
<lb/>The wheel of circling heaven was changed and cut
<lb/>All kindness for the Persians clean away.
<lb/>The slave must do the almighty Maker’s will,
<lb/>And bear what He inflicteth. Save with Him
<lb/>There is no life or joy.
<lb/>When Yazdagird
<lb/>Learned what had chanced he gathered troops on all sides, 
</p>
<milestone unit="calced" n="2062"/>
<pb n="73"/>
<p>
<lb/>And bade Hurmuzd’s son lead them forth. His name
<lb/>Was Rustam. He was wary, wise, a warrior
<lb/>And potentate, a reader of the stars,
<lb/>Exceeding shrewd and all attent to hear
<lb/>The archimages’ words. He marched away
<lb/>With all the noble, those that were alert
<lb/>And brave, and after thirty months they sought
<lb/>To fight at Kädisiya. Being learned
<lb/>In heaven’s lore as an astrologer,
<lb/>And one both just and good, he said: <q>No time
<lb/>Is this to fight, the river of the Shahs
<lb/>Will flow not in this bed,</q> and so he took
<lb/>His astrolabe, observed the stars and smote
<lb/>His head because it was a day of bale,
<lb/>Then wrote in grief and told his brother all,
<lb/>First offering praise to God who had ordained
<lb/>His good and evil fortune, and proceeded:—
</p>

<p>
<lb/><q>Well may the revolutions of the sky
<lb/>Fill the observer with disquietude!
<lb/>I am the guiltiest person of the time,
<lb/>And therefore have been caught by Ahriman,
<lb/>Because the kingship passeth from this House;
<lb/>No season this of conquest and the Grace!
<lb/>From the fourth heaven Sol is looking down
<lb/>To hasten to the fight of mighty men.
<lb/>Both Mars and Venus bode mishap to us,
<lb/>And none can 'scape high heaven. Mercury
<lb/>And Saturn are opposed, the former too
<lb/>Hath entered Gemini. Such is the case,
<lb/>A great event is toward, and my heart
<lb/>Is weary of its life. I can discern
<lb/>All that will be but fain would hold my peace.
<lb/>When I agnized this secret of the sky—
<lb/>That it assigneth us but grievous travail—
<lb/>I wept right sorely for the Iranians,
<lb/>And burned for the Sasanians. Woe is me
<lb/>For head and crown, for state and throne, and woe


<pb n="74"/>


<lb/>For majesty, for fortune, and for Grace
<lb/>Because hereafter will defeat betide them
<lb/>From the Arabians, the stars not turn
<lb/>Save to our hurt, and for four hundred years
<lb/>None of our royal race will rule the world!
<lb/>An envoy from our foemen came to me,
<lb/>And divers parleyings followed. <q>We,</q> they said,
<lb/><q>Will give up to the Shah the tract between
<lb/>The river-bank and Kadisiya; ye
<lb/>Shall grant us access to some trading centre
<lb/>That we may sell and buy; we will not ask
<lb/>For more hereafter; we will pay large dues,
<lb/>And will not seek the chieftains' diadems,
<milestone unit="calced" n="2063"/>
<lb/>But will obey withal the king of kings,
<lb/>And render hostages at his demand.</q>
<lb/>Such is the talk. No action hath ensued,
<lb/>But still the stars are adverse. Long will be
<lb/>The strife. Fierce Lions will be slain by hundreds.

<lb/>The chieftains that are with me in the war—
<lb/>Galbwi of Tabaristan and Armani,
<lb/>Who do the deeds of Ahriman in fight,
<lb/>Mahwi, he of Suran, and other chiefs,
<lb/>Who wield the heavy mace and battle-ax—
<lb/>Heed not our foes proposals but observe:—
<lb/><q>Who are these haughty folk and what do they
<lb/>Both in Iran and in Mazandaran?
<lb/>For road and territory, weal and woe,
<lb/>We must employ the mace and scimitar;
<lb/>We will exert ourselves, quit us like men,
<lb/>And make the world both dark and strait to them.</q>
<lb/>None of them knoweth circling heaven’s design,
<lb/>And how its aspect hath been changed to us.





<lb/>On reading this take measures with the chiefs,
<lb/>Make preparations and lead forth the host,
<lb/>Collect the treasures, handmaids, and state-robes,
<lb/>Then hasten Azar Abadagan—
<pb n="75"/>
<lb/>The dwelling of the Mighty and the Free.
<lb/>Whatever herds of horses thou mayst have
<lb/>Send to the treasurer of Azargashasp.
<lb/>If soldiers seek thee from Zabulistan,
<lb/>Or from Iran, imploring thy protection,
<lb/>Receive and treat with kindness their excuses
<lb/>In view of what the turning sky is doing—
<lb/>The cause of joy and terror to us all,
<lb/>At whiles exalting and at whiles abasing.

<lb/>Let mother know my words for of a truth
<lb/>She will not look upon my face again,
<lb/>Greet her from us and counsel her at large
<lb/>Not to be troubled here below. If any
<lb/>Shall bring bad news of me be not too downcast,
<lb/>For know that in this Wayside Hostelry
<lb/>He that amasseth treasure by his toil
<lb/>Will find his toil more than such worldly treasure,
<lb/>And that another will enjoy the fruit.
<lb/>What need was there for so much toil and greed?
<lb/>Desire is lessened not by having more.

<lb/>At all times worship God and purge thy heart
<lb/>Of all affection for this Wayside Inn
<lb/>Because our fortune is in straits, the king
<lb/>Will see me not again. Do thou and all
<lb/>Our House, both old and young, unceasingly
<lb/>Praise God and pray the Maker, for with this
<lb/>My host I am in stress, in travail, grief,
<milestone unit="calced" n="2064"/>
<lb/>And bitter fortune, and shall not escape
<lb/>At last. May this sweet country of Iran
<lb/>Be in prosperity! Whenas the world
<lb/>Is straitened to the king hold treasure, life,
<lb/>And person of small worth, for of that race
<lb/>So famed and honoured there is no once left
<lb/>Save that exalted one. Watch over him
<lb/>By day and night till I have fought the Arabs.
<lb/>Be not remiss in toil for he is now


<pb n="76"/>


<lb/>All that we have to look to in this world,
<lb/>And the Sasanians’ memorial,
<lb/>For no one will behold that House again.
<lb/>Woe for the head and crown, for seal and right
<lb/>Since royal throne will go adown the blast!
<lb/>Fare well, be not concerned, and ever be
<lb/>Before the world-lord, and if ill betide him
<lb/>First give thine own head to the scimitar
<lb/>Ungrudgingly. When pulpit fronteth throne,
<lb/>And when Abu Bakr and ’Umar shall be
<lb/>As household words, our long toils will be lost,
<lb/>And long will be the fall before the rise.
<lb/>Thou wilt not see throne, diadem, or state:
<lb/>The stars award the Arabs everything.

<lb/>There will not be throne, crown, or golden boot,
<lb/>Or gem, or coronet or flaunting flag.
<lb/>One man will toil, another will enjoy;
<lb/>None will give heed to justice or to bounty.
<lb/>Then warriors will be men that fight afoot
<lb/>While horsemen will be mocked and flouted at;
<lb/>The warlike husbandman will be despised,
<lb/>High birth and majesty will bear no fruit;
<lb/>Then men will rob each other, none will know
<lb/>A blessing from a curse, and secret dealing
<lb/>Prevail o’er open, while the hearts of men
<lb/>Will turn to flint, sire will be foe to son,
<lb/>And son will scheme ’gainst sire; a worthless slave
<lb/>Will be the king, high birth and majesty
<lb/>Will count for nothing; no one will be loyal.
<lb/>There will be tyranny of soul and tongue.
<lb/>A mongrel race—Iranian, Turkman, Arab—
<lb/>Will come to be and talk in gibberish.


<milestone unit="calced" n="2065"/>


<lb/>They will collect all treasures neath their skirts,
<lb/>Toil and resign the product to their foes.
<pb n="77"/>
<lb/>Grief, travail, bitterness will thus prevail
<lb/>As joy did in Bahram Gur’s days; feasts, song,
<lb/>Race and renown will cease; men will set traps,
<lb/>Will seek their profit in another’s loss,
<lb/>And make their pretext Faith; no difference
<lb/>Will be ’twixt Spring and Winter; there will be
<lb/>No wine at feasts; they will not recognise
<lb/>Degree and place but live on barley-bread,
<lb/>And dress in wool. When much time hath passed thus
<lb/>None will regard the noble Persian stock.





<lb/>They will be shedding blood for lucre’s sake,
<lb/>An evil age will be inaugurate.
<lb/>My heart is full, my face is wan, my mouth
<lb/>Is parched, my lips are filled with sighs to think
<lb/>That after I—the paladin—have gone
<lb/>Sasanian fortune shall become thus dark;
<lb/>So faithless hath revolving heaven grown,
<lb/>Ta’en umbrage, and withdrawn from us its love!
<lb/>If with my lance I strike a brazen mountain
<lb/>I pierce it, being brazen-bodied too,
<lb/>But now my shafts with steel-transfixing heads
<lb/>Are impotent with men that wear no mail!
<lb/>My sword, which felled the necks of elephants
<lb/>And lions at a blow, can not cut through
<lb/>An Arab skin! My knowledge bringeth loss
<lb/>On loss upon me. Would that I possessed not
<lb/>This wisdom since it causeth me to know
<lb/>Of this ill day! The chiefs that are with me
<lb/>From Kadisiya are both hardy men
<lb/>And hostile to the Arabs. They expect
<lb/>That this brake will be filled, that earth will run
<lb/>Like the Jihun, with our foes’ blood. None knoweth
<lb/>The secret of the skies and that this strife


<pb n="78"/>


<lb/>Can not be quickly ended; but when fortune
<lb/>Departeth from a race what profit cometh
<lb/>Of travail and of fight? Be prosperous,
<lb/>My brother! May the Shah’s heart joy in thee
<lb/>Because this Kadisiya is my charnel,
<lb/>My breastplate is my shroud, my helmet blood:
<lb/>Such is the secret of the lofty sky.
<lb/>Bind not thine own heart to my griefs but keep
<lb/>Thine eyes upon the Shah, and sacrifice
<lb/>Thyself for him in fight, because the day
<lb/>Of Ahriman is coming on apace
<lb/>When circling heaven will show us enmity.</q>
</p><p>
<lb/>When he had sealed the letter he said thus:—
<lb/><q>My blessing be upon the messenger
<lb/>That shall convey this letter to my brother,
<lb/>And tell him not what I have said, but other!</q>
</p>


</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><head>How Rustam wrote to Saad, Son of Wakkas, and how he replied</head>
<milestone unit="calced" n="2066"/>
<p>
<lb/>He sent a messenger in swiftness like
<lb/>The flash and thunder-clap to Sa’ad. They wrote,
<lb/>In apprehension yet not in despair,
<lb/>A letter on white silk and thus endorsed :—
<lb/><q>This from the paladin of paladins—
<lb/>The warlike Rustam, son of Hurmuz—<note n="1">Cf. Mardänshäh as a proper name and p. 59.</note>
<lb/>To Sa’ad, son of Wakkas, the prudent, wise,
<lb/>And circumspect, who hath come forth to fight.</q>
<lb/>It thus began: <q>We still must fear the World-lord,
<lb/>The Holy, who sustaineth turning heaven,
<pb n="79"/>
<lb/>Whose rule is justice and beneficence.
<lb/>May blessings from Him rest upon the king,
<lb/>The lustre of the signet, crown, and throne,
<lb/>The lord of sword, of diadem and lasso,
<lb/>Whose Grace restraineth Ahriman in bonds.
<lb/>A hateful matter hath occurred to us
<lb/>In these uncalled for labours and this strife.
<lb/>Reply to me and say who is your king,
<lb/>Who thou art, what thy rule and custom are,
<lb/>And whose assistance is it that ye seek
<lb/>With unmailed soldiery and unmailed chief ?
<lb/>Fed up with bread thou art still ravenous ;
<lb/>Thou hast no elephants, no throne, no baggage.
<lb/>Enough for thee to live within Iran,
<lb/>For crown and signet are another man’s,
<lb/>Who hath Grace, elephants, and crown and throne—
<lb/>A famous Shah of lengthy lineage.
<lb/>No throned king hath such stature or the moon
<lb/>In heaven such aspect. When enthroned he sitteth
<lb/>With smiles that make his silvern teeth appear ;
<lb/>His gifts would purchase Arabs in the gross,
<lb/>And not impoverish his treasury.
<lb/>His dogs, his hawks, and cheetahs are twelve thousand,
<lb/>And they are decked with golden bells and varvels.
<lb/>The whole waste of the wielders of the spear
<lb/>Could find not in a year from end to end
<lb/>Enough to feed his cheetahs and his hounds
<lb/>When he is hunting on the plain. The Arabs,
<lb/>From drinking camels’ milk and eating lizards,
<lb/>Have reached a pitch whereat the Persian throne
<lb/>Is coveted! Shame, shame on circling heaven !
<lb/>Ye have no veneration in your eyes,
<lb/>Or, in your wisdom, love or reverence.
<lb/>With such a visage and such tastes and ways
<lb/>Is thy heart set upon the crown and throne ?
<lb/>If thou art seeking power within thy means,
<pb n="80"/>
<lb/>And art not merely speaking words in jest,
<milestone unit="calced" n="2067"/>
<lb/>Dispatch to us some man of goodly speech,
<lb/>Send some brave veteran and man of lore,
<lb/>That he may tell me thine intent and who
<lb/>Doth lead thee to attempt the royal throne.
<lb/>Then will I send a horseman to the Shah
<lb/>To ask of him whatever thou wilt ask,
<lb/>But seek not with so great a king to fight,
<lb/>For shame at last will come upon thy face.
<lb/>His grandsire was the world-lord Nushirwan,
<lb/>Whose justice made the aged young again.
<lb/>His fathers have been Shahs, and he is king ;
<lb/>The age remembereth none like to him.
<lb/>Fill not the world with curses on thyself,
<lb/>Misprize not thine own precedents. Regard
<lb/>This letter of advice and bar not thou
<lb/>Thine eyes and ears to wisdom.</q> When the letter
<lb/>Was sealed he gave it to high-born Piruz,
<lb/>Son of Shaptr. To Sa’ad, son of Wakkas,
<lb/>This paladin and magnates from Iran,
<lb/>Of ardent soul, went whelmed in iron, silver,
<lb/>And gold, with golden shields and golden girdles.
<lb/>On hearing, Sa’ad, that noble man, set forth,
<lb/>Swift as the flying dust, to meet Piruz
<lb/>With troops, forthwith dismounted and inquired
<lb/>About the army and its paladin,
<lb/>About the Shah, his minister and host,
<lb/>The watchful leader and his provinces.
<lb/>He spread his cloak beneath Piruz and said :—
<lb/><q>We hold the sword and spear to be our mates :
<lb/>Brave warriors make no mention of brocade,
<lb/>Of gold and silver or of food and slumber.
<lb/>Ye have no part in manhood but are like
<lb/>To women with your colours, scents, and forms.
<lb/>Your prowess is in donning broidery,
<lb/>Adorning roofs and decorating doors.</q>
<pb n="81"/>
<lb/>Piruz then gave the letter and told Sa’ad
<lb/>The words of Rustam. Sa’ad heard, read, and
<lb/>wondered.
<lb/>He wrote an answer back in Arabic,
<lb/>Announcing good and ill. He wrote there first
<lb/>The name of God and of His messenger,
<lb/>Muhammad, who directeth to the truth.
<lb/>He spake of Jins and men, of what the Prophet,
<lb/>The Hashimite,<note n="2">Hashim was the great-grandfather of Muhammad.</note> had said, the Unity
<lb/>Of God, of the Quran, of promise, warning,
<lb/>Of menace and of novel usages,
<lb/>Of liquid pitch, of fire, and icy cold,
<lb/>Of Paradise, its streams of milk and wine,
<lb/>Of camphor and of musk, of bubbling springs,
<lb/>Of wine and honey and the trees of heaven.<note n="3">This is taken from the Quran. Cf. Vol.i., p. 99.</note>
<lb/>Then: <q> If the Shah accepteth the true Faith
<lb/>. He will obtain both worlds with joy and kingship,
<lb/>And have withal the earrings and the crown,
<lb/>Perpetual beauty and prosperity.
<milestone unit="calced" n="2068"/>
<lb/>His intercessor there will be Muhammad,
<lb/>His form like pure rose-water. In as much
<lb/>As Paradise will be thy recompense
<lb/>We must not plant thorns in the garth of bale.
<lb/>The personality of Yazdagird,
<lb/>This spacious world, such gardens, riding-grounds,
<lb/>And halls and palaces with all the thrones
<lb/>And crowns, the festivals and revelries,
<lb/>Are less worth than one hair of an Houri.
<lb/>In this our Wayside Hostelry thine eyes
<lb/>Are dazed by crown and treasure, and thou trustest
<lb/>Too much in ivory throne, in wealth, and signet,
<lb/>In fortune and in crown. Why be concerned
<lb/>About a world when one draught of cold water
<lb/>Out-prizeth it ? Whoever cometh forth
<pb n="82"/>
<lb/>To fight with me will see a narrow grave,
<lb/>And Hell, naught else; but Paradise is his
<lb/>If he believeth. Mark how he should fare.
<lb/>He still will choose the one and shun the other
<lb/>As every wise man knoweth.</q>
<lb/>Then he set
<lb/>The Arab seal thereon and praised Muhammad.
<lb/>The messenger of Sa’ad, son of Wakkas,
<lb/>Went with all speed to Rustam. Now what time
<lb/>Shu’ba Mughfra went forth from the chiefs
<lb/>To journey to the paladin, a noble,
<lb/>One of the Iranians, came in from the way
<lb/>Before the captain of the host, and said :—
<lb/><q> A messenger hath come—a weak, old man—
<lb/>Without a horse or weapons and ill-clad,
<lb/>With thin sword slung about his neck and shirt
<lb/>All plainly tattered.</q>
<lb/>Rustam thus apprised
<lb/>Prepared a tent-enclosure of brocade.
<lb/>They laid a carpet of gold thread of Chin ;
<lb/>The soldiery turned out like ants and locusts.
<lb/>They set a golden ante-throne whereon
<lb/>The captain of the host assumed his seat
<lb/>With eight score warriors attending him—
<lb/>Horsemen and lions on the day of battle—
<lb/>With crowns, with violet robes, and golden boots,
<lb/>With torques and earrings, while the tent-enclosure
<lb/>Was royally adorned. Shu’ba Mughira,
<lb/>On coming to the tent-enclosure, walked not
<lb/>Upon the cloth but humbly on the ground,
<lb/>And used his scimitar as walking-stick.
<lb/>He sat upon the dust without a look
<lb/>At any—captain of the host or chief.
<lb/>Then Rustam said to him: <q> May thy soul joy,
<lb/>And by its knowledge make thy body strong.</q>
<lb/>Shu’ba Mughira said: <q>If thou, good sir !
<pb n="83"/>
<lb/>Acceptest the true Faith, peace unto thee.</q>
<milestone unit="calced" n="2069"/>
<lb/>Now Rustam, hearing this, was vexed and frowned.
<lb/>He took and gave the letter to a reader.
<lb/>That learned man told him what was writ, and Rustam
<lb/>Made answer: <q> Tell him: <q> Thou art neither king
<lb/>Nor an aspirant to the diadem,
<lb/>But thou hast seen my fortune in eclipse,<note n="4">Reading with P.</note>
<lb/>And so thy heart ambitioneth my throne.
<lb/>The case is one of moment to the wise,
<lb/>But thou hast not considered it. If Sa’ad
<lb/>Had the Sasanian throne I well might share
<lb/>His feasts and fights, but since the faithless stars
<lb/>Bode ill, what shall I say ? This is the day
<lb/>Of bale. If for my guide I take Muhammad,
<lb/>And this new Faith for old, all will go wrong
<lb/>Beneath this crook-backed sky, and all go hard
<lb/>With us.</q> But as for thee, depart in peace ;
<lb/>The day of battle is no time for words.
<lb/>Tell Sa’ad: <q> To die with honour is a thing
<lb/>Far better for me than crude parleying.</q></q>
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><head>How Rustam fought with Saad, Son of Wakkas, and was slain</head>
<p>
<lb/>Shu’ba Mughira went his way, and Rustam
<lb/>Bade to array the host and sound the trumpet.
<lb/>From all sides troops assembled, clouds of dust
<lb/>Arose, and din that deafed the sharpest ears.
<lb/><q>The steely lance-heads mid the murky reck
<lb/>Are,</q> thou hadst said, <q>stars mid night’s azure
<lb/>gloom,</q>
<pb n="84"/>
<lb/>While spears ne’er ceased to smite on glittering helms.
<lb/>The strife endured three days, till water failed
<lb/>The Iranians, and their warriors’ hands and steeds
<lb/>Became unfit for combat. Rustam’s lips
<lb/>Grew as the dust with drought, his tongue was split,
<lb/>And men and horses battened on moist clay,
<lb/>So grievous was the stress !
<lb/>Shouts rose like thunder
<lb/>From Rustam and from Sa’ad as they advanced,
<lb/>Each from his post. Each left his army’s centre,
<lb/>And drew off from the field. Departing thus
<lb/>They came beneath a steep-up eminence,
<lb/>And there those chieftains twain assailed each other
<lb/>Revengefully upon that scene of strife
<lb/>Till Rustam, roaring like a thunder-clap,
<lb/>Smote with his sword Sa’ad’s charger on the head,
<lb/>Smote the swift charger which came headlong down,
<milestone unit="calced" n="2070"/>
<lb/>And brave Sa’ad was unhorsed. Then Rustam reared
<lb/>Aloft a trenchant blade to show to him
<lb/>The Day of Doom, and was in mind to strike
<lb/>His head off, but by reason of the dust
<lb/>Raised by the troops they could not see each other.
<lb/>Then Rustam lighted from his steed and saddle
<lb/>Of leopard-skin and fastened to his belt
<lb/>His charger’s reins but, while dust blinded him,
<lb/>Sa’ad hurried up and smote him with the sword
<lb/>Upon his helm whence blood ran down his face,
<lb/>And while his eyes were blinded by the gore
<lb/>The aspiring Arab gained the upper hand,
<lb/>Again smote Rustam on the head and neck,
<lb/>And flung his warrior-body on the dust.
<lb/>None in the two hosts were aware thereof,
<lb/>Or whither those two paladins had gone,
<lb/>But searched until they found the scene of strife.
<lb/>The Iranians, when they spied their paladin
<lb/>Slashed by the scimitar from head to foot,
<pb n="85"/>
<lb/>Fled. Many a chief perished in the press,
<lb/>And many failed for thirst upon the saddle.
<lb/>The world had had full measure of the Shahs.
<lb/>The host fared to the monarch of Iran,
<lb/>And hastened on the way both day and night.
<lb/>When Rustam had been slain in fight, and when
<lb/>The chiefs’ heads were all turned, the Muslim host
<lb/>Sped like a savage lion in pursuit.<note>The French version of the rest of this section is as follows :— <q xml:lang="fra">Yezdegird était à Bagdad lorsque ses troupes affluèrent autour de lui. Farrukhzad, fils d'Hormuzd, furieux et répandant des larmes, traversa le Tigre, entra dans Kerkh et livra un assaut terrible qui ne laissa vivant aucun des guerriers armés de lances. Les troupes sortirent aussitôt de Bagdad et allèrent cher cher la combat dans la plaine ; mais lorsque la poussière de la lutte se fut dissipée, les Iraniens étaient en fuite.</q></note>
<lb/>At that time Yazdagird was at Baghdad ;
<lb/>To him the troops came flocking and announced
<lb/>That Rustam was no more, and that the sea
<lb/>Was dry with grief, that many men had fallen,
<lb/>And that the rest had fled the battlefield.
<lb/>The hosts, both Persian and Arabian,
<lb/>Reached Karkh, and Farrukhzad, son of Hurmuzd,
<lb/>Wroth and with tearful eyes came from the Arwand,
<lb/>Arrived at Karkh, fell on the enemy,
<lb/>And not an Arab warrior survived.
<lb/>The Persians marched out from Baghdad intent
<lb/>To meet the foe, and bloody was the event.

</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><head>How Yazdagird consulted with the Iranians and went to Khurasan</head>
<p>
<lb/>When Farrukhzad had gone back to the Shah,
<lb/>All over dust and in his fighting-gear,
<lb/>He lighted from his charger, did obeisance,
<pb n="86"/>
<lb/>Blood in his eyes and anguish in his heart,
<lb/>And said to Yazdagird: <q>Why weep so much?
<lb/>Is it to wash the throne of kings with tears?
<milestone unit="calced" n="2071"/>
<lb/>Thou only of the royal race art left
<lb/>To wear the crown and sit upon the throne.
<lb/>One, with a hundred thousand enemies,
<lb/>How canst thou battle when exposed to all?
<lb/>Betake thee to the forest of Narwan;
<lb/>The folk will gather to thee there and thence,
<lb/>Like valiant Faridun, do thou renew
<lb/>The fight like fire.</q>
<lb/>The king of kings gave ear.
<lb/>New thoughts occurred. Upon the morrow’s morn
<lb/>He sat upon his throne, assumed the crown,
<lb/>Held an assembly with his men of lore,
<lb/>The magnates and shrewd-hearted archimages,
<lb/>And said: <q>What seemeth good to you herein?
<lb/>What precedents recall ye from the past?
<lb/>Saith Farrukhzad to me: <q>Depart and take
<lb/>Thy followers to the forest of Narwan:
<lb/>The people of Amul, are servitors,
<lb/>The people of Sari all slaves, to thee,
<lb/>And, when thy troops are many, come again
<lb/>With puissance to battle with the Brave.</q>
<lb/>Do ye approve?</q>
<lb/>They all of them exclaimed:—
<lb/><q>That is the course.</q>
<lb/>The king of kings rejoined:—
<lb/><q>It is not well. I purpose otherwise.
<lb/>Shall I desert the chieftains of Iran,
<lb/>And this great host, our country, throne, and crown
<lb/>To save myself? That were not majesty,
<lb/>Or manliness or policy. To fight
<lb/>The foe is better for me than disgrace.
<lb/>The leopard spake a saw in this regard:—
<lb/><q>Whene'er the time of stress shall come on thee
<pb n="87"/>
<lb/>Turn not in folly from thine enemy.</q>
<lb/>For just as subjects should obey, their king
<lb/>In good and ill so he must not desert them
<lb/>In their distress and go off to his treasures.</q>
<lb/>The great men blessed him, saying: <q>Crown
<lb/>and signet
<lb/>Exist for ends like these. Think what thy will
<lb/>And wishes are, and what assurances
<lb/>Thou wouldst of us.</q>
<lb/>The Shah thus answered them:—
<lb/><q>Anxiety is ruin to the heart.
<lb/>Our best course is to go to Khurasan
<lb/>Where we shall feel secure from strife with foes,
<lb/>For there we are possessed of many troops,
<lb/>And valiant paladins. The Turkish chiefs
<lb/>And Khan of Chin will come and do us homage
<lb/>While I will make the union stronger still
<lb/>By marriage with the daughter of Faghfur.
<lb/>A great host will arrive to succour us,
<lb/>The magnates of Turan and mighty men.
<lb/>There is the warden of the marches too,
<lb/>Mahwi, with horsemen, elephants, and wealth
<milestone unit="calced" n="2072"/>
<lb/>Of all kinds. He is our chief governor,
<lb/>The highest of the guardians of our coasts.
<lb/>I raised him when he was a vagabond,
<lb/>A minstrel and a braggart, giving him,
<lb/>Though worthless, name and worth, men, government,
<lb/>Lands, elephants. Base though he be and vile
<lb/>Still his advancement hath been at my court.
<lb/>Now I have heard an archmage quote this saw:—
<lb/><q>Of one whom thou hast wrongly harmed beware:
<lb/>Of one made rich by thee thy hopes are fair.</q>
<lb/>I never injured him in aught, and he
<lb/>Will ’venge me on my foe.</q>
<lb/>But Farrukhzad
<lb/>Smote his two hands together and exclaimed:
<pb n="88"/>
<lb/><q>O Shah who fearest God! put little trust
<lb/>In those of evil bent. In this regard
<lb/>There is a modern saw which runneth thus:—
<lb/><q>Howe’er on birth thou practise witchery,
<lb/>And strivest such an one from rust to free,
<lb/>Since the All-giver framed him thus to be
<lb/>To loose God’s bonds thou wilt not find a key.</q></q>
<lb/><q>O mighty, raging Lion!</q> said the Shah,
<lb/><q>To make this trial will work me no hurt.</q>
<lb/>He stayed that night and, when the morning broke,
<lb/>Those noble men set forth and left Baghdad
<lb/>For Khurasan, and took their travail lightly.
<lb/>The chieftains of Iran all sorrowful
<lb/>Accompanied their Shah, that noble man,
<lb/>And called down blessings on him, saying: <q>May time,
<lb/>And earth, ne’er lack thee.</q>
<lb/>From the host rose wails
<lb/>For grief and at the going of the king,
<lb/>And all the Iranian thanes—the warriors’ stay—
<lb/>Drew near to him with outcries and in tears,
<lb/>And said to him: <q>O Shah! we are thy slaves
<lb/>With souls and bodies filled with love for thee.
<lb/>We all will go with thee to learn how fortune
<lb/>Will sport with our king’s life, for if we lose
<lb/>Our Shah how can our hearts find joy in home,
<lb/>And country? We will quit our settlements,
<lb/>Our children, and our wealth to share thy toils.
<lb/>We care not for our lives without thy throne:
<lb/>May fortune ne’er abandon thee.</q><note>Three couplets omitted.</note>
<milestone unit="calced" n="2073"/>
<lb/>With eyes
<lb/>All tears the king of kings said to those nobles:—
<lb/><q>Be ever more intent in praising God.
<lb/>It may be I shall look on you again,
<lb/>And that our sorrows and distress will cease.




<pb n="89"/>
<lb/>Ye all are my true helpers and the heirlooms
<lb/>Left by my sires. I would not have you harmed:
<lb/>Share not mine ills then. We will mark the intent
<lb/>Of circling heaven, its progress, and to whom
<lb/>It showeth love. Resign yourself thereto:
<lb/>None can evade its secret purposes.</q>
<lb/>Then said he to the merchantmen of Chin:—
<lb/><q>Make no long tarrying here, else will the Arabs
<lb/>Convert your quest of gain to loss.</q>
<lb/>They parted
<lb/>With pain and trouble, sorrow, care, and wailing.
<lb/>So Farrukhzad, son of Hurmuzd, led forth
<lb/>The troops and called the veterans of Iran,
<lb/>And then the Shah set out with wail and woe.
<lb/>The leader led the van. Stage after stage
<lb/>He marched to Rai and tarried there for wine,
<lb/>And minstrelsy, thence went he to Gurgan,
<lb/>Like wind, and stayed one se’nnight sad or glad.
<lb/>Departing thence toward Bust he set his face
<lb/>With wrinkled cheeks and body in ill case.
</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><head>How Yazdagird wrote to Mahwi of Sur</head>
<p>
<lb/>The world-lord, resolute to go to Marv,
<lb/>Wrote to Mahwi of Sur, the governor,
<lb/>In rage and pain, in tears and hope deferred,
<lb/>And calling an experienced scribe poured forth
<lb/>His heart, and it was full. He first praised God,
<lb/>The all-wise Lord, the Fosterer, the Master
<lb/>Of circling Mars and Sol, of elephant
<lb/>And ant, at will creating out of naught,
<lb/>And needing no instructor, then proceeded:
<pb n="90"/>
<lb/><q>What hath befallen us? And gone are all
<lb/>This kingship’s hue and perfume. Rustam’s death
<lb/>Upon the battlefield and by the hand
<lb/>Of one whose name is Sa’ad, son of Wakkas,
<lb/>A landless, low-born, witless, aimless man,
<lb/>Hath straitened all the world to us through sorrow.
<lb/>Now that Sa’ad’s army is at Taisafun,
<lb/>With woods and foot-hills fronting them, array
<milestone unit="calced" n="2074"/>
<lb/>Thy host to fight with his and summon all
<lb/>Thy troops to that same end.<note>Three couplets omitted.</note> Lo! I will follow
<lb/>Behind my letter swiftly as the wind,
<lb/>And give thee what I purpose in my mind.</q><note>Two couplets omitted.</note>
</p>
</div>




<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><head>How Yazdagird wrote to the Marchlords of Tus</head>
<p>
<lb/>He wrote moreover to the folk of Tus,
<lb/>With full heart and with face like sandarac,
<lb/>First offering his praises to the Judge
<lb/><q>From whom are fortune, strength, and excellence,
<lb/>Grace, triumph, throne, and diadem of kingship.
<lb/>From foot of ant to soaring eagle’s plume,
<lb/>From elephant on land to crocodile
<lb/>In water, all are faithful, do His will,
<lb/>And draw no breath unless by His command.
<lb/>This from the world's Shah, mighty Yazdagird,
<lb/>Son<note>Reading with P.</note> of a famous king and valorous,
<lb/>Victorious leader of the Iranian host,
<lb/>Who guardeth his domain, desireth more,
<lb/>And cometh of a great, God-fearing race
<lb/>That thank their stars that they possess the crown,
<pb n="91"/>
<lb/>Have peopled earth and made crown, throne, and signet
<lb/>Resplendent, to his marchlords with their thrones
<lb/>And treasures, Grace, high-bearing, crowns and host
<lb/>At Shamiran, Ruin, and Mount Rada,
<lb/>Kalat and elsewhere. May the Fosterer
<lb/>Watch over us and keep you from the scath
<lb/>Of evil hap. In sooth the chiefs have heard,
<lb/>For it hath been an ensign in the world,
<lb/>That in regard to warfare, valour, birth,
<lb/>Our hearts are full of kindness, love, and justice.
<lb/>High birth especially constraineth us—
<lb/>The Shahs—to let our toils exceed our treasures
<lb/>On your behalf. What time Bahram Chubina,
<lb/>That malcontent, grew noted and rejected
<lb/>Our rule and diadem ye all abandoned
<lb/>Your marches, spacious cities, pleasances,
<lb/>Your parks and palaces, and in that case,
<lb/>In terror of disaster, made your homes
<milestone unit="calced" n="2075"/>
<lb/>On dale and lofty height. If God almighty
<lb/>Shall grant me strength and fortune favour us
<lb/>I will repay your good deeds lavishly,
<lb/>And pray to Him who watcheth o’er the world.
<lb/>In sooth ye must have heard of what the stars
<lb/>Have brought upon our head by these vile Snakes
<lb/>With looks like Ahriman, who lack all knowledge,
<lb/>Shame, fame, and treasure, fortune and descent,
<lb/>And fain would let the world go to the winds.
<lb/>It is the compass of the lofty sky
<lb/>That tribulation shall befall this realm
<lb/>By these vile miscreants, these Raven-heads,<note>The Persians translated “Arab” by “Zagh” (raven) and applied the expression to those hated enemies.</note>
<lb/>Devoid of sense and knowledge, fame and shame.
<lb/>These greedy men, who covet diadems,
<pb n="92"/>
<lb/>Have fixed their eyes upon this royal state,
<lb/>And Nushirwan once dreamed that this our throne
<lb/>Would lose its brilliant lustre. He beheld
<lb/>A hundred thousand Arabs—raging camels
<lb/>With bits<note>Properly the piece of wood passed through a perforation made in the nostrils of a camel to guide it by.</note> snapped—seeking how to cross the Arwand,
<lb/>And bring destruction on our fields and fells,
<lb/>Saw that both Fire and Fane of Fire would perish,
<lb/>The light of New Year end and Sada feast,
<lb/>That in Iran and Babylon dark smoke
<lb/>Would rise from tilth and crop to Saturn’s sphere,
<lb/>While on the world-king’s hall the battlements
<lb/>Would tumble to the ground.<note>See Vol. viii., p. 66.</note> The dream is now
<lb/>Fulfilled and heaven’s favour fain to quit us.
<lb/>Those that we value most will be misprized,
<lb/>The base will be set up on high by fortune,
<lb/>Ill scattered through the world, mishap apert
<lb/>And good concealed. In all the provinces
<lb/>Some tyrant, some obscene calamity,
<lb/>And signs of dark night’s coming will appear,
<lb/>Our glorious fortune be cut off from us.
<lb/>Now as our counsellors and paladins—
<lb/>Men of pure rede—advise we purpose going
<lb/>To Khurasan and to its warlike marchlords.
<lb/>Because now of the governor of Tus
<lb/>Have I led here the elephants and drums,
<lb/>And we shall see how fortune will make bonds
<lb/>Of our frail knots. I am girt up for battle
<lb/>That I may meet the Arabs face to face,
<lb/>While Farrukhzad—my very veins and skin,
<lb/>And my firm friend—is now at Altuniya,
<lb/>Intent on fight, and host confronteth host,
<lb/>While Kashmigan, that warrior’s son, hath reached
<lb/>Our court and spoken well and loyally.
<pb n="93"/>
<milestone unit="calced" n="2076"/>
<lb/>I heard what he could tell about these marches, 
<lb/>Their heights and depths, their caves, retreats, the hold
<lb/>Upon Mount Gumbadan and Jarmana,
<lb/>The fort of Lazhawardi for our stores,
<lb/>Spots such as Al, Makhzum, and waste of Gil:
<lb/>He kindly opened all his heart to me.
<lb/>My host for battle is too numerous
<lb/>To tarry long within these narrow holds.
<lb/>We have held council; all the paladins
<lb/>Attended; we debated and resolved
<lb/>To take with us crown, throne, and seal and signet,
<lb/>All garments of Kashmir and Rum and Chin,
<lb/>Such goods as we can gather from Kibchak
<lb/>And from Kirwan, all that we have in hand
<lb/>Of clothes and carpets, articles of gold,
<lb/>With gems uncut and all that most we prize,
<lb/>And provand and equipment for the future.
<lb/>Of oxen forty thousand will drag loads
<lb/>Of unthrashed corn and after these will come
<lb/>Twelve thousand asses drawing loads of dates
<lb/>For us. A trusty archimage will bring
<lb/>Pistachios, millet, and pomegranate-juice.
<lb/>Attending on the outcome they will send
<lb/>Thereafter many asses’ loads of salt,
<lb/>And add a thousand camels’ loads of millet,
<lb/>Fat from the tails of sheep and butter-skins.
<lb/>A thousand Bactrian camels will bring dates,
<lb/>Another thousand sugar, as their loads.
<lb/>Twelve thousand also will bring drums of honey.
<lb/>All these will come at one time to the holds.
<lb/>Besides all these my servants will bring in
<lb/>Some forty thousand salted carcasses,
<lb/>And of black naphtha in the next two months
<lb/>Three hundred camel-loads. An archimage
<pb n="94"/>
<lb/>With escort will arrive from Shamfran,
<lb/>And from Mount Rada while, in sight of all
<lb/>The elders and the wise, the mountain-chiefs,
<lb/>Sent by the marchlords, will convey whate’er
<lb/>Is needed to the gates and give the list
<lb/>To our own treasurer, and if the Great
<lb/>Among the folk will but restrain themselves
<lb/>They will in sooth receive no injury
<lb/>Among the valleys and the lofty hills
<lb/>From Arab or from Turkman. Help from you
<lb/>In these our strenuous times will aid us much.
<lb/>Our minister, that wise and holy man,
<lb/>Will now give orders to our treasurer
<lb/>To send five robes of Persian make to all
<milestone unit="calced" n="2077"/>
<lb/>That toil for us and, when those toils are over,
<lb/>A splendid turban of gold broidery.
<lb/>In these our present troubles each shall have
<lb/>Two score drachms from our treasures, afterwards,
<lb/>For service rendered, for each drachm three-score,
<lb/>Each worth more than ten dangs, and he will read
<lb/>This legend: <q>In the name of holy God,
<lb/>The Object of our reverence, hopes, and fears,</q>
<lb/>Upon one side. The other side will bear
<lb/>Our face and crown, the legend: <q>Through our love
<lb/>The earth becometh fruitful.</q> These have been
<lb/>Prepared for New Year’s Day, the nobles’ eyes
<lb/>Fulfilled with wealth. God’s blessing on the man
<lb/>Whose faults are few and who forgetteth not
<lb/>Our diadem.</q>
<lb/>The Shah when he had sealed
<lb/>The letter sent it to the army-chiefs.
<lb/>With this king’s missive in his hand there came
<lb/>A horseman of high fortune and high aim.
</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><head>How Yazdagird went to Tus and how Mahwi of Sur met him</head>
<p><pb n="95"/>
<lb/>Thence they conveyed the drums and came to Tus
<lb/>From Nishapur. Mahwi of Sur had news:—
<lb/><q>The Shah is on the road to Dahistan,</q>
<lb/>And went to meet him with a mighty power,
<lb/>All spearmen and in coats of mail, and when
<lb/>The Glory of the royal state appeared,
<lb/>The flag of majesty and such a host,

<lb/>Alighted from his steed forthwith and paid
<lb/>His duty to the king of kings, walked softly
<lb/>Upon the burning dust and from his eyes
<lb/>Shed tears of reverence. He kissed the ground,
<lb/>Prolonging his obeisance. All his troops
<lb/>Acclaimed the Shah and touched earth with their heads,
<lb/>While Farrukhzad enranked his powers when he
<lb/>Beheld the visage of Mahwi of Sur
<lb/>By whom his heart was joyed and whom he counselled
<lb/>At large: <q>This Shah of royal race do I
<lb/>Commit to thee to serve him, suffering not
<lb/>The blast to blow on him, and none save thee
<lb/>To earn his thanks. I must depart to Rai,
<lb/>Uncertain whether I shall see again
<lb/>The royal crown for ’gainst these Arab spearmen
<lb/>Full many such as I have died in battle.
<lb/>There was not one within the world like Rustam,
<lb/>The horseman, never hath the ear of sage
<milestone unit="calced" n="2078"/>
<lb/>Heard tell of such, yet by a Raven-head<note>See p. 91. note.</note>
<lb/>Was he cut off, so adverse was our day!
<lb/>God grant to him a place among the Just,
<lb/>And give the swarthy Ravens to our spears!</q>
<lb/>Mahwi replied: <q>O paladin! the Shah
<lb/>Is eye and soul to me. I undertake
<lb/>In thy place to defend thy king, thy Heaven.</q>
<lb/>So Farrukhzad, son of Hurmuzd, departed
<lb/>To Rai as bidden by the Shah. The sky
<lb/>Revolved awhile with matters in this stay,
<lb/>And all love passed from that malignant’s brain,
<lb/>And none dared go to battle with the Arabs
<lb/>Because the azure sky was helping them;
<lb/>The visage of the monarch of Iran
<lb/>Grew wrinkled; the foe’s deeds made strait his heart.
<lb/>Mahwi saw that the Shah was at a stay,
<lb/>And driven on by fortune helplessly,
<lb/>Ambitioned speedily the throne and changed
<lb/>In policy, in manners, and dispose,
<pb n="96"/>
<lb/>Then for a season he began to affect
<lb/>Ill health and barely showed the Shah respect.
</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><head>How Mahwi of Sur incited Bizhan to war with Yazdagird and how Yazdagird fled and hid himself in a Mill</head>
<p>
<lb/>There was a paladin, a Turk by race,
<lb/>A man of influence and named Bizhan;
<lb/>He dwelt within the coasts of Samarkand
<lb/>Where he had many kin. Ill-starred Mahwi,
<lb/>Becoming self-assertive, wrote to him:—
<lb/><q>Thou prosperous scion of the paladins!
<pb n="97"/>
<lb/>A strife hath risen that will bring thee profit:
<lb/>The Shah is of all places here at Marv
<lb/>And with no troops! His head and crown and state,
<lb/>Wealth, throne, and host, are thine if thou wilt come.
<lb/>Recall the vengeance owing to thy sires,
<lb/>And give this unjust race its just reward.</q>
<lb/>Bizhan, considering the letter, saw
<lb/>That insolent Mahwi would win the world,
<lb/>Then spake thus to his minister: <q>Thou chief
<lb/>Of upright men! what sayest thou to this?
<lb/>If I lead forth a host to aid Mahwi
<lb/>Twill be my ruin here.</q><note>Two couplets omitted.</note>
<lb/>The minister
<lb/>Replied: <q>O lion-hearted warrior!
<milestone unit="calced" n="2079"/>
<lb/>Twere shame to help Mahwi and then withdraw.
<lb/>Command Barsam to set forth with a host:
<lb/>To aid upon this scene of strife. The sage
<lb/>Will term thee daft to go and fight in person
<lb/>At the insistence of this man of Sur.</q>
<lb/>Bizhan replied: <q>'Tis well, I will not go
<lb/>Myself.</q>
<lb/>He therefore bade Barsam to lead
<lb/>Ten thousand valiant cavaliers and swordsmen
<lb/>To Marv with all the implements of war
<lb/>If haply he might take the Shah. That host
<lb/>Went like a flying pheasant from Bukhara
<lb/>To Marv within one week. One night at cock-crow
<lb/>The sound of tymbals went up from the plain.
<lb/>How could the king of kings suspect Mahwi
<lb/>Of Sur to be his enemy? Shouts rose.
<lb/>A cavalier reached Yazdagird at dawn
<lb/>To say: <q>Mahwi saith thus: <q>A host of Turks
<lb/>Hath come. What is the bidding of the Shah?
<lb/>The Khan and the Faghfur of Chin command:
<lb/>Earth is not able to support their host!</q></q>
<pb n="98"/>
<lb/>The Shah wroth donned his mail. The armies ranged.
<note>Couplet omitted.</note>
<lb/>He formed his troops to right and left, and all
<lb/>Advanced to battle. Spear in hand he held
<lb/>The centre, and the whole world was bedimmed
<lb/>With flying dust. He saw how lustily
<lb/>The Turks engaged, unsheathed his sword, and came,
<lb/>As ’twere an elephant before his troops.
<lb/>Earth Nile-wise flowed. Like thundering cloud he charged,
<lb/>But not a warrior supported him;
<lb/>All turned their backs upon that man of name,
<lb/>And left him mid the horsemen of the foe.
<lb/>The world’s king, when Mahwi withdrew, perceived
<lb/>The practice hid till then—the intent and plan
<lb/>To capture him—yet played the man in fight,
<lb/>Displaying valour, strength, and warriorship,
<lb/>Slew many at the centre, but at length
<lb/>Fled in despair, with falchion of Kabul
<lb/>In hand, pursued by many Turks. He sped
<lb/>Like lightning mid night’s gloom and spied a mill
<lb/>On the canal of Zark.<note>See LEC, p. 400.</note> Alighting there
<lb/>The world’s king lay in hiding from his foes
<lb/>Within the mill. The horsemen searched for him;
<lb/>All Zark was hue and cry. The Shah abandoned
<milestone unit="calced" n="2080"/>
<lb/>His gold-trapped steed, his mace, and scimitar
<lb/>With golden sheath. The Turks with loud shouts sought him,
<lb/>Excited by that steed and equipage.
<lb/>The Shah within the mill-house lurked in hay.
<lb/>With this false Hostel thus it ever is:
<lb/>The ascent is lofty and profound the abyss.
<lb/>With Yazdagird, while fortune slumbered not,
<lb/>A throne enskied<note>Reading with T.</note> by heaven was his lot,
<lb/>And now it was a mill! Excess of sweet
<pb n="99"/>
<lb/>Bred bane for him and, if thou art discreet,
<lb/>Affect not this world for its end is ill.
<lb/>Whiles a tame serpent to the touch it still
<lb/>At whiles will bite, and hot that bite will be.
<lb/>Why then affect this cozening hostelry
<lb/>While like a drum the signal to be gone
<lb/>Thou hearest, bidding: <q>Bind the baggage on,
<lb/>And for sole throne the grave’s floor look upon?</q>
<lb/>With mouth untasting and with tearful eyes
<lb/>The Shah abode until the sun arose,
<lb/>And then the miller oped the mill-house door.
<lb/>He bore a truss of grass upon his back.
<lb/>A low-born-man was he, by name Khusrau,
<lb/>Poor, foolish, unrespected, purposeless.
<lb/>He lived upon the profits of his mill,
<lb/>Which gave him full employment. He beheld
<lb/>A warrior, like a lofty cypress, sitting
<lb/>In dolour on the ground with kingly crown
<lb/>Upon his head and with brocade of Rum
<lb/>Bright on his breast; his eyes a stag’s, his chest
<lb/>And neck a lion’s; of beholding him
<lb/>The eye ne’er tired. He was unique in form;
<lb/>Wore golden boots; his sleeves were fringed with pearls
<lb/>And gold. Khusrau looked, stood astound, and called
<lb/>On God, then said: <q>O man of sunlike mien!
<lb/>Say in what sort thou camest to this mill?
<lb/>Why didst thou take it for thy resting-place
<lb/>Full as it is of wheat and dust and hay?
<lb/>Who art thou with such form, such Grace and looks?
<lb/>Sure, heaven never saw the like of thee!</q>
<lb/>The Shah replied: <q>I am Iranian-born,
<lb/>In flight before the army of Turan.</q>
<lb/>The miller said, abashed: <q>I have no comrade
<lb/>Save penury, but still, if barley-bread,
<pb n="100"/>
<lb/>With some poor cresses from the river-bank,
<lb/>Will serve thee I will bring them; naught have I
<lb/>Besides: a man so straitened well may wail.</q>
<lb/>Through stress of fight the Shah had rested not,
<lb/>Or eaten, for three days and so replied:—
<lb/><q>Bring what thou hast, that and the sacred twigs
<lb/>Will serve my turn.</q>
<milestone unit="calced" n="2081"/>
<lb/>The poor and lowly miller
<lb/>Brought him the cresses and the barley-bread,
<lb/>Made haste to fetch the sacred twigs and, reaching
<lb/>The toll-house<note>The toll-house was at the ford or ferry. The same word might also mean a place of worship and accordingly Mohl or rather his successor (see p. 37 note) translates:— <quote xml:lang="fra">Il se rendit au lieu où était l'oratoire et fit prévenir aussitôt le chef de Zark qu'on lui demandait le Barsom.</quote></note> on the way, crossed to the chief
<lb/>Of Zark to make request for them. Mahwi
<lb/>Had sent men on all sides to find the Shah,
<lb/>And so the chieftain asked the miller: <q>Friend!
<lb/>For whom need’st thou the sacred twigs?</q>
<lb/>Khusrau
<lb/>Replied: <q>There is a warrior at the mill,
<lb/>And seated on the hay, a cypress slim
<lb/>In height, a sun in looks, a man of Grace,
<lb/>With eyebrows arched and melancholy eyes:
<lb/>His mouth is full of sighs, his soul is sad.
<lb/>I set stale fare before him—barley-bread,
<lb/>Such as I eat myself—but he is fain
<lb/>To take the sacred twigs while muttering grace.<note>See Vol. 1., p. 80 s.v. Baj.</note>
<lb/>Thou well mayst muse at him.</q>
<lb/>The chief rejoined:—
<lb/><q>Go and inform Mahwi of Sur hereof,
<lb/>For that foul miscreant must not reveal
<lb/>His proper bent when he shall hear of this.</q><note>I.e., if subsequently he should learn that we knew and did not tell him.</note>
<lb/>Forthwith he charged a trusty man to take
<pb n="101"/>
<lb/>The miller to Mahwi who asked of him,
<lb/>Then anxious for himself: <q>For whom didst thou
<lb/>Require the sacred twigs? Tell me the truth.</q>
<lb/>The miller all a-tremble made reply:—
<lb/><q>I had been out to fetch a load and flung
<lb/>The mill-door open roughly, when know this:
<lb/>The sun was in mine eyes, but his are like
<lb/>Those of a startled fawn; his locks are dark
<lb/>As the third watch of night; his breath suggests
<lb/>Musk, and his face embellisheth his crown.
<lb/>One that hath never seen the Grace of God
<lb/>Should take the mill-house key. His diadem
<lb/>Is full of uncut jewels, and his breast
<lb/>Bright with brocade of Rum. The mill hath grown
<lb/>As ’twere a sun through him, and yet his food
<lb/>Is barley-bread, his seat upon the hay!
<lb/><q>Spring,</q> thou wouldst say, <q>in Paradise is he:
<lb/>No thane e’er set so tall a cypress-tree.</q></q>
</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10"><head>How Mahwi of Sur sent the Miller to kill Yazdagird, and how the Archimages counselled Mahwi to forbear</head>
<p>
<lb/>Now when Mahwi had taken thought he knew:
<lb/><q>Tis none but Yazdagird!</q> and bade the miller:
<lb/><q>Haste and cut off his head forthwith or I
<milestone unit="calced" n="2082"/>
<lb/>Will cut thine own off presently and leave
<lb/>None of thy stock alive.</q>
<lb/>The chiefs, the nobles,
<lb/>And mighty men heard this and all the assembly
<lb/>Were filled with wrath at him; their tongues were charged
<pb n="102"/>
<lb/>With words, their eyes with tears. An archimage,
<lb/>By name Radwi, whose mind wore wisdom’s bridle,
<lb/>Said to Mahwi: <q>O thou malignant one!
<lb/>Why hath the Div confused thine eyes? This know:
<lb/>The royal and prophetic offices
<lb/>Are two gems set within one finger-ring.
<lb/>To break one is to trample life and wisdom
<lb/>Beneath thy feet. Reflect upon thy words,
<lb/>And then forbear. Be not the Maker’s foe.
<lb/>First will disaster come on thee herefrom,
<lb/>Then thou wilt leave a seed-plot for thy child,
<lb/>With fruit of colocynth and leafage blood.
<lb/>Ere long thou wilt behold thy head abased;
<lb/>Thy villainy will be exposed; thy sons
<lb/>Will reap what thou hast sown. This deed of thine
<lb/>Will wreck the Faith of God, and crown and throne
<lb/>Will curse thee.</q>
<lb/>Then a devotee devout,
<lb/>Who never put his hand forth to injustice,
<lb/>By name Hurmuzd, son of Kharrad, a man
<lb/>Who rested in the Faith, said to Mahwi:
<lb/><q>O thou oppressor! quit not thus the way
<lb/>Of holy God. I see thy heart and sense
<lb/>Bedimmed. We see thy breast a tomb. Though strong
<lb/>Thou hast no brain; thy mind is weak; thou seekest
<lb/>The smoke and not the fire. I see that thou
<lb/>Wouldst have the malediction of the world,
<lb/>And, when thou quit'st it, travail, smart, and anguish.
<lb/>Now will thy lifetime prove a wretched one,
<lb/>And fire thy dwelling-place when thou departest.</q>
<lb/>He sat. Shahran rose and addressed Mahwi:
<lb/><q>Why this audacity? Thou hast opposed
<lb/>The king of kings and cottoned with the Khan
<lb/>And the Faghfur. Full many of this race
<lb/>Have proved of no account yet men ne’er hasted
<pb n="103"/>
<lb/>To slay them. Shed not, as thou art a slave,
<lb/>The blood of Shahs because thou wilt be cursed
<lb/>Till Doomsday.</q>
<lb/>This he said, and sat down weeping
<lb/>In anguish with heart full and eyes all gall.
<lb/>Then Mihr-i-Nush stood forth in deep distress,
<lb/>With lamentation, and addressed Mahwi:
<lb/><q>O evil man of evil race, who art
<lb/>Not well advised or just! a crocodile
<lb/>Respecteth royal blood, a leopard finding
<lb/>A slain king doth not rend him. O thou worse
<lb/>In love and instinct than the beasts of prey!
<lb/>Thou covetest the Shah’s crown! When Jamshid
<lb/>Was slaughtered by Zahhak did that affect
<milestone unit="calced" n="2083"/>
<lb/>Heaven’s will? Nay, when Zahhak had won the earth
<lb/>Abtin appeared, the glorious Faridun
<lb/>Was born, the fashion of the world was changed,
<lb/>And thou hast heard what tyrannous Zahhak
<lb/>.Brought on himself as sequel of his crimes,
<lb/>For though he lived above a thousand years
<lb/>Still in the end the avenger came to him.
<lb/>Then, secondly, when Tur, the exalted one,
<lb/>Afflicted by his longing for Iran,
<lb/>Slew in his folly virtuous Iraj,
<lb/>On whom the very dust looked pityingly,
<lb/>Dispatched him<note>His head, according to the story. See Vol. i., p. 202.</note> to the hero Faridun,
<lb/>And gave the world to sorrow, Minuchihr,
<lb/>One of the race, appeared and undid all
<lb/>Those bonds. When, thirdly, princely Siyawush
<lb/>Went forth to war, albeit reluctantly,
<lb/>Afrasiyab, inspired by Garsiwaz,
<lb/>Washed shame and honour from his mind and wits,
<lb/>And slew the youthful and right royal prince,
<lb/>So that the world became his enemy.
<lb/>Sprung from that prince the world-lord Kai Khusrau
<pb n="104"/>
<lb/>Came and filled all the world with hubbub, clave
<lb/>Asunder with his scimitar his grandsire,<note>Afrasiyab, whose daughter Farangis married Siyawush.</note>
<lb/>And frayed all those that else had sought revenge.
<lb/>The fourth count is the feud against Arjasp,
<lb/>The slayer of Lohrasp. Asfandiyar
<lb/>Went forth to fight with him and took swift wreak.
<lb/>Fifth, is the vengeance ta’en for Shah Hurmuzd.
<lb/>Khusrau Parviz, whenas he felt confirmed
<lb/>In heart and power, dealt in the way we know
<lb/>Both with Bandwi and Gustaham. The sky,
<lb/>Which then revolved, revolveth still.<note>I.e., history repeats itself.</note> Forgetting
<lb/>What they had done for him, when his sire’s blood
<lb/>And love and family appealed to him,
<lb/>He in his day of strength abated theirs.<note>Vol. viii., pp. 354, 358.</note>
<lb/>One may not scorn the occasion of revenge,
<lb/>For such a time will quickly come to thee,
<lb/>And thou wilt suffer for thine evil thoughts,
<lb/>Thy son will reap what thou hast sown, and fate
<lb/>Will not rest long from vengeance; so refrain
<lb/>From all this treasure-hoard, this heritage
<lb/>Of crown and precious things. Thou art revolting
<lb/>Because the Div enjoineth, and abjuring
<lb/>The way of God. The Div, as thou wilt learn,
<lb/>Is tempting thee with things not for thine honour.
<lb/>Burn not thy soul and body in Hell-fire;
<lb/>Dim not this world-illuming crown but gather
<lb/>Thy scattered troops; recant what thou hast said;
<lb/>Go ask the Shah to pardon thee and when
<lb/>Thou seest him renew thy fealty.
<milestone unit="calced" n="2084"/> 
<lb/>From there prepare to battle with the foe:
<lb/>Be instant both in counsel and excuse,
<lb/>For not to hearken to the words of sages
<lb/>Will mark thee out as evil in both worlds.
<lb/>Men bring to naught things done a day too late.
<pb n="105"/>
<lb/>Wilt thou treat Yazdagird, the king of kings,
<lb/>Worse than malignant Turks, for in the fray
<lb/>He is a lion, on the throne a Shah
<lb/>As bright as sun and moon, a memory
<lb/>Of the Sassanians? None is girdle-girt
<lb/>Like him. From sire to sire his ancestors
<lb/>Were mighty men and compassers of wisdom
<lb/>From Nushirwan, the Shah, back to Ardshir,
<lb/>While, seventh backward from Ardshir, Sasan,
<lb/>The world-lord, had the crown,<note>De jure not de facto. The first Sasan, here referred to, was the son of Dara and after his father’s overthrow by Alexander took refuge in obscurity. Several generations later a descendant of his of the same name became the father of Ardshir Papakan—the founder of the Sassanian Dynasty. The Sassanians, naturally sought to connect themselves with the old line of the Persian monarchy, with the Achaemenids in history and with the Kayanians in legend. Cf. Vol. vi., p. 199.</note> for God entrusted
<lb/>To him the Kaian crown, and all the kings
<lb/>Were of that glorious race. Now many a man
<lb/>Hath been thy better, but they ne’er conceived
<lb/>Designs like these. As for Bahram Chubina,
<lb/>Three hundred thousand skillful cavaliers
<lb/>—On barded steeds fled at one shaft of his,<note>See Vol. viii., p. 126.</note>
<lb/>And left the field of fight to him; but when
<lb/>His heart grew weary of the race of Shahs
<lb/>The head of his resplendent fortune fell.
<lb/>So Faridun, who sought the throne of kings
<lb/>Unworthily and bathed his hands in blood,
<lb/>Was in like manner miserably slain:
<lb/>This age endureth not such mockeries.
<lb/>Fear Him, the Lord, the Maker of the world,
<lb/>For He created throne and crown and signet.
<lb/>Defame not thine own person wantonly
<lb/>Because ere long such things will rise against thee.
<lb/>Know that whoever speaketh not the truth
<lb/>To thee is thy soul’s foe. Now thou art sick
<lb/>While I am as the leech, a leech that waileth,
<pb n="106"/>
<lb/>And sheddeth drops of blood. Thou art thyself
<lb/>Less than the slave of slaves. Be not ambitious
<lb/>In thy heart’s thoughts. Leave strife to holy God,
<lb/>And seek in honour’s way the throne of greatness.</q>
<lb/>The shepherd-born<note>I.e., Mahwi. Cf. p. 87.</note> had set his heart upon
<lb/>The throne: the archimages’ rede was hard.
<lb/>So hath it ever been; 'tis no new thing:
<lb/>The flouts of fortune are past reckoning,
<lb/>Exalting to the sky above this one,
<lb/>And making that vile, wretched, and undone,
<lb/>Not leagued with that, on war with this not bent,
<lb/>But void of wit, shame, Faith, and precedent.
<lb/>The archimages all, till the world gloomed and moon
<lb/>Succeeded sun, warned that vindictive man,
<lb/>Who was not one hair better for their talk,
<lb/>And said when night came: <q>Ye must leave me now
<milestone unit="calced" n="2085"/>
<lb/>O sages! I will ponder this to-night,
<lb/>And take all kinds of wisdom to my breast.
<lb/>We will call twenty wise men from the host
<lb/>That we may need not to deplore this ill.</q>
<lb/>The prudent archimages went their ways,
<lb/>The men of war arrived. Mahwi held session
<lb/>With his confederates<note>Reading with P.</note> and said: <q>What think ye
<lb/>Herein? If Yazdagird remain alive,
<lb/>Troops will collect to him from every side;
<lb/>My secret purposes have been exposed,
<lb/>And all, both great and small, have heard thereof!
<lb/>My life will end through his hostility,
<lb/>And neither folk nor field and fell be left.</q>
<lb/>A wise man said: <q>Thou shouldest not have acted
<lb/>At first so. If the monarch of Iran
<lb/>Be ill-disposed toward thee then past doubt
<lb/>Ill will befall thee from him, yet 'tis ill
<lb/>To shed his blood for then God will avenge him.
<lb/>To left and right are cares and pains of all kinds:
<pb n="107"/>
<lb/>Consider how thou need'st must act herein.</q>
<lb/>Mahwi’s son said to him: <q>Well counselled sire!
<lb/>Since thou hast made the Shah thine enemy
<lb/>Be rid of him; troops from Machin and Chin
<lb/>Will come to him and earth grow strait for us.
<lb/>Hold this no trifle. Since thou hast prevailed
<lb/>Tempt not the maws of lions. Thou and all
<lb/>Thy host will be uprooted from the world
<lb/>If standard-wise the Shah’s skirt be unfurled.</q>
</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11"><head>How Yazdagird was slain by Khusrau, the Miller</head>
<p>
<lb/>Thereat the shameless, infamous Mahwi
<lb/>Turned fiercely to the miller, saying: <q>Up!
<lb/>Take cavaliers and shed my foeman’s blood.</q>
<lb/>The miller, hearing, knew not what to do,
<lb/>But when at night the moon assumed her throne
<lb/>Departed mill-ward to the Shah and when
<lb/>He left the court-gate of Mahwi his eyes
<lb/>Were charged with tear-drops and his heart was full.
<lb/>Forthwith Mahwi dispatched some cavaliers
<lb/>To follow swift as smoke, instructing them:—
<lb/><q>See that ye sully not the crown and earrings,
<lb/>The signet and the royal robes with blood,
<lb/>And strip the Shah when lifeless.</q>
<pb n="108"/>
<lb/>With his eyes
<lb/>All tearful and cheeks yellow as the sun
<lb/>The miller went, exclaiming: <q>Judge almighty,
<lb/>Who art above the processes of time!
<lb/><milestone unit="calced" n="2086"/>
<lb/>Wring presently his heart and soul for this
<lb/>Abhorred behest!</q>
<lb/>With heart all shame and qualm,
<lb/>With wetted cheeks and tongue all charged with dust,
<lb/>He reached the Shah and drawing nigh with caution,
<lb/>As one would speak a secret in the ear,
<lb/>Stabbed with a dirk his middle. At the blow
<lb/>The Shah cried: <q>Ah!</q> Then tumbled head and crown,
<lb/>And barley-bread before him, to the dust!
<lb/>He that abideth when he might depart
<lb/>From this world hath no wisdom in his heart,
<lb/>And wisdom is not in the turning sky,
<lb/>Whose love is as its stress and enmity.
<lb/>Tis well to look not on the world and so
<lb/>From these its doings love and wrath not know.
<lb/>The planets weary of their fosterlings,
<lb/>And guiltless folk like Yazdagird are slain;
<lb/>None else hath perished thus of all the kings,
<lb/>Nor of his host a plier of the rein.
<note>Reading the couplet that follows here two couplets lower.</note> Those emissaries,
<note>Thus, if we interpret the passage by strict Zoroastrian principles, polluting one of the elements and adding sacrilege to regicide, but cf. Vol. iv., p. 129.</note>
<note>Couplet omitted.</note> When they arose, all framed their tongues to curse:—
<lb/><q>Oh! may Mahwi himself fare, prostrate thus,
<lb/>All gory on earth’s face.</q>
<lb/>They told Mahwi:—
<lb/><q>The exalted Shah hath passed away from throne,
<lb/>From battle and delights,</q> and he commanded
<lb/>To take, when it was night, the monarch’s corpse,
<lb/>And fling it in the stream. The miller took
<lb/>The body of the Shah forth from the mill,
<pb n="109"/>
<lb/>And flung it (mark the horror!) in the water,
<lb/>And there it floated with a bobbing head!
<lb/>When it was day and people went abroad
<lb/>Two men of worship visited the spot.
<lb/>One of these men austere and sober reached
<lb/>The river-bank and, when he saw the corpse
<lb/>All naked in the water, hurried back
<lb/>In consternation to the monastery,
<lb/>And told the other monks what he had seen:—
<lb/><q>The Shah, the master of the world, is drowned,
<lb/>And naked in the water-way of Zark!</q>
<lb/>Then many of those holy men—the chief
<lb/>And others of all ranks—set forth. A cry
<milestone unit="calced" n="2087"/>
<lb/>Of anguish rose from them: <q>O noble man,
<lb/>And royal crown-possessor! none e’er saw
<lb/>The wearer of it in such plight as this,
<lb/>Or ever heard before the time of Christ
<lb/>A case like this king’s through his wicked slave,
<lb/>This misbegotten dog, this reprobate,
<lb/>Who fawned upon his master till ill came;
<lb/>Mahwi’s just portion is to be accursed.
<lb/>Woe for the head and crown, the height and mien!
<lb/>Woe for the breast and arms, the hands and mace!
<lb/>Woe for the last descendant of Ardshir!
<lb/>Woe for that cavalier so young and goodly!
<lb/>Strong wast thou; thou hadst wisdom in thy soul,
<lb/>And thou hast gone to bear the news hereof
<lb/>To Nushirwan that, though thy face was moonlike,
<lb/>And though thou wast a king and soughtest crowns,
<lb/>Yet in the mill they pierced thy liverstead,
<lb/>And flung thy naked body in the stream!</q>



<note>Three couplets omitted.</note> 
<lb/>Four of the monks went stripped into the water,
<lb/>Seized the bare body of the youthful king,
<pb n="110"/>
<lb/>That grandson of the world-lord Nushirwan,
<lb/>And drew it to the bank while young and old
<lb/>Lamented greatly. They prepared for him
<lb/>Within the garth a charnel-house and raised
<lb/>Its summit to the clouds. They sealed his wound
<lb/>With gum, with pitch, with camphor, and with musk,
<lb/>And then arrayed him in brocade of gold,
<lb/>With fine Egyptian linen underneath,
<lb/>And dark-blue Russian cloth o’er all. They decked
<lb/>His place of rest with wine and gum and camphor,
<lb/>With musk and with rose-water. 
<lb/>When the form
<lb/>Was hidden of that noble Cypress-tree
<lb/>What said that honoured thane of Marv? <q>In secret
<lb/>A guerdon waiteth him that after travail
<lb/>Departeth with good conscience from the world.</q>
<lb/>Another said: <q>Though man may laugh, yet know
<lb/>That he is of the sufferers, for he
<lb/>Will find the falseness of the turning sky,
<lb/>Which will reveal to him both rise and fall.</q>
<lb/>Another said: <q>Call not him one of wit
<lb/>That serveth his own form with princes’ blood,
<lb/>And seeketh wealth, despite of infamy,
<lb/>With soul unfearful of an evil end.</q>
<lb/>Another said: <q>Since the Shah’s lips are closed
<lb/>I see not crown or royal seat or signet,
<lb/>Or courtiers or a realm or diadem,
<lb/>Or throne or helmet, and if these possess
<lb/>No moment in themselves why this expense
<lb/>Of toil and time?</q>
<milestone unit="calced" n="2088"/> 
<lb/>Another said: <q>Thy good report, I see,
<lb/>Will win thee worthy praise. Thou in the garth
<lb/>Of Paradise didst set a cypress: now
<lb/>Thy soul beholdeth it.</q>
<lb/>Another said: <q>God took thy soul and gave
<lb/>Thy body to the care of the devout.
<pb n="111"/>
<lb/>Hereby thy soul is profited, hereby
<lb/>Will harm betide the foe. The Shah hath now
<lb/>His work in Paradise; his foeman’s soul
<lb/>Is on the road to Hell.</q>
<lb/>Another said: <q>Wise, knowledge-loving Shah sprung from Ardshir!
<lb/>Thou reapest now the crop that thou didst sow:
<lb/>The lamp of sovereignty is still alight.</q>
<lb/>Another said: <q>Though thou'rt asleep, young king!
<lb/>Thy spirit is awake. Thy lips are mute,
<lb/>And with full many a groan thy spirit passed
<lb/>And left thy body free. Thy work is done:
<lb/>Thy soul is busy now. Thy foeman’s head
<lb/>Is on the stake. Although thy tongue is tied
<lb/>Thy spirit speaketh, and thy soul is purged
<lb/>Although thy form is pierced, while if thy hand
<lb/>Have dropped the reins thy spirit still will wield
<lb/>The spear in battle.</q>
<lb/>Said another one: <q>O famous warrior! thou hast departed
<lb/>With thine own works as guide. Thy royal seat
<lb/>Is now in Paradise; this earth of bale
<lb/>Is now another’s share.</q>
<lb/>Another said: <q>The man that slew
<lb/>One such as thee will look upon harsh days anon.</q>
<lb/>The prelate said: <q>Thy slaves are we and laud thy holy soul.
<lb/>Be this, thy charnel, as a garth all tulips,
<lb/>This bier thine upland and thy plain of joy.</q>
<lb/>They spake, took up the bier and carried it
<lb/>From waste to mausoleum. Thither came
<lb/>The hapless Shah, crown, throne, and casque at end.
<lb/>O man of many years, whose words still run!
<lb/>Turn from the path of greed, break off thy strain.
<lb/>What shall we say hereof? Was justice done,
<pb n="112"/>

<lb/>Or vengeance by the seven planets ta’en,
<lb/>On Yazdagird? The sage, if unresolved
<lb/>Upon the point, could make me no reply,
<lb/>Or if he spake 'twould be in words involved
<lb/>That keep the answer still a mystery.
<lb/>If thou hast means, good man! indulge thy heart;
<lb/>Trust not to what the morrow promiseth,
<lb/>Because the world and thou perforce must part,
<lb/>And time accounteth for thine every breath;
<lb/>Thou shouldest sow not any save good seed
<lb/>In what remaineth of thy mortal strife;
<lb/>Control the door of appetite and greed;
<lb/>He that provided will provide through life,
<lb/>And life itself will but produce for thee
<lb/>Fair fame and happiness, good friend! Then still
<milestone unit="calced" n="2089"/> 
<lb/>With all thy might eschew iniquity,
<lb/>For from a wise man should proceed no ill.
<lb/>Bring wine; our day is nearly o’er and hence
<lb/>We must away, for what hath been will be.
<lb/>Had I incomings balancing expense
<lb/>Then time would be a brother unto me.
<lb/>The hail this year like death on me hath come,
<lb/>Though death itself were better than the hail,
<lb/>And heaven’s lofty, far-extending dome
<lb/>Hath caused my fuel, wheat, and sheep to fail.
</p>

</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12"><head>How Mahwi of Sur was informed of the Obsequies<note><gloss>Slaying</gloss> in the text.</note> of Yazdagird and ascended the Throne</head>
<p>
<lb/>One came and told Mahwi of Sur: <q>The world-lord
<lb/>Is hidden in the dust. The prelates, priests,
<pb n="113"/>
<lb/>And monks of Rum—all those of life austere,
<lb/>Both young and old, throughout that march and land—
<lb/>Went wailing, took his body from the stream,
<lb/>And made for him within the garth a charnel—
<lb/>A great one, higher than the mountain-slopes.</q><note>Reading with P.</note>
<lb/>Mahwi, that luckless wretch, exclaimed: <q>Iran
<lb/>Had ne'er before affinity with Rum.</q>
<lb/>He sent and slew the builders of that charnel,
<lb/>With those that mourned, and gave that march to spoil,
<lb/>Such was his will and worth! Thereafter he
<lb/>Made search throughout the world and found not one
<lb/>Of that great stock. He had a crown and signet,
<lb/>The Shah's erewhile, and to that shepherd-born
<lb/>The throne appealed. He called his intimates,
<lb/>Announced the purpose that he had at heart,
<lb/>And told his minister: <q>Experienced man!
<lb/>The day of strife and battle is upon us.
<lb/>I have no treasure, fame or lineage,
<lb/>And may but give my head up to the winds.
<lb/>The name that is upon my signet-ring
<lb/>Is Yazdagird: my scimitar hath failed
<lb/>To make men yield to me. Throughout Iran
<lb/>Men are his slaves although his kin is scattered.
<lb/>The sages do not hail me as the Shah,
<lb/>The soldiers do not recognise my seal.
<lb/>My machinations tended otherwise.
<lb/>Oh! wherefore did I shed the world-king's blood?
<lb/>All night am I sore-troubled in my thoughts:
<lb/>The World-lord knoweth how it is with me.</q>
<milestone unit="calced" n="2090"/>
<lb/>The counsellor replied: <q>The thing is done,
<lb/>And common talk. Act for thine own behoof,

<lb/>For thou hast burst thy belt. The Shah is dust
<lb/>Within the charnel; dust hath healed his soul.
<pb n="114"/>
<lb/>Call round thee all the world-experienced men,
<lb/>And set thy tongue to words of pleasantness.
<lb/>Say thus: 'The Shah gave me the crown and signet
<lb/>As emblems of authority, perceiving
<lb/>The coming of an army from the Turks,
<lb/>Called me at dead of night, and said: <q>When bruit
<lb/>Of war ariseth who can say which side
<lb/>The dust will be, so take this crown and ring,
<lb/>For they may help thee on the day of battle.
<lb/>I have one daughter only left to me:
<lb/>In truth she is in hiding from the Arabs.
<lb/>Hereafter yield not to the foe my throne,
<lb/>And by these tokens walk thou in my steps.</q>
<lb/>I have then from the Shah as legacy
<lb/>This crown and in accord to his behest
<lb/>Am sitting on the throne.' By this device
<lb/>Give thou thine acts a gloss for who will know
<lb/>The truth from falsehood?</q> <q>Good!</q> exclaimed Mahwi,
<lb/><q>Thou art a minister—a peerless one!</q>
<lb/>He summoned all the captains of the host,
<lb/>And spake at large to them to that effect.
<lb/>They knew: <q>It is not true, and well it were
<lb/>To cut his head off for his shamelessness.</q>
<lb/>A paladin observed: <q>Tis thy concern
<lb/>If what thou sayest be the truth or not.</q>
<lb/>He heard and sat him down upon the throne,
<lb/>By his deceit gat hold of Khurasan,
<lb/>Distributed the earth among his chiefs,
<lb/>And said: <q>I am the world's king with the signet.</q>
<lb/>He called his kin and said the same at large;
<lb/>He took the whole earth as it were a gift;
<lb/>The stars were in amaze at him. He chose
<lb/>The vicious as accorded to his nature,
<lb/>Debased the sages and made everywhere
<lb/>Chiefs of the bad. The head of right was humbled,
<pb n="115"/>
<lb/>And knavery on all sides manifest.
<lb/>He gave his elder son Balkh and Harat,
<lb/>And sent troops to each quarter. As his host
<lb/>And treasures grew the heart of that ingrate
<lb/>Was gratified. He gave his troops rewards
<lb/>And put them in good case; he filled the heads
<lb/>Of his own kith and kin with vapourings.
<lb/>Then with his troops and valiant warriors,
<lb/>Preceded by the scouts and Garsiyun—
<lb/>A veteran chief—they marched upon Bukhara,
<lb/>Intent on war, for <q>Chach and Samarkand
<lb/>Are ours,</q> Mahwi said, <q>and they must be made
<lb/>The captives of this crown and seal, for so
<milestone unit="calced" n="2091"/>
<lb/>Did Yazdagird, king of the world, command—
<lb/>Chief of the planets seven. With the sword
<lb/>Will I take vengeance on Bizhan by whom
<lb/>The fortune of earth's king was turned to gloom.</q>
</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13"><head>How Bizhan, hearing of the Slaying of Yazdagird and of Mahwi of Sur's Accession to the Throne, led forth the Host to fight with him</head>
<p>
<lb/>In time news reached Bizhan: <q>Mahwi hath seized
<lb/>The throne of might and everywhere imposes
<lb/>His seal and signet; earth accepts him,
<lb/>And now with warlike troops his face is turned
<lb/>Toward the Jihun for battle.</q>
<lb/><q>Who bestowed
<lb/>The signet on him?</q> asked Bizhan, and one
<lb/>Acquainted him with all: <q>When thou didst reach
<lb/>The desert of Farab, and fortune's lips
<lb/>Were closed to good and ill, there parted hence



<pb n="116"/>
<lb/>To him a force of haughty cavaliers
<lb/>In quest of fame, for he had said: 'If thou
<lb/>Wilt send me troops I will dispatch to thee
<lb/>By privy pact the crown of king of kings
<lb/>With golden throne and signet. In the world
<lb/>The sovereignty is fitly thine.' Thy troops
<lb/>Went hence in haste and found the Shah at Marv.
<lb/>They compassed him about. The Iranians fled.
<lb/>When that wise king was left alone he feared
<lb/>That ill might come upon him from the host.
<lb/>There was a certain mill upon the ford,
<lb/>And thither went the Shah, a sun in Grace.
<lb/>Mahwi of Sur heard of him, sent and slew him,
<lb/>And through the royal signet gained the world
<lb/>When he had slain his master. Now the more part
<lb/>Of praise and blame in this affair is thine,
<lb/>Thine were the valiant horsemen and the strife.</q>
</p><p>

<lb/>Barsam said thus: <q>O king! what time<note>Reading with P.</note> I took
<lb/>A mounted force from Chach<note>Couplet omitted.</note> Mahwi had said
<lb/>To thee: 'The golden throne of Yazdagird,
<lb/>His armlets set with gems, his crown withal
<lb/>And treasure, will I send to Balkh. The throne
<lb/>And crown within the world must needs be thine.'
<lb/>I fought three days at Marv. When on the fourth
<lb/>The world's light shone I battled furiously,
<lb/>For I was pressed. Tyrannical Mahwi
<lb/>Displayed his back. 'The Iranian king of kings,
<lb/>Abandoned, like a furious lion charged
<milestone unit="calced" n="2092"/>
<lb/>My troops and slaughtered many of my chiefs,
<lb/>But, when he had no comrades left, he too
<lb/>Displayed his back; but how that master-slayer,
<lb/>That faithless slave, put him to death I know not.
<lb/>Thus with no toil Mahwi obtained and used
<lb/>His master's treasures. Then the miscreant,
<lb/>Becoming dazed by so much wealth, appeared,
<pb n="117"/>
<lb/>Thou mightest say, as if he ne'er had seen me!
<lb/>Although my troops remained two months at Marv
<lb/>He gave us no kind look but put to death,
<lb/>And privily, his lord, so great a king,
<lb/>The lustre of the world, a cavalier
<lb/>That 'raiseth o'er the orbit of the moon
<lb/>His head amidst the host' thou wouldst have said.
<lb/>No Turk encountered and escaped his mace:
<lb/>He broke our nobles' hearts. I have not seen
<lb/>Such breastplate, hand, and mace. Mahwi thus furnished
<lb/>Seized on the realm in this unholy wise.
<lb/>Now that the foe in arms invades thee
<lb/>Thou and thine army must be up and doing.
<lb/>Let not weeds blossom in the royal garden
<lb/>Or it will be forgotten.</q>



<lb/>Hearing this,
<lb/>Bizhan raged much at having helped to dim
<lb/>The fortune of the Shah, then bade assemble
<lb/>His host of Turks, his horsemen of the day
<lb/>Of battle, sped forth from Kachar Bashi,
<lb/>And lost no time upon the road. Whenas
<lb/>He drew anear Bukhara all the waste
<lb/>Was covered with his troops to whom he said:—
<lb/><q>Haste not and let Mahwi be first to lead
<lb/>His host across the water<note>The Oxus.</note> to contend
<lb/>With me. Perchance on him I may avenge
<lb/>The Shah.</q>
<lb/>He asked thereafter: <q>Did the king
<lb/>Leave no availful child? Had he no brother?
<lb/>In the default of sons had he no daughter,
<lb/>Whom we might carry with us and assist,
<lb/>And take full satisfaction of Mahwi?</q>
<lb/>Barsam replied: <q>My lord! this race's day
<lb/>Is passed; the Arabs hold those provinces;

<pb n="118"/>
<lb/>No Shah is left or worshipper of Fire.</q>
<lb/>Bizhan, on hearing this, resumed his march,
<lb/>Astound at this world's doings. Scouts announced:—
<lb/><q>A host hath come and campeth at Baigand.
<lb/>They crossed in boats, their dust obscured the sun.</q>
<lb/>Bizhan, the chief, led on his troops to war,
<lb/>And when Mahwi of Sur beheld them thou
<milestone unit="calced" n="2093"/>
<lb/>Hadst said: 'His soul took flight.' He was in dudgeon
<lb/>At all those breastplates, helmets, shields of Chin,
<lb/>At all those maces, spears, and battle-axes
<lb/>Of Chach. The air grew dark and earth was lost
<lb/>To sight therein as he arrayed his host.
</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14"><head>How Mahwi of Sur was taken and slain by Order of Bizhan</head>
<p>
<lb/>Bizhan, when he had drawn up his array,
<lb/>Prepared an ambush for the Iranians;
<lb/>Mahwi knew of it and with loud exclaims
<lb/>Departed from among his troops. Bizhan
<lb/>Looked forth, beheld the flag, and knew: <q>Mahwi
<lb/>Is minded to take flight,</q> and bade Barsam:—
<lb/><q>Lead from the central host what troops thou hast,
<lb/>And draw toward one side; we must not let
<lb/>Mahwi decline the battle and haste thus
<lb/>Jihun-wards. Speed and keep him well in sight,
<lb/>For we must deal with him in other wise.</q>
<lb/>Barsam of Chin observed the flag and drew
<lb/>His troops apart until with frowning face,
<lb/>And malisons upon his lips, he reached
<lb/>The desert of Farab, there found Mahwi,
<pb n="119"/>
<lb/>And, with his weight upon the stirrups, charged;
<lb/>Then, closing face to face, he plied his sword,
<lb/>Displaying valour, seized his foeman’s belt,
<lb/>Unseated him and dashed him to the ground,
<lb/>Alighted, bound his hands, and then remounting
<lb/>Drove him along in front. With that came up
<lb/>Barsam’s own comrades, and the bruit of him
<lb/>Filled all the plain. They said: <q>O chief! Mahwi
<lb/>Should be beheaded on the way.</q>
<lb/>He answered:—
<lb/><q>Not so; Bizhan as yet is not informed
<lb/>About the capture.</q>
<lb/>Presently Bizhan
<lb/>Gat news: <q>That ill-conditioned slave is taken,</q>
<lb/>Heard and grew glad of heart. He hugged himself,
<lb/>And thus released from care roared lion-like.
<lb/>Then many valiant Turks came and discussed
<lb/>The fashion of the slaying of Mahwi.
<lb/>All that they recognised as of his court
<lb/>They put to death—a countless multitude.
<lb/>They looted all the baggage and dragged off
<lb/>Mahwi stripped bare of all. The guilty wretch
<lb/>Lost all his wits when he beheld Bizhan,
<milestone unit="calced" n="2094"/>
<lb/>Was as a soulless body with affright,
<lb/>And strewed upon his head the unstable sand.
<lb/>Bizhan said: <q>O thou miscreant! may none have
<lb/>A slave like thee! Why didst thou put to death
<lb/>That righteous Shah, the lord of victory
<lb/>And throne, and by ancestral right both Shah
<lb/>And king, the memory of Nushirwan?</q>
<lb/>Mahwi made answer thus: <q>The evil-doer
<lb/>Can look for naught but slaying and reproach.
<lb/>Now smite my neck for wrong done and fling down
<lb/>My head in presence of this company.</q>
<lb/>The other gave reply: <q>I will so act
<lb/>That I shall banish vengeance from my heart,</q>
<pb n="120"/>
<lb/>Struck off Mahwi’s hand with the scimitar,
<lb/>And said: <q>This hand hath not a peer in crime.</q>
<lb/>The hand thus lopped, he said: <q>Cut off his feet
<lb/>That he may not escape,</q> and further bade:—
<lb/><q>Cut off his nose and ears, let him be placed
<lb/>Upon a horse out on the burning sand
<lb/>Until he sleepeth in his shame.</q>
<lb/>They bound him
<lb/>From head to foot with cords, the clarions sounded,
<lb/>A herald went the circuit of the host,
<lb/>And, as he passed the entry of the tents,
<lb/>Made proclamation: <q>Slaves that slay your masters!
<lb/>Indulge no foolish thoughts, and may all those
<lb/>Without compunction for a monarch’s life
<lb/>Be as Mahwi and never see the throne.</q>
<lb/>There was a prince, by name Guraz, at once
<lb/>The glory and the pleasure of Mahwi.
<lb/>He was the governor of Marv what time
<lb/>Mahwi died wretchedly. As eldest son
<lb/>He was his father’s lustre, who had made
<lb/>A crown of gold for him. When fortune lowered
<lb/>Upon Mahwi the horsemen rode to Marv
<lb/>From all sides. Tumult spread. The war-cry rose,
<lb/>And strife and turmoil filled the land. Guraz
<lb/>Was slain amid those dark doings, and the day
<lb/>Of all his race was done. He had three sons
<lb/>Among his troops, three favourite sons possessed
<lb/>Of crown and throne. A lofty pyre was kindled,
<lb/>And he and his three sons were burned thereon.
<lb/>None of the seed remained or if some did
<lb/>Men harried them. The chieftains cursed that race,
<lb/>All vengeful for the slaughter of the Shah:—
<lb/><q>May it be cursed and may there never fail
<lb/>A man to curse it as it hath deserved.</q>
<lb/>Bizhan, the Turk, too was an evil-doer.
<lb/>His own time came, his wisdom was estranged,
<pb n="121"/>
<lb/>And I have heard that he grew mad at last,
<milestone unit="calced" n="2095"/>
<lb/>And was so till he slew himself. Well done,
<lb/>Thou still revolving, crook-backed sky! Since then
<lb/>Hath been the epoch of Umar, made known
<lb/>The Faith, and to a pulpit changed the throne.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15"><head>Account of the Completion of the Shahnama</head>
<p>
<lb/>When five and sixty years had passed me by
<lb/>I viewed my task with more anxiety,
<lb/>And as my yearning to achieve it grew
<lb/>My fortune’s star receded from my view.
<lb/>Persians well read and men of high degree
<lb/>Wrote all my work out and would take no fee.
<lb/>I over-looked from far, and thou hadst said
<lb/>That they had rather handselled me instead!
<lb/>Naught but the praises had I for my part,
<lb/>And while they praised I had a broken heart.
<lb/>The mouths of their old money-bags were tied,
<lb/>Whereat mine ardent heart was mortified.
<lb/>Of famous nobles of this town 'Ali,
<lb/>The Dilamite,<note>In Vol. i., p. 35, the names are given according to the reading of BCM.</note> most shared the work with me,
<lb/>For he, a man of ardent temper made,
<lb/>Through kindliness of soul forwent no aid.
<lb/>Husain, son of Kutib, a Persian lord,
<lb/>Asked me for naught without its due reward,
<lb/>But furnished gold and silver, clothes and meat,
<lb/>And found me ways and means, and wings and feet.
<lb/>As for taxation, naught thereof know I;
<lb/>All at mine ease in mine own quilt I lie.
<pb n="122"/>
<lb/>- What time my years attained to ten times seven
<lb/>And one my poetry surmounted heaven.
<lb/>For five and thirty years I bore much pain
<lb/>Here in this Wayside Inn in quest of gain,
<lb/>But all the five and thirty years thus past
<lb/>Naught helped; they gave my travail to the blast,
<lb/>And my hopes too have gone for evermore
<lb/>Now that mine age all but hath reached fourscore.
<lb/>I end the story of Shah Yazdagird,
<lb/>And in Sapandarmad, the day of Ard,
<lb/>And year four hundred of Muhammad’s Flight,
<lb/>The last words of this royal book I write.
<lb/>For ever flourishing be Shah Mahmud,
<lb/>His head still green, his heart with joy imbued.
<lb/>I have so lauded him that publicly
<lb/>And privily my words will never die.
<lb/>Of praises from the Great I had much store;
<lb/>The praises that I give to him are more.
<lb/>May he, the man of wisdom, live for aye,
<lb/>His doings turn to his content alway.
<lb/>This tale of sixty thousand couplets I
<lb/>Have left to him by way of memory.
<milestone unit="calced" n="2096"/>
<lb/>My life from days of youth to eld hath sped
<lb/>In talk and hearkening what others said.
<lb/>When this, my famous tale, was done at last
<lb/>O’er all the realm my reputation passed.
<lb/>All men of prudence, rede, and Faith will give
<lb/>Applause to me when I have ceased to live,
<lb/>Yet live I shall; the seed of words have I
<lb/>Flung broad-cast and henceforth I shall not die.
</p><p>
<lb/>The Shahnama of Firdausi is ended.
</p>
</div>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>